<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="correct_periscope_drift" context="tools"
         refkeywords="aspect solution motion source coordinates astrometry alignment
         correction temporal drift sub-arcsec sub-pixel subarcsec subpixel thermal
         periscope alignment psf"
         seealsogroups="" displayseealsogroups="pixtools asptools">

    <SYNOPSIS>
        Correct a Chandra aspect solution for temporal drift calculated from a fit of the
        drift in the sky positions of the events in a supplied circle region.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
        Thermal cycling on the spacecraft can result in an apparent temporal drift of the sky
        position of an X-ray source during an observation.  This appears as a drift of up to about
        0.5 arcsec in X-ray event sky X, Y coordinates over time.  Because of the thermal
        variation time scales, this effect is usually most prominent in long observations (more
        than about 50 ksec).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        As of DS 8.4, a drift correction is applied to the aspect solution using the periscope
        gradients telemetry.  However, temporal drifts have continued to increase with thermal
        variation of the spacecraft.  Therefore the Aspect team suggests that to accomplish
        science related to sub-arcsec source structure, users should follow this thread to correct
        residual drift induced by the periscope.  This requires a relatively bright, on-axis
        source (within
        a few arcmin off-axis angle) to perform a "self-calibration" of the aspect solution.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This tool takes as input a source aspect solution and event files and returns a
        new/corrected aspect solution that may be applied to the events to correct
        residual temporal drift.
      </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
       <QEXAMPLE>
         <SYNTAX>
           <LINE>
              % correct_periscope_drift 
infile=pcadf537654279N001_asol1.fits.gz 
evtfile=acisf16659N001_evt2.fits.gz 
x=4133.76 
y=4078.74 
radius=6 
outfile=driftcorr_asol1.fits 
verbose=2
           </LINE>
         </SYNTAX>
         <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
Running: correct_periscope_drift
  version = 0.1
with parameters:
  infile=pcadf537654279N001_asol1.fits.gz
  evtfile=acisf16659N001_evt2.fits.gz
  outfile=driftcorr_asol1.fits
  verbose=2
  and ASCDS_INSTALL is /soft/ciao-4.8
------------------------------------------------------------
Fitting a line to the data to get reduced stat errors
Fitting a polynomial of degree 2 to the data
Fitting a line to the data to get reduced stat errors
Fitting a polynomial of degree 2 to the data
------------------------------------------------------------
Fit results
Events show drift range of 0.24 arcsec in yag axis
Max absolute correction of 0.14 arcsec for yag axis
Events show drift range of 0.20 arcsec in zag axis
Max absolute correction of 0.11 arcsec for zag axis
------------------------------------------------------------
Writing out corrected aspect solution file to driftcorr_asol1.fits
To review fit see correction plots in:
corr_fit_yag.png
corr_data_yag.png
corr_fit_zag.png
corr_data_zag.png
</VERBATIM>

         </DESC>
       </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

   <PARAMLIST>
     <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Input Chandra aspect solution.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="evtfile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Input Chandra event file (evt1 or evt2).
       </SYNOPSIS>
       <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The event file should have been made with/processed with the aspect solution
            supplied with infile (evtfile ASOLFILE header key value should match infile)
          </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Output filename for corrected aspect solution file
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="corr_plot_root" type="string" filetype="output" reqd="no" stacks="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Output prefix for fit and data plots.
       </SYNOPSIS>
       <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The output prefix for fit and data plots.  The
            output names will look like ${corr_plot_root}_fit_${axis}.png and
            ${corr_plot_root}_data_${axis}.png where ${axis} will be 'yag' or 'zag'.
          </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="x" type="float" min="1">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Sky X position of center of circle region used to extract events to fit correction.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="y" type="float" min="1">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Sky Y position of center of circle region used to extract events to fit correction.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="radius" type="float" min="0">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Radius in pixels of circle region used to extract events to fit correction.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="src_min_counts" type="float" min="0" def="250">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Minimum number of counts required in extracted source region (below which the
         tool will complain and not fit).
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="corr_poly_degree" type="integer" min="1" max="8" def="2">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Degree of polynomial used in the fit model to fit and correct drift in the two
         Aspect Camera axes.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
       <SYNOPSIS>
        Amount of tool chatter level.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
           Overwrite output files if they already exist?
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

   </PARAMLIST>

   <ADESC title="Caveats">
        <PARA title="Bad fits">
            This tool is provides output plots of the fits of the events.  The user
            must evaluate those plots to determine if a correction is warranted and
            if the output fit is reasonable.  This tool should not be blindly applied
            to observations in aggregate.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Cannot be run headless or without ChIPS">
            The output plots are not optional.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Counts needed for good fit">
            The tool is not intended for short observations (less than 50ks) and
            will not fit observations well without a bright point-like source.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Multiple aspect solutions files">
            This tool is only intended for observations with single aspect solution files.
        </PARA>
   </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2018</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>    
</cxchelptopics>
