<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY pr "chips>">
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="lc_clean" context="contrib"
	 refkeywords="maxim markevitch lightcurve histogram timing time times background variability gti clean filter clip lcclean lclean lc_clean.py"
	 seealsogroups="contrib timingtools cleantools">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      lc_clean - remove periods of high (or low) count rates using the same technique as the ACIS background files
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>
	lc_clean(filename,
	[outfile=None], [mean=None], [clip=3.0], [sigma=None], [scale=1.2], [minfrac=0.1],
	[plot=True], [rateaxis="y"], [pattern="solid"], [gcol="green"], [pcol="red"],
	[verbose=1])
      </LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The lc_clean() routine removes flares (and periods of anomalously-low
	count rates) from lightcurves using the same technique as used
	on the ACIS backgroud files. It is based on the lc_clean program created by
	Maxim Markevitch.
	For more information see the <HREF 
        link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/acisbackground/">Using
        the ACIS "Blank-Sky" Background Files</HREF> thread.
	The deflare tool can be used to run this algorithm from the command
	line; see "ahelp deflare" for more information.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Loading the routine">
        The routine can be loaded into a Python
	interpreter - such as chips, sherpa, or ipython
	- by saying:
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
from lightcurves import *
</VERBATIM>

      <PARA>
	See "ahelp lightcurves" for more information on the lightcurves module.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Common arguments">
	The lc_sigma_clip() and lc_clean() routines share a number of
	common arguments and options.
	The filename argument - which is the only required argument for either
	call - is used to specify the name of the light curve to analyze.
	The required columns for this file are discussed in the
	"Format of Lightcurves" section below.
      </PARA>

      <TABLE>
	<CAPTION>Common options between the three routines (i.e. those with the same meaning)</CAPTION>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>Option</DATA>
	  <DATA>Default</DATA>
	  <DATA>Meaning</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>outfile</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>If set, this gives the name of the GTI file to create.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>verbose</DATA>
	  <DATA>1</DATA>
	  <DATA>Do we display screen output (1) or not (0)?</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>plot</DATA>
	  <DATA>True</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    Should the light curve be displayed as a plot?
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>pattern</DATA>
	  <DATA>solid</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    If a GTI file is created as well as a plot, then we indicate the
	    excluded times using regions filled with this pattern. Valid values
	    are the same as those for region and histograms - see the "Fill Patterns"
	    section of "ahelp chipsopt".
	    A value of "none" means no regions will be drawn.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>rateaxis</DATA>
	  <DATA>"y"</DATA>
	  <DATA>Should the light curve (the top plot)
	  be drawn with the count rate along the y axis ("y") or x axis ("x")?</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>gcol</DATA>
	  <DATA>"green"</DATA>
	  <DATA>The color used to display "good" points when drawing the light curve.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>pcol</DATA>
	  <DATA>"red"</DATA>
	  <DATA>The color used to color regions indicating excluded times (see the
	  pattern argument).</DATA>
	</ROW>
      </TABLE>

      <PARA>
	Although all routines contain an optional sigma argument, the
	meaning of this parameter is not exactly
	the same.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Using lc_clean">
	The lc_clean algorithm was designed to work with 
	the ACIS blank-sky datasets. The routine calculates
	- or is given - a mean rate from which it deduces a 
	minimum and maximum valid count rate.
	Since the calculations assume Poisson statistics
	all the time bins are assumed to have the same
	width (i.e. exposure value).
	For further information see the documentaion linked
	to in the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/acisbackground/">thread</HREF>.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The "mean", "clip", "sigma", "scale", and "minfrac"
	options control the behavior of the routine.
	If mean is set then the value is taken as the initial
	guess, otherwise the level is calculated from the data,
	with outliers clipped using the clip parameter
	(which defaults to 3.0). This is not an iterative
	clipping scheme - as used in lc_sigma_clip() - since the
	variance of the lightcurve is assumed to be
	<EQUATION>var = mean-rate / bin-width</EQUATION>
	Once the mean level has been calculated, the limits
	are given by (if sigma is changed from its default
	value of  None)
	<EQUATION>mean - sigma * sqrt(var)</EQUATION>
	to
	<EQUATION>mean + sigma * sqrt(var)</EQUATION>
	otherwise they are
	<EQUATION>mean / scale</EQUATION>
	to
	<EQUATION>mean * scale</EQUATION>
	where scale defaults to 1.2.
	The minfrac option determines the minimum fraction of
	bins that must remain "good" for the routine to
	finish.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="How do we use the output GTI file?">
	If the outfile argument is set, then a GTI file
	will be created listing those time periods which
	are considered to be "good" by the algorithm.
	This file can be used to filter an event file using
	the following syntax (we assume here that the event file
	to be filtered is evt2.fits and the output of the routine
	is called evt.gti):
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
unix% dmcopy "evt2.fits[@evt.gti]" evt2_filt.fits
</VERBATIM>

      <PARA title="A warning about low count-rate lightcurves">
	The lc_clean algorithm excludes bins which have a zero
	count rate, whether it is because the exposure time
	of the bin is zero or because no counts were detected
	in this bin.
	This is because the algorithm is not designed for use
	with low count-rate data.
	Therefore the routines should be used with 
	extreme care when
	applied to data for which zero-rate bins are
	expected (for example a very-faint source).
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="A note on times">
	When run with verbose set to 1,
	durations are displayed alongside time filters.
	These values are instructive, but should not
	be taken as the actual exposure-length of each interval
	because they may not account for
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
	<ITEM>
	  the dead-time correction of the observation (DTCOR
	  header keyword);
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  exposure variations within the bin due to existing
	  time filters (i.e. the time filters already applied
	  to the observation).
	</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
	The best way to find out what the final exposure time will
	be is to create a GTI file, use it to filter the event file,
	and then look at the EXPOSURE value of the filtered file.
      </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>

      <QEXAMPLE>

	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; lc_clean("bg.lc")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The default parameters are used to analyze the light curve
	    in the file bg.lc. A plot will be created and information about
	    the calculation, including the final filter range, is
	    printed to the screen.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The plot can be printed using the ChIPS print_window command,
	    for example
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; print_window("bg.lc.ps", ["fittopage", True, "orientation", "landscape"])</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    will create a postscript plot which is drawn
	    in landscape format and fills the page.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>

      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>

	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; lc_clean("bg.lc", outfile="clean.gti")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Since the outfile parameter is set, the routine creates
	    a GTI file (clip.gti)
	    that represents the "good" times calculated by the algorithm.
	    After writing out the file the filtered-out times will be displayed
	    on the plot using red cross-hatched regions.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The output file (clean.gti)
	    can be used to filter an event file (say evt2.fits) like
	    so:
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
unix% dmcopy "evt2.fits[@clean.gti]" evt2_filt.fits
</VERBATIM>
	</DESC>

      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>

	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; lc_clean("bg.lc", outfile="bg.gti", pattern="none")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Create a GTI file (bg.gti) but do
	    not use regions to indicate the excluded times in the
	    count-rate plot.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>

      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>

	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; lc_clean("bg.lc", outfile="bg.gti", pattern="crosshatch", pcol="orange")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Create a GTI file (bg.gti) and use
	    an orange cross-hatch fill to indicate the excluded times in the
	    count-rate plot.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>

      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>

	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; lc_clean("bg.lc", outfile="bg.gti", verbose=0, plot=False)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Create a GTI file (bg.gti) but do
	    not create any screen output or a plot.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>

      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <ADESC title="Format of Lightcurves">
      <PARA>
	The lc_clean routine is designed to work with light curves that were
	created using the CIAO dmextract tool, run with the opt parameter set
	to ltc1. They should however also work with any file which has the 
	following columns:
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>TIME</ITEM>
	<ITEM>TIME_MIN and TIME_MAX (both columns are optional)</ITEM>
	<ITEM>COUNT_RATE or, if not present, RATE</ITEM>
	<ITEM>EXPOSURE</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	If the file contains OBJECT and OBS_ID keywords then these will be
	used to label the plot.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/lightcurves.html">bugs page
        for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
        listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2018</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
