<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="tg_bkg" context="tools" refkeywords="xspec background backscal" seealsogroups="tgtools"> 
    <SYNOPSIS>
      Creates a PHA background file for use in XSPEC
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <SYNTAX>
        <LINE>tg_bkg input_pha2.fits [output_bkg_pha2.fits]</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
        tg_bkg makes a background file that is compatible with
	XSPEC.  Sherpa will be able to use it, but that application
	can already read the arrays directly from the PHA file. The
	script sums the BACKGROUND_UP and BACKGROUND_DOWN columns and
	adjusts the scale factor keyword (BACKSCAL) accordingly. Since
	it is designed to keep the same format as the PHA file,
	i.e. the rows in both files correspond to one another, it is a
	more convenient way of inspecting the background.  
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        Note that since the script updates the BACKFILE keyword, the
	input file must have write permission.  If an output file name
	is not specified, the script uses the input file name with
	"_bkg" appended. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        It is important to note that these are estimates to the
	background. Since they are binned adjacent to the spectrum
	source region, they will have a contribution from the wings of
	the PSF. They also have a contribution from signal aliased in
	chipy during the frame shift at the level of (usually) 41 ms
	frame shift / 3200 ms integration / 1024 rows, or 1.25e-5 times
	the source rate (HEG+MEG or LEG, all orders). The source count
	rate at that diffraction angle gets smeared during the frame
	shift. 
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>

      <SYNTAX>
        <LINE>
	  tg_bkg acisf0145N003_pha2.fits acisf0145N003_bkg_pha2.fits
        </LINE>
      </SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Create a background file for ObsID 145.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>

      <SYNTAX>
        <LINE>
	  tg_bkg acisf00459N002_pha2.fits 
        </LINE>
      </SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Create a background file for ObsID 459.  Since an output
	    filename is not given, tg_bkg creates
	    "acisf00459N002_pha2.fits_bkg". 
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/tg_bkg.html">bugs page
        for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
        listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2018</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>

