<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="acis_check_pha_range" context="tools"
         refkeywords="acis mask energy filter pha pha_ro phas cti calibration onorbit orbit flight grade bias"
         seealsogroups="acistools">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Compute approximate energy range for on-orbit PHA filter. 
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
        <PARA>
        All ACIS observations use an on-orbit PHA filter.  The 
        values used on orbit are stored in the Level 1 mask file, 
        *_msk1.fits: PHAMIN and PHAMAX  column values.
        The default filter used by most observations retains event 
        with energies in the approximately the 0.2 to 14 keV range.        
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        However, observers may request an arbitrary energy filter.
        The only advantage to using an energy filter is when the 
        expected count rate in the field would be near the telemetry
        saturation limit.  Nonetheless, there are numerous observations
        which specify an energy filter with low count fields.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        The problem is that observers specify a filter in energy units (keV).
        The actual filtering on orbit is done on the events' Pulse Height
        Amplitude (PHA), in ADU (engineering) units.  The on orbit
        PHA value differs from the PHA value computed by acis_process_events
        since it does not include CTI corrections.  
        The on-orbit PHA value is closest to the PHA_RO (PHA Read Out) 
        value in the event list.  As a result, the 
        gain conversion from on-orbit PHA_RO to observed ENERGY 
        varies spatially (due to CTI and node-to-node gain settings),
        varies with energy (gain is non-linear with energy), and
        varies with time (short term CTI temperature dependent effects
        and long term time adjustments).
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        The purpose of this script then is to compute an estimated gain
        based on the actual observed event data, and use it to 
        compute an approximate energy range where all events were 
        telemetered.  Users should then ensure that the energy range
        used in their analysis (eg, energy range used when 
        fitting spectrum) falls within these limits.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Description of Algorithm">
            
        This tool works by ignoring the temporal and spectral (non-linear)
        gain variations.  It computes a gain map (eV/ADU) in CHIP coordinates
        by computing the mean ENERGY/PHA_RO of the events in 
        128x128 blocks (default binsize).  It then applies these gain 
        values to the PHA_RO limits obtained from the level1 mask: 
        PHAMIN and PHAMAX column values.  The maximum, low energy
        and the minimum, high energy values are then a conservative,
        approximate set of energy limits.    
         This algorithm is described in greater detail in the 
        <HREF link="https://cxc.cfa.harvard.edu/ciao/why/acis_energy_filter.html">Understanding ACIS on-orbit energy filters</HREF>
        why topic.
        </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
       <QEXAMPLE>
         <SYNTAX>
           <LINE>unix% acis_check_pha_range 5705/primary/acisf05705N003_evt2.fits.gz 
           </LINE>
         </SYNTAX>
         <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
acis_check_pha_range
          infile = 5705/primary/acisf05705N003_evt2.fits.gz
         mskfile = 
         binsize = 128
         verbose = 1
            mode = ql

Using maskfile: '5705/secondary/acisf05705_000N003_msk1.fits'
Processing data for CCD_ID=2
Processing data for CCD_ID=3
Processing data for CCD_ID=5
Processing data for CCD_ID=6
Processing data for CCD_ID=7
Processing data for CCD_ID=8
#ccd_id	pha_lo	pha_hi	E_lo	E_hi
2	39	2499	 192.1	  9383.1
3	39	2499	 191.3	  9892.4
5	26	2499	 127.6	 10808.6
6	39	2499	 202.8	  9642.1
7	26	2499	 128.9	 11380.3
8	39	2499	 202.8	 10662.5

Conservative limits are 202.8 to 9383.1 eV
</VERBATIM>
<PARA>
This example shows the results for OBSID 5705.  The observation used
a non-standard high energy threshold.  The requested cutoff, as reported by
ChaSER, was 10keV.  However, due to gain corrections on different chips, 
the energy cutoff on CCD_ID 2 is **approximately** 9.4 keV.
</PARA>
         </DESC>
       </QEXAMPLE>
    


       <QEXAMPLE>
         <SYNTAX>
           <LINE>
unix% acis_check_pha_range 5705/primary/acisf05705N003_evt2.fits.gz bin=32
           </LINE>
         </SYNTAX>
         <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
acis_check_pha_range
          infile = 5705/primary/acisf05705N003_evt2.fits.gz
         mskfile = 
         binsize = 32
         verbose = 1
            mode = ql

Using maskfile: '5705/secondary/acisf05705_000N003_msk1.fits'
Processing data for CCD_ID=2
Processing data for CCD_ID=3
Processing data for CCD_ID=5
Processing data for CCD_ID=6
Processing data for CCD_ID=7
Processing data for CCD_ID=8
#ccd_id	pha_lo	pha_hi	E_lo	E_hi
2	39	2499	 306.9	  9192.8
3	39	2499	 310.1	  9812.4
5	26	2499	 264.6	 10759.3
6	39	2499	 326.2	  9561.1
7	26	2499	 208.1	 11232.7
8	39	2499	 305.6	 10591.7

Conservative limits are 326.2 to 9192.8 eV
</VERBATIM> 
<PARA>
The same as the previous example but now using a smaller bin size.
Since this observation contains a low number of counts, the mean 
gain value in each bin is somewhat sensitive to the binsize. 
The approximate low energy threshold has changed from 0.2 to 0.36keV.
</PARA>


         </DESC>
       </QEXAMPLE>
       <QEXAMPLE>
         <SYNTAX>
           <LINE>
unix% acis_check_pha_range 2785/primary/acisf02785N003_evt2.fits.gz 
           </LINE>
         </SYNTAX>
         <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
acis_check_pha_range
          infile = 2785/primary/acisf02785N003_evt2.fits.gz
         mskfile = 
         binsize = 128
         verbose = 1
            mode = ql

Using maskfile: '2785/secondary/acisf02785_000N003_msk1.fits'
Processing data for CCD_ID=2
Processing data for CCD_ID=3
Processing data for CCD_ID=5
Processing data for CCD_ID=6
Processing data for CCD_ID=7
Processing data for CCD_ID=8
#ccd_id	pha_lo	pha_hi	E_lo	E_hi
2	126	3124	 554.6	 11794.5
3	126	3124	 592.9	 12370.8
5	126	3124	 613.8	 13579.9
6	126	3124	 602.3	 12109.2
7	126	3124	 622.8	 14141.2
8	126	3124	 640.2	 13332.6

Conservative limits are 640.2 to 11794.5 eV
</VERBATIM>
           <PARA>
OBSIS 2785 is an example were a low energy threshold was requested.
The requested threshold was 0.5keV.  Based on the approximate gain
maps, the minimum safe energy (above which we expect to have 
received all events) is closer to 0.64 keV.
           </PARA>         
         </DESC>
       </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

   <PARAMLIST>
     <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
         Input ACIS Level 2 event file.
       </SYNOPSIS>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
            The level 2 event file.  Users should not use the Level 1
            event file since the bad grades and bad pixels 
            lead to different gain estimates.  
         </PARA>

       </DESC>     
     </PARAM>
   
    <PARAM name="mskfile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>
        The ACIS mask file
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The mask file, *_msk1.fits, for the observation.  If left
            blank, the tool will attempt to locate the file specified
            in the MASKFILE keyword in the event file.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>    
    </PARAM>


    <PARAM name="binsize" type="integer" def="128">
      <SYNOPSIS>
      Block size in chip coordinates used to estimate the gain.
      </SYNOPSIS>
      <DESC>
        <PARA>
        The gain is estimated by computing the mean ENERGY/PHA_RO for the
        events in 128x128 blocks (in chip coordinates).  Since it is
        computing an average, a large number of events is required to get
        a meaningful estimate. For observations
        with large number of events, the binsize can be decreased to 
        better capture the spatial variation across the detector.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        Since the mean gain must not be compute across node boundaries,
        the binsize is restricted to the following values: 1,2,4,8,16,32,64,128,256.
        </PARA>     
      </DESC>
    </PARAM>



     <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
       <SYNOPSIS>
        Amount of tool chatter level.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

   </PARAMLIST>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/acis_check_pha_range.html">bug
        pages</HREF>on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2020</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>    
</cxchelptopics>
