<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY context="tools::statistics" key="aplimits" refkeywords="poisson net count rate flux
  background psf fraction average exposure upper limit" seealsogroups="stattools">
    <SYNOPSIS>
      Compute upper limits for the detection of a source, using data
      obtained from background apertures in event lists, images,
      and exposure maps.
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
        The aplimits tool estimates the upper limit for a detection. This is a
        property of the detection process and depends on the values chosen for
        two error conditions: First, the maximum probability of a false detection (false
        positive), i.e. that a background fluctuation alone exceeds the
        calculated upper limit, and second the probability that
        a source with a flux of exactly the upper limit will be missed (false
        negative), because Poisson fluctuation of background and source counts
        lead to an observed count rate that is below the detection limit. The
        value of the upper limit depends only on the background rate and the
        probabilities chosen for the two errors, not on the observed
        number of counts in the source region. All input is obtained from the
        input parameter file; output is written to an output parameter file.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        It is possible to find combinations of parameters that numerically
        result in a negative upper limit. Since this does not make sense
        physically, 0 is reported as the upper limit in these cases.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        If the background rate is not known exactly, it can be estimated from
        the number of counts in a large source-free background region. In this
        case, the true background rate is not known, and a Bayesian computation
        needs to marginalize over the possible background rates. To perform this
        computation, one needs to set a prior on the background count rate. This
        tool uses an uninformative prior expressed as a Gamma distribution which
        represents an prior knowledge of 0 counts in 0 area. This uninformative
        prior is an "improper" prior, which means that it cannot be normalized.
        However, the gamma distribution is the conjugate prior for this process
        and thus the posterior for the background rate can be calculated
        analytically given the number of observed background counts. The
        functional form for the posterior is the same as for aprates.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This tool is based on the following article:
        <HREF link="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2010ApJ...719..900K">On computing upper limits to source intensities</HREF>
        (Kashyap et al. 2010, ApJ, 719, 900).
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="User inputs">
        This tool can either assume perfect knowledge of the background; in this
        case the parameter bkg_rate must be set. Alternatively, the user can set
        the number of counts m in the background region, and, unless source and
        background region have the same area and exposure time, also set the the
        geometric areas (A_s, A_b) and respective exposure times (T_s, T_b). If
        both bkg_rate and m are given, the tool assumes that the background rate
        is known and ignores the setting for m.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Return values">
       Output is written to an output parameter file. The parameter files
       contains two values: min_counts_detect, which is the minimum number of
       counts in the source region that is needed to claim a detection, and
       upper_limit, which is the upper limit on the count rate (counts per time)
       for a non-detection. Note that the upper limit is given for the entire
       source region and not normalized to the source area. In a typical case of
       a point source, the source aperture should be large enough to include
       most of the PSF and then the upper limit can be interpreted as the upper
       limit on the source flux. For an extended source, the upper limit applies
       to the part of the extended source that is covered by the source
       aperture.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Things to Watch Out For:"></PARA>
      <PARA title="1.) Extracting Aperture Quantities">
        A number of different CIAO tools can be used to determine the area and
        number of events in apertures. These tools may yield slightly different
        results, depending on whether one starts with an event list or image.
        Results from event lists are more accurate, since event locations are
        typically known to finer resolution that a pixel size, and areas can be
        determined analytically for simple apertures. For images, aperture
        counts and areas are determined from those pixels whose centers fall
        within the aperture. We recommend the use of dmextract if an event list
        is available.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        Unfortunately, determination of effective exposure and psf fractions in
        apertures will almost always require the use of exposure map and psf
        images, leading to possible inaccuracies in the determination of these
        quantities. For apertures containing many image pixels, this is a
        negligible effect, because exposure maps typically vary smoothly, and
        thus inclusion or exclusion of particular exposure map pixels has little
        effect on the average in the aperture. Similarly, the psf fraction
        change due to inclusion or exclusion of a few pixels at the aperture
        edge is likely to be small.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This will not be the case, however, if aperture sizes are small compared
        to image pixel sizes. In those cases, it is recommended that the user
        repixelate the psf and exposure map images to a finer scale.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This tool itself does not account for the fraction of the PSF that falls
        outside the source aperture, but one can divide the resulting upper flux
        limit by the PSF fraction in the aperture to estimate the upper limit on
        the count rate.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="2.) Upper limit on a detection vs. credible interval for the flux">
        This tool calculates the upper limit on the source flux, given
        properties of the detection method (type I and II errors and source
        region size and exposure time) and background level. This calculation is valid 
	      for all source regions in an observation (assuming a smooth
        background and constant exposure time). This is conceptually different
        from aprates, which instead looks at the source count rate in one
        specific region and then derives the credible interval for the flux of a
        source at one specific region. For undetected or weak sources, the
        credible interval includes 0 and sometimes the upper end of the interval
        is taken as upper limit on the source flux. That is not mathematically
        correct, since "upper limit" and "upper end of credible interval"
        describe different statistical concepts, even though the derived
        numbers can be similar; see
        <HREF link="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2010ApJ...719..900K">Kashyap et al. (2010)</HREF>
        for a more detailed discussion.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="3.) What are the units for area and exposure time?">
        To calculate the upper limit, the tool needs to know the number of expected
        background counts in the source area. Because of that the formulas do not
        depend directly on the exposure time or aperture area.
        Instead, the source aperture area is
        only used to get the number of expected background counts (if bkg_rate is given)
        or the ratio to the background area (if the number of counts m in the background
        aperture is given). So, it is sufficient to use consistent units for areas,
        e.g., A_s and A_b can be given in pixels or arcsec^2, so long as both numbers
        use the same units (and if source and background aperture are the same size,
        they can both be left at their default 1.0).
        Similarly, bkg_rate can be "per pixel" or "per arcsec^2" as long as the unit
        is consistent with A_s.
        The same is true for the units of exposure time:
        T_s and bkg_rate (or T_b) just need to be
        consistent and the output will be in the same time unit.
        If T_s is given in seconds, then the upper limit will be returned as counts/sec;
        but one can also use "exposure time" as the unit:
        if T_s and T_b are left at the default of 1.0 (or bkg_rate is "counts over the
        entire observation"), then the upper limit will be in
        "counts over the entire observation".
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="4.) Incomplete PSF in source aperture">
        The calculation of the upper limit is done in counts. If the source aperture does not cover
        the full PSF, it will only apply to that fraction of the PSF, e.g., if A_s only
        include 90% of the PSF, then the resulting upper limit is a limit on 90% of the
        source flux; in other words, the limit on the full source flux is upper_limit/0.9.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>unix% aplimits prob_false_detection=.05 prob_missed_detection=.5 bkg_rate=1.23 outfile=aplimits_out.par</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% pget aplimits_out.par upper_limit</LINE>
          <LINE>2.44206</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% pget aplimits_out.par min_counts_detect</LINE>
          <LINE>3</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
      In this example, we know the background rate and calculate the upper limit
      on the source count rate (in cts/s).
      We want the probability for a background fluctuation to
      appear as a source to be less than 5%, and we want the probability to miss
      a real source with a flux comparable to the upper limit to be below 50%.
      We do not set the source extraction area and exposure time. Both default to 1.
      So, we can interpret the resulting number as source flux per unit time.
      However, the calculation of the limits does not directly depend on the exposure
      time; it is really just about the number of counts. It also does not depend directly
      on A_s, that is only needed to calculate the number of expected background counts.
      The defaults for exposure time and area are 1.0 for each value. So, we can also view
      this example as follows: We expect 1.23 background counts in the source area
      over the entire exposure time and and the upper limit to the source flux is
      2.44206 counts over the entire exposure time.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>unix% aplimits prob_false_detection=.1 prob_missed_detection=.5 bkg_rate=INDEF m=5 A_b=4.065 outfile=aplimits_out.par</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% pget aplimits_out.par upper_limit</LINE>
          <LINE>2.2316</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
    If the background rate is not known exactly (bkg_rate set to INDEF), the
    tool can marginalize over all possible background rates given the
    information on a single background measurement. With 5 counts in the
    background aperture and a region that is about 4.065 times larger than the
    source aperture, one might naively expect a background count rate of
    5/4.065=1.23. However, given Poisson statistics, the true background rate
    could be higher or lower and thus the resulting upper limit is about 10%
    smaller than in the first example. When the background is measured better
    (more counts in a larger background area) the difference between the
    calculation for a perfectly known background and marginalizing over the
    background rate is even smaller.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>unix% aplimits prob_false_detection=.05 prob_missed_detection=.5 bkg_rate=0.34 A_b=1 T_b=1 outfile=aplimits_out.par</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% pget aplimits_out.par upper_limit</LINE>
          <LINE>1.338348388671875</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% aplimits prob_false_detection=.05 prob_missed_detection=.5 bkg_rate=0.34 A_b=10 T_b=23 clobber+ outfile=aplimits_out.par</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% pget aplimits_out.par upper_limit</LINE>
          <LINE>1.338348388671875</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
          The background rate is given per unit are and unit time, so changing
          the background area and exposure time has no effect on the results
          when a background rate is input.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="prob_false_detection" type="real" min="0" max="1" def="0.1" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	        Upper limit for the probability of a false detection
	      </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The probability of a type I error describes the possibility a background
            fluctuation alone causes an observed count rate above the detection threshold.
	        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="prob_missed_detection" type="real" min="0" max="1" def="0.5" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	        Probability of detecting a source with a flux equal to the upper limit
	      </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The probability of a type II error describes the possibility that a
            true source with a flux of the upper limit will be missed in the
            detection because the Poisson fluctuations of the source and
            background flux lead to a count number below the detection
            threshold.
	        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	        Filename of output file
	      </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="T_s" type="real" min="0" def="1" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Exposure time in source aperture
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
      This is given in the same units as exposure time of the background T_b.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="A_s" type="real" min="0" def="1" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Geometric area of source aperture
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
      This is given in the same units as geometric area of the background A_b.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="bkg_rate" type="real" min="0" def="INDEF">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Background count rate
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
        Known background rate. The flux is given per area and time. The unit of
        the area must match the units used for A_s. When the exact background
        rate is not known, bkg_rate has to be set to INDEF. In that case, the
        number of observed background counts m has to be provided, so that the
        tools can marginalize over the background rate.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="m" type="integer" min="0">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Number of counts in background aperture
	  </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="T_b" type="real" min="0" def="1">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Exposure time in background aperture
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
      This is given in the same units as exposure time of the source T_s.
      This parameter is only used if bkg_rate is not given.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="A_b" type="real" min="0" def="1">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Geometric area of background aperture
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
      This is given in the same units as geometric area of the source A_s.
      This parameter is only used if bkg_rate is not given.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="max_counts" type="integer" min="0" def="50">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Background count number above which the uncertainty on the background is ignored
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    When the background count rate is not know exactly, the tool performs a Bayesian
      computation and marginalizes over the background. In particular for a large number
      of counts, this computation can take a long time or be numerically unstable.
      On the other hand, when the number of counts in the background is large, that means
      that the uncertainty on the background flux is small and there is little difference
      between the full Bayesian computation and assuming a known background rate.
      When the number of background counts m becomes larger than max_counts, then the
      tool switches from the Bayesian computation to the a faster and more numerically
      stable formula for an exactly known background rate of m divided by the
      area and exposure time of the background exposure.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="maxfev" type="integer" min="1" def="500">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Maximal number of function evaluations in numerical root finding
	  </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    Verbose level
	  </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    If set to a non-zero value then the tool will print information to the
	    screen when it is run. The extra information produced when verbose is
	    greater than 1 is only likely to be useful when debugging the script.
	    </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	    OK to overwrite existing output file?
	  </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
	made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>
        .
	Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
	ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        For an up-to-date listing of known bugs, see the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/aplimits.html">bugs page
        for this tool.</HREF>
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <LASTMODIFIED>October 2022</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
