<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY upr "unix&#37;">

 <!ENTITY verdate "12 November 2015">
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <!--* seealsogroups is pretty random here *-->
  <ENTRY key="apply_fov_limits" context="tools" 
	 refkeywords="limit limits sky region bound bounding box
		      filter filtering dmfilter xygrid fov field view
		      fieldofview sky apply copy bin grid" 
	 seealsogroups="bintools fovtools">
    <SYNOPSIS>Create an image that matches the FOV file for the observation</SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The apply_fov_limits tool takes an event file and creates
	an image from it in SKY coordinates, calculating the limits
        from the Field-Of-View (FOV) file for the observation.
	The default mode is to create the FOV based on the aspect
        solution of the observation, filtered by the GTI of the
	event file, but a FOV file can also be given.
	It is essentially get_fov_limits followed by a dmcopy
	call; the 
        <HREF
	    link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/get_fov_limits.html">help
	file for get_fov_limits</HREF>
        describes how the limits are calculated.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Thread">
	See the 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/match_binning/">Match 
	  the Binning of an Image thread</HREF>
	on the CIAO web site for more information.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>
    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; apply_fov_limits evt2.fits img.fits</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The tool creates the file img.fits, which is an image of
	    the data in evt2.fits, binned to cover the spatial extent
	    of the observation. The default binning is used (8 pixels
	    for ACIS and 32 for HRC) and, as no Data Model filters
	    were applied to the event file, all the data will be
	    included in the output image.
	    For an example ACIS-S dataset, the output is
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
Running: apply_fov_limits
  version: &verdate;
Observation: ObsId 5437 - ACIS-235678
Using ccd_id=2,3,5,6,7,8 from evt2.fits
Calculating FOV file using:
  Aspect solution pcadf233357758N003_asol1.fits
  Mask file       acisf05437_000N003_msk1.fits

The output image will have 322 by 529 pixels, pixel size of 3.936 arcsec,
    and cover x=2160.5:4736.5:8,y=2192.5:6424.5:8.

Created: img.fits
</VERBATIM>

	  <PARA>
	    Note that the aspect solution and mask file have been
	    automatically identified from the header of the event file.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; apply_fov_limits "repro/acisf05437_repro_evt2.fits[ccd_id=7]" \</LINE>
	  <LINE>chip7.img bin=1</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we restrict the event file to ACIS-S3 only, and
	    reduce the bin size to 1, which changes the output image
            sky range and number of pixels compared to the first example.
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
Running: apply_fov_limits
  version: &verdate;
Observation: ObsId 5437 - ACIS-235678
Using ccd_id=7 from repro/acisf05437_repro_evt2.fits[ccd_id=7]
Calculating FOV file using:
  Aspect solution repro/pcadf233357758N003_asol1.fits
  Mask file       repro/acisf05437_000N003_msk1.fits

The output image will have 1102 by 1102 pixels, pixel size of 0.492 arcsec,
    and cover x=3529.5:4631.5:1,y=3238.5:4340.5:1.

Created: chip7.img
</VERBATIM>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; apply_fov_limits "evt2.fits[energy=500:900,ccd_id=7]" \</LINE>
          <LINE>chip7.img bin=1 verbose=0</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example an energy filter has also been applied.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; apply_fov_limits evt2.fits img.out fovfile=fov.fits</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example the FOV file is explicitly given, rather
	    than created by the script from the aspect solution and
	    mask file.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; dmcopy "evt2.fits[sky=region(src.reg)]" src.fits</LINE>
	  <LINE>&upr; apply_fov_limits src.fits src.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Since the event file sent to apply_fov_limits has already
	    been filtered, then the output image area is determined by
	    the intersection of the existing spatial filter with those
	    from the FOV file.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="infile" type="string" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Input event file
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The event file to bin up. Use
            <HREF
		link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/dmfiltering.html">Data
	    Model filters</HREF> to select the required rows, such
            as a chip and energy filter:
	    <EQUATION>evt2.fits[ccd_id=0:3,energy=500:7000]</EQUATION>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Note that if the event file has been spatially filtered,
	    then this information - taken from the 
	    <HREF
		link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/subspace.html">data
	    subspace of the file</HREF> - will be combined with the
	    filter from the FOV file. This means that the output image
	    may not cover the full chip area.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="outfile" type="string" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Output image
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The name of the image created by this script.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="binsize" type="real" def="INDEF" min="0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Image binning factor
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    When set to INDEF a default value is used: 
	    8 for ACIS data and 32 for HRC data.
	    The binning factor has units of the 
	    SKY pixel (0.492" for ACIS and 0.1318" for HRC),
	    so binsize=4 for an ACIS observation will create
	    images with 1.968 arcsecond pixels.
	    The value need not be an integer, and can be less
	    than 1 if you want to look at small-scale structure near
	    the aim point of the observation; in this case it is strongly
	    suggested that a ccd_id filter is used to ensure
	    manageable file sizes.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>    
      <PARAM name="fovfile" type="file">
	<SYNOPSIS>
          Input FOV file
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the parameter is not empty then it gives the name of the FOV
	    file to use; this can either be generated using
            skyfov or the *fov1.fits from the archive used.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    If the parameter is empty then the 
	    ASOLFILE and MASKFILE keywords in the 
	    event file (the infile parameter) will be 
	    used to find the aspect solution and mask file,
	    and these are then passed to the skyfov tool
            to create a FOV file (with the aspect solution being
            time filtered to match the GTI of the event file).
	    Note that the file, or files, pointed to by the 
	    ASOLFILE are required but the MASKFILE is optional;
	    a warning will be displayed if it can not be found,
	    and the full chip size will be used in calculating the
	    bounding box.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="tmpdir" type="string" def="${ASCDS_WORK_PATH}">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Directory for temporary files. 
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Directory for storing temporary files that
	    require further processing before becoming useful.
	    If the directory does not exist then it will be created
	    for use by the script, and then deleted.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  OK to overwrite existing output file?
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Verbose level
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If set to a non-zero value then the tool will
	    print information to the screen when it is run.
	    The extra information prduced when verbose is greater than 1
	    is only likely to be useful when debugging the script.
	  </PARA>
          <PARA>
            The script version is displayed when the verbose parameter is set
            to 1 or higher.
          </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.1 (December 2015) release">
      <PARA>
        The code has been updated to avoid warning messages from
        NumPy version 1.9. There is no difference to how the
        script behaves.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.7.2 (April 2015) release">
      <PARA>
	The output image is no-longer created with the dmcopy option=all
	parameter, which means that some of the metadata of the output
	file (such as position of the image block and the subspace of
	the file) may change. This should make no difference for
	most uses of the output image.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.7.1 (December 2014) release">
      <PARA title="The mask file is now optional">
	The script will now no-longer exit if the file pointed to by
	the MASKFILE keyword in the infile can not be found; instead,
	a warning will be displayed as resulting bounds may be too
	large (for example, if a sub-array was used).  This is only
	relevant when the fovfile parameter is not set.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
	This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
	made available as "contributed" software via the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
	Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
	ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

   <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/get_fov_limits.html">bugs page
        for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
        listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>November 2015</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
