<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY context="tools::region" key="bkg_fixed_counts" 
        refkeywords="region background counts snr constant exclude source" 
        seealsogroups="regiontools">
    <SYNOPSIS>
        Create a background region with a fixed number of counts
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
        <PARA>
            'bkg_fixed_counts' will create a annular background region at each
            input source position that encloses a minimum number of counts.
            The inner annulus radius is determined from the size of the PSF
            at that location, which encloses the inner_ecf fraction of the PSF
            at the specified value of energy.  Users can specify a 
            maximum radius to keep the background region from becoming
            too large (and thus possibly becoming non-representative
            of the source region).
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
            The background excludes other overlapping inner_ecf regions. 
            If the src_region's are specified, the background regions will
            also exclude those source regions.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
          The background is also bound by the input fovfile which
          is needed if any of the regions intersect the edge of the detector.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
          The output will be one file for each input source position.  The
          output will be a FITS region file (in physical coords, as all FITS region files are).
          The output file names will look like ${outroot}_i${src_number}_bkg.reg, where
          outroot is the user supplied output root file name, and src_number is the 
          source number matching the input positions (going from 1 to N,
          where N is the number of positions).
        </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>% bkg_fixed_counts infile=acis_evt.fits outroot=my_catalog pos=my_catalog.fits min_counts=100
          </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            This will create annular background regions centered at each RA and Dec 
            position from the input table: my_catalog.fits.  Each 
            background region will include 100 counts (as determined from
            the input event file: acis_evt.fits), and will be written out
            into individual FITS region files my_catalog_${n}_bkg.reg;
            where ${n} is the row number in the input catalog.
            The inner radius of the annulus will be computed as
            as the radius of a circle that encloses 95% of PSF at 1.0keV (default parameters).
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>% bkg_fixed_counts infile=acis_evt.fits"[energy=500:7000]" outroot=my_catalog pos=my_catalog.fits min_counts=100
          </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
              Same as the previous example, but only consider events in the 
              energy range from 500 to 7000 eV.              
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>% bkg_fixed_counts infile=acis_evt.fits outroot=my_catalog pos=my_catalog.fits min_counts=100 \
            </LINE><LINE>
              energy=2.0 inner_ecf=0.98 max_radius=128
          </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            Same as Example 1, but the inner radius will be the size of the PSF
            at 2.0keV that encloses 98% of the PSF.  Also, there is an 128 pixel outer
            radius threshold applied; that is the maximum radius allowed, meaning 
            that there may be some regions with fewer than 100 counts.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>% bkg_fixed_counts infile=acis_evt.fits outroot=my_catalog pos=my_catalog.fits min_counts=100 \
          </LINE>
          <LINE>
              src_region=@my_catalog_src.lis 
            </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>where the input stack: my_catalog_src.lis looks like
          </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
% cat my_catalog_src.lis
my_catalog_i0001_src.reg
my_catalog_i0002_src.reg
my_catalog_i0003_src.reg
my_catalog_i0004_src.reg
</VERBATIM>

<PARA>
This is similar to Example 1, but now a stack of source region files has been provided.
These source regions will also be excluded from the background regions, in addition to the
inner 95% ECF region.
</PARA>


        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>% bkg_fixed_counts infile=acis_evt.fits outroot=my_catalog pos="12.34,-56.789" min_counts=100
          </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            This is similar to Example 1, except a single source position has been
            specified in decimal degrees.  The pos parameter can also be specfied
            in color-separated sexagesimal format, eg "12:34:56.7 -8:9:10.11".
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>



    </QEXAMPLELIST>


    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM filetype="input" name="infile" reqd="yes" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
          The input event file.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The input event file is used to determine the number
            of counts in the background region.  Users can filter
            the background event file if they wish to only consider
            events in certain energy bands.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM filetype="output" name="outroot" reqd="yes" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            The root of the output file names
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
            If the output root contains a directory, then that directory
            must already exist.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM filetype="input" name="pos" reqd="yes" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            Input position.  
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The input position can either be a pair of celestial coordinates
            or can be a table with RA and DEC columns.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM  name="min_counts" type="integer" def="10" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
          The target minimum number of counts in the background region
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The minimum number of counts may not be met if the 
                user specifies a value for the max_radius parameter.                
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
                The user may also see small differences in the
                number of background counts when filtering an image
                vs filtering an event file.            
            </PARA>
            
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="src_region" type="file" filetype="input" stacks="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            A stack of source regions to exclude.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
                In addition to excluding the inner ECF PSF fraction radius,
                users can exclude source regions from the background.
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
              The input stack can also contain other regions that the
              users wishes to exclude such as for the readout streak.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="fovfile" type="file" filetype="input">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            Field-of-view file name
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The background regions will be intersected with the 
                FOV region if supplied.  It is necessary to include the FOV 
                when the background regions intersect the edge of the detector to ensure 
                that the area of the region can be computed correctly.  
                Otherwise the FOV file does not affect how the background
                region is created.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>




      <PARAM name="max_radius" def="INDEF" type="real" units="pixels">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            The maximum allowed outer radius, in pixels.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The background region should be located close to
                the source region.  However, for low count observations
                the background radius needed to obtain the requested
                number of background counts may grow very large.  If this
                parameter is set, then it will limit the outer radius size
                to this value.
            </PARA>
            <PARA>Setting this parameter to 'INDEF' removes any
            limit on the background radius.</PARA>

        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="inner_ecf" def="0.95" min="0.9" max="0.99" type="real">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            The PSF ECF size to use for the inner annulus radius.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
        <PARA>
            The background region is an annulus located at the source
            position.  The inner radius is obtained by finding the
            size of the PSF at that location which encloses this fraction
            of the PSF at the specified energy.  The outer radius then
            is computed to enclose the specified minimum number of counts.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>

      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="energy" def="1.0" min="0.3" max="10.0" type="real" units="keV">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            The energy used for the PSF size lookup, in units of keV.
        </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>    

    <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
       <SYNOPSIS>
        Amount of tool chatter level.
       </SYNOPSIS>
     </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            Overwrite output files if they already exist?
        </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>

    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Changes in scripts 4.16.1 (April 2024) release">
      <PARA>
        Fixed an issue when the stack of input source regions contains
        empty/NULL regions; for example when a source region is
        entirely outside the field-of-view. 
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


  <ADESC title="Changes in scripts 4.15.2 (April 2023) release">
    <PARA>
      Internal rework of coordinate parsing.
    </PARA>  
  </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Relation to acis_extract">
      <PARA>
        This script is inspired by the acis_extract tool developed by the
        ACIS IPI team at PSU.  
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


   <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/psf_contour.html">bug
        pages</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    
    <LASTMODIFIED>March 2024</LASTMODIFIED>


  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
