<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY pr "unix&#37;">
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="clean_spec" context="Tools::Composite"
	 refkeywords=" crisscross spectrum spectra pha gratings HETG spectral-extraction cleaning confusion orders ARF"
	 seealsogroups="gratings, tgextract, resptools">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Helper tool for CIAO contrib tool crisscross and used for removing spectral confusion from HETG spectra observed 
      in fields with multiple, bright X-ray sources. This tool is currently only used with crisscross output files.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>

      <PARA>
	  CrissCross and its helper tool clean_spec allow users to analyze Chandra High Energy Transmission Grating (HETG) 
      spectra that are extracted from a field of view with multiple other astrophysical X-ray sources. The HETG 
      instrument will disperse events onto the ACIS CCDs from all sources in a field of view and if there are several 
      sufficiently-bright X-ray sources then there is a potential for 'confusion' to occur. Confusion is a term used 
      here for special scenarios where <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/gspec.html">standard HETG 
      spectral extraction</HREF> of a source may erroneously assign events (counts) from a different astrophysical 
      source in the field of view to the extracted source. This can result in events from an unrelated astrophyscal 
      source 'confusing' the spectrum of an extracted source.	
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      CrissCross is used to identify where spectral confusion occurs for a list of input sources (or a single source) 
      and generates 'confusion tables' which identify the wavelength in each source's spectrum that are likely to 
      include X-ray events from unrelated field astrophysical sources. The user can then run clean_spec to deal with all events from the source spectrum in the wavelength range where this confusion occurs. The CrissCross helper program clean_spec uses the CrissCross output confusion tables and input HETG PHA spectra to generate 'cleaned' spectra and matching ARFs where these events are removed. CrissCross and clean_spec are especially useful for crowded X-ray fields with multiple observations such as stellar clusters.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      Users are encouraged to try CrissCross and clean_spec using the jupyter notebook tutorial 
      'crisscross_tutorial.ipynb' included with CIAO installations using contrib-scripts version X or later. 
      It provides an end-to-end example of running CrissCross and clean_spec on an HETG observation of a crowded stellar cluster and extracting a cleaned spectrum. More examples can also be found in the crisscross ahelp page.
      </PARA>      

    
      <PARA>
      To utilize clean_spec, users are expected to have already extracted HETG source spectra from the observation of interest using 
      <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/gspec.html">standard grating CIAO tools</HREF> and run crisscross to produce confusion tables for each HETG spectrum. Please see the crisscross ahelp page for more info.
      </PARA>     

      <PARA title="Try the jupyter notebook tutorial!">

      A tutorial is included in every ciao-installation with ciao-contrib version X or later. Users can setup this 
      tutorial in a new directory using the following commands:

    </PARA>

      <VERBATIM>
      unix% mkdir notebooks
      unix% cp $ASCDS_INSTALL/share/ciao/notebooks/*ipynb notebooks/
      unix% jupyter lab --notebook-dir notebooks
      </VERBATIM>

    <PARA>
      The examples below highlight some of the ways to use clean_spec with associated crisscross output files. Please see the crisscross ahelp for creating confusion tables. 

    </PARA>

    </DESC>


    <QEXAMPLELIST>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  
      <LINE>&pr; punlearn chandra_repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro indir=3 outdir=custom_hetg_extraction root=tet1oriE \</LINE>
      <LINE>tg_zo_position='83.8156671,-5.3861617'</LINE>

      <LINE>&pr; punlearn crisscross</LINE>
      <LINE>&pr; crisscross infile=3/custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_evt2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>outdir=cc_singlesrc_outdir main_list=all_srcs.fits single_src_pos='83.8156671,-5.3861617'\</LINE>
      <LINE>single_src_root='tet1oriE' mode=a</LINE>

      <LINE>&pr; punlearn clean_spec</LINE>
      <LINE>&pr; clean_spec infile=3/custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_pha2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>conf_file=cc_singlesrc_outdir/output_dir_obsid_3/confusion_output_files/table_fits_data/\</LINE>
      <LINE>confused_tet1oriE_consolidated_obsID_3.fits spec_root=tet1oriC</LINE>


	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Run crisscross to assess confusion for a single source and clean the spectrum with clean_spec. To run this example
      verbatim, see the crisscross ahelp page for creating the necessary main_list 'all_srcs.fits' file. For this example,
      we utilizes the chandra_repro tg_zo_position parameter which allows users to pick an RA and DEC to extract a specific 
      source's HETG spectra. This runs the standard tg_extract tools and produces PHA files and ARFs and RMFs. The 
      chandra_repro tg_orders parameter can be used to specify more orders than the default +1/-1.  Users can assess confusion for a single 
      source by utilizing the single_src_pos parameter. Running crisscross with a single RA and DEC will create a 
      single confusion table for that source as long as it matches a source in the main_list input file. The main_list 
      sources still need to be provided as they are the sources of potential confusion.  See the jupyter notebook 
      tutorial for more info about comparing cleaned vs uncleaned spectra.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn clean_spec</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; clean_spec infile=custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_pha2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>conf_file=cc_singlesrc_outdir/output_dir_obsid_3/confusion_output_files/table_fits_data/\</LINE>
      <LINE>confused_tet1oriE_consolidated_obsID_3.fits spec_root=tet1oriE_cleaned mode=a</LINE>
  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      The clean_spec tool will automatically find the associated ARFs when provided with an HETG pha2 spectrum and the 
      arf_file parameter left blank. It will produce cleaned spectra for all the orders associated with the found ARF 
      files. Note, even thought the default PHA2 HETG files include all 12 orders, chandra_repro only produces arfs for 
      +1/-1 orders by default unless the chandra_repro tg_orders parameter is used. The clean_spec tool will produce a 
      new 'cleaned' pha2 file that includes all 12 orders but ONLY the orders with matching arfs will be cleaned. If the
      arfs are not correctly found, the 'resp_dir' parameter can be set to point to the arfs.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn stk_build</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; stk_build infile= 'custom_hetg_extraction/tg/tet1oriE_repro_heg_p1.arf \</LINE>
      <LINE>custom_hetg_extraction/tg/tet1oriE_repro_heg_m1.arf' outfile=arf.lis clobber=yes</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn clean_spec</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; clean_spec infile=custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_pha2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>conf_file=cc_singlesrc_outdir/output_dir_obsid_3/confusion_output_files/table_fits_data/\</LINE>
      <LINE>confused_tet1oriE_consolidated_obsID_3.fits spec_root=tet1oriE_heg_spec arf_file=@arf.lis mode=a</LINE>
  

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      To produce cleaned spectra for only specific orders such as heg +1 and heg -1 you can use clean_spec with a stack 
      file of arfs and the input PHA2 spectrum. This also works with an individual arf (order) without stacks.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>

      <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  The PHA1 or PHA2 HETG spectrum file to be cleaned.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This file is typically produced via chandra_repro or running the tg_extract and associated ciao tools for extracting
        HETG spectra. Note, many HETG PHA2 spectra include all 12 orders but only the orders with matching arfs will be 
        cleaned. The output cleaned PHA2 file may include all 12 orders even if only some of the orders have been cleaned.
        The remaining orders will not be modified.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="conf_file" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Confusion fits table produced by the ciao tool crisscross.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      This table is the output of the ciao tool crisscross and indicates the portions of a spectrum with confusion. Each 
      crisscross table is unique to a particular source and obsID and its output depends on the parameters used when running
      crisscross. This table includes information on all HETG orders with identified confusion unless the user changed the
      default crisscross parameter 'highest order'.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="spec_root" type="string" reqd="no" >
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  A root name for naming the output cleaned spectra.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="arf_file" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  A chandra HETG ARF file or files associated with each HETG order.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      If this parameter is left blank then the ARFs associated with the PHA1 or PHA2 file will be looked-up using keywords
      in the PHA2 file. Only ARFs identified with a matching order will be used to clean the spectra. If a stack is used
      then only orders matched to the included ARFs will be cleaned even though all spectra may be included in the 
      cleaned output PHA2 file. 
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>


      <PARAM name="resp_dir" type="string" reqd="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Path to ARFs associated with the input PHA1 or PHA2 HETG spectrum file.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    A path to the ARFs can be provided if the auto-lookup feature does not automatically identify the ARFs or if 
        the user has ARFs located in a non-default location.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
     </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean"  def="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Specifies if an existing output file should be overwritten.
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer"  def="0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Specifies the level of verbosity (0-5) in displaying
	  diagnostic messages.
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>



    <BUGS>
 
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>June 2026</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
