<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY pr 'unix&#37;'>
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="combine_spectra" context="tools" 
  refkeywords="combine coadd add spectra PHA spectral combined multi-obsid multi-obs" 
  seealsogroups="resptools"> 

    <SYNOPSIS>
     Combine PHA files and their associated response files.
    </SYNOPSIS>


     <DESC>
      <PARA>
         The combine_spectra script sums multiple PHA
	 spectra.  It will also combine the associated background PHA spectra and
	 source and background ARF and RMF response files.       
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      Typically only the src_spectra parameter and outroot parameters
      need to be specified, since the
      response (ARF and RMF) and background files will be found
      from the ANCRFILE, RESPFILE, and BACKFILE keywords in the
      spectra. If required, the user can override these settings
      using the src_arfs, src_rmfs, bkg_spectra, bkg_arfs, and
      bkg_rmfs parameters.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      The output source spectrum will contain the sum of the 
      source spectrum counts and (by default) the sum of the
      exposure time.  The background counts are scaled by 
      the exposure times and areas as discussed below.
      </PARA>
  </DESC>


    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; combine_spectra obs1843.pi,obs1842.pi combined</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
            Combine the two source spectra.  The output source file 
	    is called combined_src.pi and
            contains the summed source counts and the summed EXPOSURE.  
            If the files contain ANCRFILE, RESPFILE, and/or BACKFILE
            keywords, the responses and background files will also be
            created.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; combine_spectra /data/pha1.pi,/data/pha2.pi summed \</LINE>
	  <LINE>bkg_spectra=pha1_bkg.pi,pha2_bkg.pi bkg_arfs=@pha_arf.lis</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	   The input source spectra 'pha1.pi' and 'pha2.pi' are
	combined to produce the summed counts spectrum
	'summed_src.pi'. The script locates the associated source ARF and RMF
	files for these spectra and combines them, producing output
	files 'summed_src.arf' and 'summed_src.rmf'. Instead of having the script search for
	the associated background spectra and background ARFs to combine,
	they are explicitly entered into the 'bkg_spectra' and
	'bkg_arfs' parameters, the latter using a
	<HREF
	    link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/stack.html">stack
	file</HREF>.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; combine_spectra @pha3.lis combined verbose=2</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	   An ASCII file containing a list of Level-3 PHA spectral
	filenames is input to combine_spectra for combining.  The script
	locates the associated source responses, background
	spectra, and background responses, and combines these files as
	well. The verbosity level is changed from the default value of
	1 to 2, in order to print to the screen each step of the code
	as it is carried out.  
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>


   <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="src_spectra" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
            Source PHA files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
             A stack of PHA TYPE:I spectra to combine. 
             </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="outroot" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes" >
         <SYNOPSIS>
            Root name for output files
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
             The script will create the following output files based
             on the available inputs:              
           </PARA>
            <LIST>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_src.pi : Source spectrum</ITEM>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_src.arf : Source ARF file</ITEM>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_src.rmf: Source RMF file</ITEM>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_bkg.pi : Background spectrum</ITEM>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_bkg.arf : Background ARF file</ITEM>
              <ITEM>${outroot}_bkg.rmf : Background RMF file</ITEM>
            </LIST>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>     
      <PARAM name="src_arfs" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="no" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
            Source ARF files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
	      If this parameter is blank then the script will locate
	      the ARF file using the
              ANCRFILE keyword in each of the input files.
	      If given, then the order of the ARF files
              must match the order of the src_spectra parameter.  
            </PARA>
        <PARA>
          The parameter can be set to "NONE" and the keyword value will
          not be used.
        </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>     

      <PARAM name="src_rmfs" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="no" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
           Source RMF files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
	      If this parameter is blank then the script will locate the RMF file using the
              RESPFILE keyword in each of the input files.
	      If given, then the order of the RMF files
              must match the order of the src_spectra parameter.  
            </PARA>
        <PARA>
          The parameter can be set to "NONE" and the keyword value will
          not be used.
        </PARA>

            <PARA>
              Note: RSP-style responses which have been premultiplied by an ARF
              are not supported.
	    </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>     

      <PARAM name="bkg_spectra" type="file" reqd="no" filetype="input" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
            Background PHA files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
	      If this parameter is blank then the script will locate
	      the background file using the
              BACKFILE keyword in each of the input files.
	      If given, then the order of the background files
              must match the order of the src_spectra parameter.  
            </PARA>
        <PARA>
          The parameter can be set to "NONE" and the keyword value will
          not be used.
        </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>     

      <PARAM name="bkg_arfs" type="file" reqd="no" filetype="input" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
	   Background ARF files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
                See the src_arfs parameter for more details.
            </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>     

      <PARAM name="bkg_rmfs" type="file" reqd="no" filetype="input" stacks="yes">
         <SYNOPSIS>
	   Background RMF files to combine; enter list or '@stack'
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
            See the src_rmfs parameter for more details.
           </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM> 

  
      <PARAM name="method" type="string" reqd="no" def="sum">
         <SYNOPSIS>
	   Sum or average PHA exposures?
         </SYNOPSIS>
         <DESC>
            <PARA>
             The method parameter may be set to either 'sum' (default)
             or 'avg' to specify how the individual PHA exposure
             times should be combined for the output combined
             spectrum.	When 'method=sum', combined spectra are output
             with the total PHA exposure time recorded in the header.             
             When 'method=avg' ,
             the mean exposure time is recorded. The output combined
             responses are appropriately adjusted for the current
             'method' setting.
            </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>      

      <PARAM name="bscale_method" type="string" reqd="no" def="asca">
        <SYNOPSIS>
	  How are BACKSCAL and background counts computed?
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
              There are 3 different algorithms to combine
              the background counts compute the background
              scaling (BACKSCAL) values.            
          </PARA>
          
          <PARA title="'asca'">
          When simply subtracting the background, the 'asca'
          method can be used.  The combined background counts
          are an exposure and area weighted combination:
          </PARA>
        
<VERBATIM>
f = {(bkg_exp1 + ... + bkg_expN)/[src_exp1(src_backscal1/bkg_backscal1) + ... + src_expN(src_backscalN/bkg_backscalN)]}*
f_I = f*{(src_expI/bkg_expI)*(src_backscalI/bkg_backscalI)}  
BKG_COUNTS = f_1*bkg_counts1 + f_2*bkg_counts2 + ... f_N*bkg_countsN
BKG_BACKSCAL = (src_exp1 + ... + src_expN)/[src_exp1(src_backscal1/bkg_backscal1) + ...  + src_expN(src_backscalN/bkg_backscalN)]  
SOURCE_COUNTS = src_counts1 + src_counts2 + ... + src_countsN
SOURCE_EXPOSURE = src_exp1 + src_exp2 + ... + src_expN
SOURCE_BACKSCAL = 1.0
</VERBATIM>
          
          
          <PARA title="'time'">
  The 'time' methods computes the total counts (unweighted) and
  the provides and exposure time weighted BACKSCAL value.
          </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
BKG_COUNTS = bkg_counts1 + bkg_counts2 + ... bkg_countsN
SS = [(src_exp1*src_backscal1) + ... + (src_expN*src_backscalN)] / (src_exp1 + ... + src_expN)
BB = [(bkg_exp1*bkg_backscal1) + ... + (bkg_expN*bkg_backscalN)] / (bkg_exp1 + ... + bkg_expN)
BKG_BACKSCAL = BB / SS
SOURCE_COUNTS = src_counts1 + src_counts2 + ... + src_countsN
SOURCE_EXPOSURE = src_exp1 + src_exp2 + ... + src_expN
SOURCE_BACKSCAL = 1.0
</VERBATIM>

          <PARA title="'counts'">
  The 'counts' method gives background counts and backscale values that
  are correctly weighted when the background is going to be modeled
  rather than subtracted.  That is the background has been combined
  such that the errors on the background are correct.
          </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
r_i = (src_exp_i*src_backscal_i)/(bkg_exp_i*bkg_backscal_i)
m1 = (bkg_counts1*r_1) + ... + (bkg_countsN*r_N)
m2 = (bkg_counts1*r_1^2) + ... + (bkg_countsN*r_N^2)

BKG_COUNTS = (m1*m1) / m2
BKG_BACKSCAL = SOURCE_BACKSCAL * ((src_exp1+...+src_expN)/(bkg_exp1+...+bkg_expN))*(m1/m2)

SOURCE_COUNTS = src_counts1 + src_counts2 + ... + src_countsN
SOURCE_EXPOSURE = src_exp1 + src_exp2 + ... + src_expN
SOURCE_BACKSCAL = (src_exp1*src_backscal1) + ... + (src_expN*src_backscalN) / (src_exp1 + ... + src_expN)
</VERBATIM>

        </DESC>
      </PARAM>

     <PARAM name="exp_origin" type="string" def="pha" reqd="no">
       <SYNOPSIS>
	 Write combined PHA or ARF exposure time to header(s) (pha, arf)
       </SYNOPSIS>
       <DESC>
	 <PARA>
	   Should the combined EXPOSURE time be taken from the PHA or
	   ARF files?
	 </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no"  reqd="no">
         <SYNOPSIS>
	   OK to overwrite existing output file?
         </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>       
    

      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5" reqd="no">
         <SYNOPSIS>
	   Debug Level(0-5)
         </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>       
    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Caveats">
        <LIST>
         <ITEM>
	Any grouping flags which may be present in input source or 
    background PHA spectra will be ignored by the script.
	</ITEM>
	
	<ITEM>
	Combining background spectra with
	wildly varying spectral extraction region areas may
	yield misleading uncertainty estimates; i.e., some extractions
	will be over-represented while others will be under-represented.
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	If the background rates	contributing to a source are
	significantly different in the individual spectra to be
	combined, it is recommended that these spectra remain separate
	and be modeled simultaneously - otherwise, the modeling
	results of the combined source spectrum could be biased
	towards the observation(s) with the highest background rate(s).
	</ITEM>

      <ITEM>
	RSP-style responses which have been premultiplied by an ARF
	are not supported.
      </ITEM>

    <ITEM>
        Statistical errors on the combined counts in the combined
	source and background spectra are only recomputed using the Gehrel's
    approximation if the input file has a STAT_ERR column.
    </ITEM>

    <ITEM>
        Non-chandra files may not work correctly.
    </ITEM>

       </LIST>
</ADESC>


    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.10.3 (October 2018) release">
      <PARA>
      Recognizes when outroot is a directory and adjusts file names
      so they no longer begin with an underscore or period.      
      </PARA>
    
    </ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.9.2 (April 2017) release">
  <PARA>
    If the input spectra contain a STAT_ERR column, the script will
    now recompute the error using the Gehrel's approximation.
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Change in the 4.7.3 (June 2015) release">
  <PARA>
    The path name is now removed from the file names 
    stored in the ANCRFILE, RESPFILE, and BACKFILE keywords.
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.6.7 (November 2014) release">
<PARA>Users can now specify src_arf, src_rmf, bkg_spectra, bkg_arf, and bkg_rmf
as "NONE" to for the tool to entirely skip combining those products, even
if they are able to be located by the ANCRFILE, RESPFILE, or BACKFILE keywords in the
input source spectrum files. (Value is case sensitive) 
</PARA>
<PARA>
Fixes a bug in the bscale_method='counts' method when the 
combined background counts in any channel is 0.
</PARA>
 
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the CIAO 4.11.5 (September 2019) release">
      <PARA>
        Fixed a bug when bkg_spectrum=NONE. It should have skipped 
        combining background spectrum files even when the 
        BACKFILE keywords were populated in the source spectra.
      
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

      
    <ADESC title="Changes in the CIAO 4.6.6 (September 2014) release">
      <PARA>
      The script will ensure that the ONTIME, LIVETIME, and EXPOSURE
      keywords (and the per-chip variants) in the output ARF files 
      are consistent with the input ARF times.  The PHA values in the
      PHA files (used by sherpa and xspec) are not affected.
      </PARA>
    
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="Changes in the CIAO 4.6.5 (June 2014) release">
      <PARA>
        The combine_spectra script has been completely re-written.
        It no longer makes use of a large number of temporary
        files and as a result is much faster.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        Two new parameters have been added.  exp_origin controls
        whether the EXPOSURE keyword is computed from the
        spectrum, pha, files or whether it is computed from
        the ARF files.  bscale_method allows the user to select
        different algorithms to compute the combined
        background counts and associated scaling factor (BACKSCAL);
        the default, 'asca', is the same as previous versions
        of this script.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
     
    <ADESC title="Changes in the February 2012 Release">
      <PARA>
       The script was updated to work around a CIAO 4.4 bug
       in the tool addresp, used for
       combining ARF and RMF responses: the output combined RMF file
       is missing the TLMIN header keyword for the F_CHAN column;
       combine_spectra now adds the TLMIN4 keyword to the combined RMF file.
      </PARA>
       <PARA>
        The script now cleans up several temporary files which were
        being written to the outroot directory, instead of to /tmp/.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the December 2011 Release">
      <PARA>
       New 'method' parameter for selecting between a summed and mean
       exposure value to be recorded in the header of output combined spectra and
       ARFs.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
       Bug fix: the ANCRFILE header keyword in an output combined
       background spectrum was incorrectly being set to "NONE" 
       when the input backround response files exactly matched the
       input source responses.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
       Internal updates to the addresp step of the script to support
       the new addresp 'phafiles' and 'method' parameters. 
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the April 2011 Release">
      <PARA>
       The script prints the version number when verbosity is greater
      than 0.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
       Temporary output files are written to the 'outroot' directory instead
      of the current working directory, before being moved to the /tmp
      directory.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the December 2010 Release">
      <PARA>
       combine_spectra in CIAO 4.3 invokes the new tool addresp for
      combining ARF and RMF responses. Prior to this release, the
      script combined ARFs via the dmarfadd tool -  with results
      equivalent to the output of addresp - and did not combine RMFs.
      </PARA>
     </ADESC> 

     <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/combine_spectra.html">bugs
        page for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
   
    <LASTMODIFIED>September 2019</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
