<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY pr "unix&#37;">
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="crisscross" context="Tools::Composite"
	 refkeywords=" spectrum spectra pha gratings HETG wavdetect source-detection MEG HEG pointsource pointsource psf 
     OSIP spectral-extraction cleaning confusion orders 0th-order ARF"
	 seealsogroups="gratings, tgextract, resptools">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Analysis tool for Chandra-HETG observations with multiple bright souces in a field of view.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>

      <PARA>
	  CrissCross and its helper tool clean_spec allow users to analyze Chandra High Energy Transmission Grating (HETG) 
      spectra that are extracted from a field of view with multiple other astrophysical X-ray sources. The HETG 
      instrument will disperse events onto the ACIS CCDs from all sources in a field of view and if there are several 
      sufficiently-bright X-ray sources then there is a potential for 'confusion' to occur. Confusion is a term used 
      here for special scenarios where <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/gspec.html">standard HETG 
      spectral extraction</HREF> of a source may erroneously assign events (counts) from a different astrophysical 
      source in the field of view to the extracted source. This can result in events from an unrelated astrophyscal 
      source 'confusing' the spectrum of an extracted source.	
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      CrissCross is used to identify when spectral confusion occurs for a list of input sources (or a single source) 
      and generates 'confusion tables' which identify the wavelength in each source's spectrum that are likely to 
      include X-ray events from unrelated field astrophysical sources. The user can then choose to remove all events 
      from the source spectrum in the wavelenegth range where this confusion occurs. The CrissCross helper program 
      clean_spec uses the CrissCross output confusion tables and input HETG PHA spectra to generate 'cleaned' spectra 
      (and ARFs) where these events are removed. CrissCross is especially useful for crowded X-ray fields with multiple 
      observations such as stellar clusters.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      Users are encouraged to try CrissCross and clean_spec using the jupyter notebook tutorial 
      'crisscross_tutorial.ipynb' included with CIAO installations using contrib-scripts version X or later. 
      It provides an end-to-end example of running CrissCross on an HETG observation of a crowded stellar cluster and 
      extracting a cleaned spectrum.
      </PARA>      

      <PARA title="How does CrissCross work?">
     
      The CrissCross routine (crisscross) takes advantage of the characteristic 'X' shape the Chandra-HETG instrument 
      makes when dispersing X-ray light onto the ACIS-S CCDs. For each source, the center of this 'X' is located at the 
      position of the (non-dispersed zeroth-order) X-ray source in the field of view. While technically all X-ray sources 
      cast their own X shape, the majority in most Chandra fields-of-view are too faint to disperse enough events onto 
      the detector for high-resolution X-ray spectroscopy purposes. As a result, only the brightest X-ray sources will 
      produce this X shape visible by eye in an HETG event file. If there are two or more bright sources in the same 
      field of view then their respective X shapes likely intersect with each other somewhere on the detector. In other 
      words, if one were to extract HETG spectra from each of these sources using 
      <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/gspec.html">standard CIAO tools</HREF>, there are locations 
      (wavelength ranges) in each spectrum that could contain events from other sources. Throughout this documentation, 
      this scenario is referred to as 'confusion'. Confusion occurs when events from another source end up in the 
      spectrum of your source of interest during extraction.

      </PARA>


      <PARA>
      HETG-ACIS already has a mechanism to handle some level of this confusion. Energy/wavelength as a function of 
      distance from the center of the HETG 'X' shape is known based on the gratings dispersion equation and the 
      instrumental setup. When the energy of an X-ray event, as measured by the ACIS CCDs, is very different than what 
      is expected at the location in the spectral arm (distance from center of X) then CIAO tools will remove these 
      events automatically using Order Sorting Integrated Probability tables in the CALDB. However, there can be cases 
      where the energy of confusing events from another source is the SAME as what is expected from the spectrum of the
       extracted source based on the dispersion distance from its 0th order. These cases are currently not handled in 
       CIAO and are exactly what is identified by CrissCross. For example, lets assume you are interested in the HETG 
       spectrum of 'Src A' and there is another source in the field of view called 'Src B'. The crisscross routine 
       handles all four possible types of confusion:
      </PARA>

      <LIST>

        <ITEM>
      'Point Source Confusion' occurs when the (zeroth order) point source of SRC B lands on/near (is coincident with) 
      a dispersed HEG or MEG spectral arm of Src A. The Src B 0th order will include events of all energies in the Src B 
      spectrum and is likely to cause confusion in the relevant wavelength range of the extracted HEG/MEG spectrum of 
      Src A. The proximity of Src B (max_pntsrc_dist), the size of its PSF and an estimate of the number of counts in 
      the relevant wavelength range of Src A is used to determine if confusion can occur. If the estimated ratio of 
      counts in the affected wavelength range (Src B / Src A) > 10% then the relevant portion of the Src A spectrum is 
      marked as confused. Typically, most sources in the field of view are too faint to meaningfully dispersed HEG/MEG 
      counts so an on-axis point source confuser will only confuse a small wavelength range of the Src A spectrum 
      (approx. 0.5 Ang). However, if Src B is sufficiently bright then it will also cause ARM confusion (see below).
      </ITEM>

      <ITEM>
      'Spectral Confusion' occurs when the HEG or MEG dispersed spectrum of Src B intersects with the X shape of Src A 
      and Src B is bright enough to disperse a meaningful number of events. What is a meaningful number of events in 
      this context? When spectral confusion can occur based on the geometry of two sources, the wavelength of confusion 
      is calculated from the gratings equation. Both the confused (Src A) and confuser (Src B) zeroth order point 
      sources are analyzed to determine how many Nth order (1st, 2nd, 3rd) dispersed counts exist in the energy bandpass
       where confusion can occur. If this counts ratio (src B / src A) is > spec_confuse_limit (default = 10%) then 
       CrissCross marks this as confusion. This calculation accounts for the effective area at the location of confusion
        as well as the efficiencies of different spectral orders (e.g., if MEG+3 from src B is confusing HEG+1 of 
        source A).
      </ITEM>

      <ITEM>
      'Arm Confusion' occurs when Src B is very bright and lands on/near the HEG or MEG arm of Src A. In this case, 
      Src B is bright enough to disperse its events into an X-shape and if it lands on the arm of Src A that means it 
      will disperse events directly along the entire HEG/MEG arm of Src A. This situation is unfortunate as it 
      potentially confuses a large portion of the Src A spectrum. When arm confusion can occur, the distance between
       the Src A and Src B 0th orders (in the dispersion direction) dictates how much of the arm is likely to be 
       confused. The closer the sources are, the more of the spectral arm is confused. CrissCross will use the distance 
       between these sources to identify the relevant range of arm confusion in Src A.
      </ITEM>

      <ITEM>
      'Readout Streak Confusion' is rare but occurs for extremely bright sources. The 0th order of an extremely bright 
      'Src B' source will produce a line of events along the CCD readout direction that could intersect with the 
      dispersed spectra of Src A. CrissCross identifies these rare situations and will mark the limited portion of 
      Src A's spectrum as confused.
      </ITEM>            

      </LIST>


      <PARA title="What are the main considerations for running crisscross and clean_spec?">
      
      The crisscross tool has a lot of parameters but the vast majority of them can be kept at their default values. The
      main thing one needs to run crisscross is a list of potential X-ray sources in the field of view of the 
      observation (parameter 'main_list'). CrissCross ultimately needs to know the number of counts for every 0th order 
      point source in the field of view. For non-HETG observations, this can be obtained with CIAO source-detection 
      programs like wavdetect. However, these detection tools are not designed to work on HETG event files where many 
      events are dispersed by the gratings which can cause a lot of false detections. CrissCross runs wavdetect by 
      default (or alternatively uses an input wavdetect source table) and cross-matches positive source-detections with 
      the main_list to remove the erroneous gratings-identified sources. With knowledge of the point source locations 
      and counts, CrissCross identifies confusion for every source provided in the subset_src_list file (or a single 
      source if parameter single_src_pos is used) and creates a corresponding confusion table.

      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      Users are expected to have already extracted HETG source spectra from the observation of interest using 
      <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/gspec.html">standard grating CIAO tools</HREF>. It is these 
      sources for which CrissCross will produce confusion tables that can be used with clean_spec to create 'cleaned' 
      spectra free of identified confusion. CrissCross will create confusion tables for every source in the 
      subset_src_list so this should include only the bright HETG sources for which the user has extracted spectra. 
      Note, a source bright enough to obtain quality HETG spectra can also produce confusion for other sources in the 
      field of view. As such, every source in subset_src_list must also include an identical entry in the 'main list' 
      file.
      </PARA>     


      <PARA title="What is an example workflow for creating cleaned spectra?">

      A typical end-to-end workflow using CrissCross would look something like this:

    </PARA>

  <LIST>
      <ITEM>
      For your HETG observation(s) of choice, create a source list (parameter 'main list') of all potential X-ray 
      sources in the field of view. Many HETG fields have been previously observed with ACIS imaging which can be used 
      with wavdetect to build a source list. Alternatively, all-sky source catalogues like GAIA, 2MASS, SDSS can be 
      used to build an initial list and then members can be removed if they are not observed in the HETG observations 
      emitting X-rays. It is not very important to know exactly which field sources are emitting X-rays in any 
      individual observation since CrissCross will ignore wavdetect-matched sources with 0 counts. However, the more 
      non-X-ray sources that are in your main list increases the chance one of these sources overlap with an 
      erroneously-identified wavdetect source from dispersed events.
      </ITEM>  

      <ITEM>
      Extract HETG spectra using standard ciao tools for every source whose spectrum you need assessed for confusion 
      from other sources in the field of view (main_list). These sources will make up your sources in the 
      'subset_src_list' file.
      </ITEM>  

      <ITEM>
      Run crisscross (see examples below) to produce confusion tables for every source listed in the subset_src_list file.
      </ITEM>  

      <ITEM>
      For each HETG spectra, run the CIAO contrib tool clean_spec using both the appropriate crisscross confusion table 
      and HETG PHA spectrum file as input. This will produce a set of 'cleaned' HETG spectra and associated ARF 
      response files for each source. These 'cleaned' spectra will have counts and response values zeroed-out 
      (set to zero) where confusion was identified. It is important to note CrissCross removes ALL counts in the 
      identified confused wavelength range and not just the counts from the confusing source.
      </ITEM>              
  </LIST>

      <PARA title="Try the jupyter notebook tutorial!">

      A tutorial is included in every ciao-installation with ciao-contrib version X or later. Users can setup this 
      tutorial in a new directory using the following commands:

    </PARA>

      <VERBATIM>
      unix% mkdir notebooks
      unix% cp $ASCDS_INSTALL/share/ciao/notebooks/*ipynb notebooks/
      unix% jupyter lab --notebook-dir notebooks
      </VERBATIM>

    <PARA>
      The examples below highlight some of the ways crisscross can be used to create confusion tables and cleaned 
      spectra. Chandra observations of the Orion Nebular Cluster, a cluster of X-ray-emitting pre-main sequence stars, 
      are used to demonstrate the utility of crisscross.  

    </PARA>

    </DESC>


    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>

	  <LINE>&pr; download_chandra_obsid 3498</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn chandra_repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro 3498</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn fluximage</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; 3498/repro/acisf03498_repro_evt2.fits binsize=2.0 bands=broad \</LINE>
	  <LINE>outroot=acisf03498 psfecf=0.9 clobber=yes</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn wavdetect</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; wavdetect infile=acisf03498_broad_thresh.img outfile=source_list.fits \</LINE>
	  <LINE>scellfile=source_cell.fits imagefile=image.fits defnbkgfile=background.fits \</LINE>
	  <LINE>expfile=acisf03498_broad_thresh.expmap regfile=source_list.reg expfile=none \</LINE>
	  <LINE>psffile=acisf03498_broad_thresh.psfmap scales='2 4 8' clobber=yes</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn dmcopy</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; dmcopy infile='source_list.fits[cols RA,DEC]' outfile = all_srcs.fits</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; dmcopy infile='source_list.fits[cols RA,DEC][NET_COUNTS > 3500]' \</LINE>
      <LINE>outfile = bright_srcs.fits clobber=yes</LINE>
  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      This example demonstrates one way to create 'main_list' and 'subset_src_list' input files for crisscross using 
      ACIS imaging-mode (non-HETG) observations. First we reprocess the observation to utilize up-to-date calibration 
      files and then run fluximage and wavdetect to create a table of detected X-ray sources in the Orion Nebula Cluster. 
      Fluximage is a helpful tool prior to running wavdetect because it creates a psfile and an image file used in 
      wavdetect. More information on these tools can be found on their respective CIAO pages. The dmcopy tool is then 
      used to remove the columns unnecessary for crisscross from the output wavdetect table to generate an RA/DEC list 
      of all sources in the field of view (all_srcs.fits) and a list of only the brightest sources (greater than 3500 
      counts) for which we will later want to extract HETG spectra (bright_srcs.fits). Note that it is not guaranteed 
      that any single obsID represents all potential X-ray sources in a field of view and that some astrophysical 
      sources are variable so if they are 'bright' in one obsID it does not mean they will be bright in all future obsIDs. 
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>




      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>

	  <LINE>&pr; download_chandra_obsid 3</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn chandra_repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro 3</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn crisscross</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; infile=3/repro/acisf00003_repro_evt2.fits outdir=cc_outdir main_list=all_srcs.fits \</LINE>
	  <LINE>subset_src_list=bright_srcs.fits verbose=1 clobber=yes mode=a</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn clean_spec</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; clean_spec infile=3/repro/acisf00003_repro_pha2.fits \</LINE>
	  <LINE>conf_file=cc_outdir/output_dir_obsid_3/confusion_output_files/table_fits_data/\</LINE>
	  <LINE>confused_src_397_consolidated_obsID_3.fits spec_root=tet1oriC</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Run crisscross for a single HETG observation (obsID 3) with a list of input sources generated in example 1 above. 
      This will create an output directory 'cc_outdir' that contains two subdirectories: (1) 'confusion_output_files' 
      which contains confusion tables generated for each source in subset_src_list and (2) wavdetect_output_files which 
      contain wavdetect files that were used to estimate the number of 0th order counts for each source in main_list.  
      The clean_spec tool is used with the HETG PHA2 spectral file automatically generated by chandra_repro for the 
      source at the aimpoint (theta1 Ori C) to produce a 'cleaned' spectrum. See the jupyter notebook tutorial for more
       information about comparing cleaned vs uncleaned spectra.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>



      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  
      <LINE>&pr; punlearn chandra_repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro indir=3 outdir=custom_hetg_extraction root=tet1oriE \</LINE>
      <LINE>tg_zo_position='83.8156671,-5.3861617'</LINE>

      <LINE>&pr; punlearn crisscross</LINE>
      <LINE>&pr; crisscross infile=3/custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_evt2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>outdir=cc_singlesrc_outdir main_list=all_srcs.fits single_src_pos='83.8156671,-5.3861617'\</LINE>
      <LINE>single_src_root='tet1oriE' mode=a</LINE>

      <LINE>&pr; punlearn clean_spec</LINE>
      <LINE>&pr; clean_spec infile=3/custom_hetg_extraction/tet1oriE_repro_pha2.fits \</LINE>
      <LINE>conf_file=cc_singlesrc_outdir/output_dir_obsid_3/confusion_output_files/table_fits_data/\</LINE>
      <LINE>confused_tet1oriE_consolidated_obsID_3.fits spec_root=tet1oriC</LINE>


	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Run crisscross to assess confusion for a single source. For this example, we utilizes the chandra_repro 
      tg_zo_position parameter which allows users to pick an RA and DEC to extract a specific source's HETG spectra. 
      This runs the standard tg_extract tools and produces PHA files and ARFs and RMFs. The chandra_repro tg_orders 
      parameter can be used to specify more orders than the default +1/-1.  Users can assess confusion for a single 
      source by utilizing the single_src_pos parameter. Running crisscross with a single RA and DEC will create a 
      single confusion table for that source as long as it matches a source in the main_list input file. The main_list 
      sources still need to be provided as they are the sources of potential confusion.  See the jupyter notebook 
      tutorial for more info about comparing cleaned vs uncleaned spectra.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn stk_build</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; stk_build infile='obs1_evt2.fits obs2_evt2.fits obs3_evt2.fits' \</LINE>
	  <LINE>outfile=crisscross_evt2_stk.lis</LINE>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn crisscross</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; crisscross infile=@crisscross_evt2_stk.lis outdir=multi_obs_crisscross \</LINE>
	  <LINE>main_list=all_srcs.fits subset_src_list=bright_srcs.fits</LINE>

    </SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      The crisscross tool can also be run with multiple obsIDs at once. This is a convenient way to calculate confusion 
      for HETG campaigns that were split into many observations. The above commands will not work verbatim but are meant
       to demonstrate syntax. Users that don't wish to have crisscross run wavdetect every time can also provide matching 
       wavdetect source files in a stack matching the evt2 syntax above. The evt2 and wavdetect stacks do not have to be 
       in the same order.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>



      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>

	  <LINE>&pr; punlearn crisscross</LINE>
    
	  <LINE>&pr; crisscross infile=3/repro/acisf00003_repro_evt2.fits \</LINE>
	  <LINE>wavdetect_file=custom_wavdetect_file.fits outdir=cc_outdir \</LINE>
      <LINE>main_list=all_srcs.fits subset_src_list=bright_srcs.fits clobber=yes</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      For users that wish to run wavdetect with custom parameters, a wavdetect output source fits file can be provided 
      to crisscross. This also saves computation time. The above commands will not work verbatim without creating the 
      appropriate wavdetect file.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>

      <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" stacks="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  The evt2 file(s) of an ACIS-HETG observation.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The primary input to this tool is an event file (or stack of
	    event files) which correspond to the observation(s) that include 
        sources input in main_list and subset_src_list.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
        If a stack of event files is included then crisscross will run sequentially
        for each observation.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="outdir" type="file" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Root for the output directory where crisscross output will be saved.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      This directory will contain all the output from crisscross which includes
      the spectral confusion tables for each source in subset_src_list or 
      single_src_pos as well as log files and wavdetect output if it was run.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="main_list" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" >
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  An ascii/tsv file which includes columns RA, DEC, and ID of all potential
      X-ray sources in the input evt2 file(s).
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Wavdetct must be run on each event file to identify 0th order point sources and obtain an estimate of their 
      counts. This is done automatically if users do not provide a wavdetect_file. When wavdetect is run on an HETG 
      observation, dispersed events from the HEG/MEG arms can be erroneously identified as 'real' sources. The 'main_list' 
      of sources is matched to the wavdetect output to ensure only real sources are considered when assessing confusion.  
	  </PARA>


	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="subset_src_list" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes" >
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  An ascii/tsv file which includes columns RA, DEC of sources for which confusion will be assessed.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      This list should contain sources whose HETG spectra you want to extract and understand whether or not there is 
      confusion. Every source in subset_src_list should also be present in main_list since even these sources can cause
       confusion in other sources. Typically the sources in this list will be relatively bright otherwise the spectra 
       may not be useful. If users wish to only calculate confusion for a single source (single_src_pos) then this field
        can be left blank.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>


      <PARAM name="single_src_pos" type="string">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Assess confusion for only a single HETG source.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Instead of providing a list of relatively-bright HETG sources in subset_src_list, users can provide the RA and 
        DEC in J2000 deg of a single source. The format should be e.g., '(83.818,-5.389)' and must be in degrees. Use 
        of this parameter can be used with single_src_root for naming the output file.
	  </PARA>


	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="single_src_root" type="string">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Root name for output confusion table of single_src_pos.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      This root will be included in the name of the output confusion table if crisscross is run with a single source 
      (single_src_post). If 'None' or empty then the element number source matched in the main_list is used in table name.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="wavdetect_file" type="file" filetype="input" stacks="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  The wavdetect output source table. If None, CrissCross will create one.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      The wavdetect source fits table(s) associated with the evt2 observation. This is the '*src.fits' file
        output from wavdetect. If no files are included (e.g., wavdetect_file=None) then wavdetect will be run during
        execution of CrissCross for each evt2 file provided.
	  </PARA>

	  <PARA>
      Wavdetect is run with a set input including binsize=2.0, bands='broad', and psfecf=0.9 and scales='1 2 4 8 16'. 
      These parameters are generally optimized for HETG observations to minimize the number of false (dispersed event) 
      detections. Users may wish to run wavdetect separately from crisscross with different parameters. In that case, 
      users should provide their choice of wavdetect source fits table to 'wavdetect_file'. Otherwise crisscross runs 
      with these default parameters. Depending on ones processor, running wavdetect may take some time so users can 
      reduce this by providing their own wavdect files.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="conf_table_level" type="string">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  The type of output to be saved to the confusion file for each subset_src_list source. Options are 'confused', 
      'warn' and 'clean'.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      The 'confused' option (default) includes spectral regions with high confidence of confusion. The 'warn' option 
      includes both confused regions and regions where confusion could have occured but the detection is marginal. 
      The 'clean' option includes 'confused', 'warn' and regions where there should be no confusion.
 
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="arf_ratios_dir" type="string" def="None">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      Path to ARF ratio fits tables that are necessary to estimate the number of counts expected in the nth order based 
      on the detected 0th order counts. 'None' value defaults to crisscross file.
	</SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
      The default parameter value of 'None' will used an arf ratios table designed for CrissCross and provided with CIAO. 
      It is based on the expected response ratios of an HETG source located at the ACIS-S aimpoint. Based on the number 
      of 0th order counts detected in a particular energy range, this file is used to estimate the number of nth (1,2,3) 
      order events at locations where confusion can occur. If a directory is input it will look for arf ratio tables 
      with a file format matching the default files.

      </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="max_pntsrc_dist" type="real" def="8">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Maximum distance in pixels to be considered a potential (0th order) point source confuser.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Field sources whose 0th order position is less than or equal to this distance, measured in ACIS pixels
        perpendicular from the dispersed spectrum of an extracted source, will be assessed as potential point source
        confusion (default: 8).
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="min_pntsrc_counts" type="real" def="5">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  0th order counts limit for field source to be assessed as a potential point source confuser.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Field sources with 0th order counts greater than this threshold will be assessed for potential point
        source confusion. This parameter can be used to save computation time by restricting the number
        of sources for which confusion is assessed.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="min_spec_counts" type="real" def="3">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Minimum number of 0th order counts required to calculate confusion for sources in subset_src_list or single_src_pos.
      This parameter can be used to save computation time by restricting the number
        of sources for which confusion is assessed.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Minimum number of 0th order counts for a source in subset_src_list or single_src_pos to be considered bright enough 
      warrant confusion assessment from field sources.This parameter can be used to save computation time by restricting
      the number of sources for which confusion is assessed.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="min_spec_confuser_counts" type="real"  def="50">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      0th order counts limit for field source to be assessed as potential sources of spectral confusion.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Minimum number of 0th order counts for a field source to be considered bright enough to disperse spectra and
        potentially contaminate the spectrum of source in subset_src_list or single_src_pos.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="osip_frac" type="real"  def="1.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Fraction of the OSIP window to use in spectral intersection calculation.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    When a confuser source disperses light that intersects with the spectrum of a source in subset_src_list, the 
        confused source's OSIP window at the ACIS-chip intersection location is used to determine the liklihood that events
        from the confuser source would cause confusion. This parameter represents a fraction from 0 to 1 denoting the 
        portion of an OSIP (Order Sorting Integrated Probability) range to be used in the spectral intersection 
        calculation. 1.0 means 100% of the OSIP window is used.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="spec_confuse_limit" type="real" def="0.1">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Fraction of dispersed counts allowed in a spectral confusion region before flagging as confused.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	   The fraction of dispersed events allowed in a spectral confusion region before deciding the region is
        contaminated (and thus later removed with clean_spec). A value of 0.1 means if confuser 'Src B' contributes
        more than 10% of counts in the confused portion of the spectrum of 'Src A' then the spectral region of Src A is
        flagged as confused. Note: The number of counts from each source in the affected spectral intersection region
        (wavelength range) is estimated using the HETG instrument effeciency (ARF) and the number of 0th order counts
        from each source within the wavelength range.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="max_arm_dist" type="real" def="8.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Maximum distance in pixels perpendicular to confused spectra to be considered as a potential arm confuser.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Two bright sources whose 0th order distance, measured in ACIS pixels perpendicular from one source to the
        dispersed spectrum of an extracted source, is less than this will be considered as potential arm confusion.
        Users can increase this parameter if they believe spectra are unfairly being flagged as arm confused. An
        on-axis source spectrum has a width of approximately 5 pixels so if two on-axis sources are within 10 pixels
        then it is possible they can cause confusion in eachother's spectra.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="arm_nsig" type="real" def="6.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      Approx for OSIP range for arm confusion. Higher values will ignore more of spectrum for arm confusion.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
      Approximation for how wide the OSIP range is for order sorting when determining which events are part of the
        Nth order spectrum. This parameter is for arm confusion only and increasing it will cause larger portions of a
        spectrum to be considered confused by arm confusion. Users should consider increasing this value up to ~10 if
        arm confusion appears to be missed with lower values.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="arm_confuse_limit" type="real" def="0.1">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Fraction of events allowed in arm confusion regions before flagging as confusion.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This fraction is based on 0th order counts ratio of each arm-confusion pair. For example, if the position and minimum
        brightness of two sources are sufficient to cause arm confusion with eachother, this ratio allows some confusion 
        in the subset_src_list spectrum without flagging it as confused. Arm confusion can result in the flagging of 
        significant portions of an extract sources spectrum so users may with to tolerate some fraction of erroneous events.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="min_arm_counts" type="real" def="50">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Min number of 0th order counts before a field source is considered a potential source of arm confusion.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	  While it depends on the spectrum, if a 0th order source has 50 counts then there are only approximately 
      (1.3 * 50) = 65 dispersed counts in the sum of all arms (HEG/MEG) and orders. This parameter can be increased if 
      the arm confusion flagging is too aggressive for the particular field and anticipated source spectra.
	  </PARA>

	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="meg_cutoff_low" type="real" def="1.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  MEG wavelength low boundary in Angstroms for all confusion calculations.  Confusion is not assessed outside bounds.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="meg_cutoff_high" type="real" def="32.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  MEG wavelength high boundary in Angstroms for all confusion calculations.  Confusion is not assessed outside bounds.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="heg_cutoff_low" type="real" def="1.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  HEG wavelength low boundary in Angstroms for all confusion calculations.  Confusion is not assessed outside bounds.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="meg_cutoff_low" type="real" def="16.0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  HEG wavelength high boundary in Angstroms for all confusion calculations.  Confusion is not assessed outside bounds.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>


      <PARAM name="highest_order" type="integer" def="3">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Determines which orders are included in the confusion calculations. '3' includes all orders. Options are '1','2' or '3'.
	</SYNOPSIS>

	<DESC>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>


      <PARAM name="min_tg_d" type="real"  def="-6.6e-4">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Lower bound of spectral extraction in cross-dispersion direction in degrees.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
        This parameters should be set to the same values used in `tg_extract` and they default
        to the default used in `tg_extract`. Crisscross assumes rectangular extraction regions.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="max_tg_d" type="real"  def="6.6e-4">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Upper bound of spectral extraction in cross-dispersion direction in degrees.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
        This parameters should be set to the value used in `tg_extract` and defaults
        to the default used in `tg_extract`. Crisscross assumes rectangular extraction regions.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean"  def="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Specifies if an existing output file should be overwritten.
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer"  def="0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Specifies the level of verbosity (0-5) in displaying
	  diagnostic messages.
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>



    <BUGS>
 
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>June 2026</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
