<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
   <ENTRY context="tools" key="dax" refkeywords="gui ds9 ds9tools ciaotools" seealsogroups="ds9">
   <SYNOPSIS>
       Run CIAO tasks from the ds9 Analysis menu
   </SYNOPSIS>


   <DESC>
      <PARA>
	A number of common CIAO tasks are available from the ds9
        Analysis menu.  This menu addition allows users to get source
        counts, smooth an image, and create a histogram - among many
        other things - from the ds9 program in CIAO.  The analysis
        menu tasks are known as "dax" (ds9 analysis
        extensions).
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Getting Started">
	The commands are stored in the file
	$ASCDS_CONTRIB/config/ciao.ds9 and are
	automatically loaded when ds9 is launched within CIAO.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The user can also explicitly point to the file in the ds9
	-analysis switch:	 
      </PARA>
      <VERBATIM>
unix% ds9 -analysis $ASCDS_CONTRIB/config/ciao.ds9 ...
      </VERBATIM>

      <PARA title="Using the Tools">
	Under ds9's Analysis menu, at the bottom will be a "CIAO tools (DAX)" 
	option.   Selecting "CIAO tools (DAX)" will display the category of CIAO tasks :
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM> 
           Statistics: calculates various statistics: min|max pixel value, 
           centroid, net-counts, and fully calibrated aperture photometry (for
           Chandra event  files). 
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Histograms: create spectra, lightcurves, and radial
	   profiles.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Coordinates: Obtain coordinates for a region center or crosshair 
           in various Chandra coordinate systems:  chips, detector, 
           sky, celestial. Also identify location of energies in 
           Chandra dispered grating spectra.           
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Regions: generate regions that enclose a fraction of flux,
	   magic-wand style source selector (local contouring), and 
       convex hulls.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Detect: run source detection tools on images.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
          Chandra PSF: look up the size of the Chandra PSF at a location,
          or determine the fraction of the PSF enclosed by a selected
          region.  Users can also simulate the PSF using MARX.        
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Sherpa: extract and fit spectra, 2D images, or radial profiles.
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
           Image Processing: adaptive smooth (including csmooth),
	   adaptive bin, smooth (various kernels), non-linear
	   filtering (median), fill in where sources have been removed
	   (dmfilth), and more options. 
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          Calculator: add, subtract, multiply, divide, scale, offset,
          and more.
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          Change DAX output directory: All outputs files are saved to
          a temporary directory; the default is $ASCDS_WORK_PATH/ds9_dax.$USER.
          Users can select a different directory.        
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
        Custom Color Map: users can create a custom color map (color lookup
        table).
        </ITEM>



      </LIST>

      <PARA title="Calculating the Statistics">
	The options under the Statistics item use the combination of
	all defined regions to calculate the quantities.  To exclude
	certain areas, define a region and use the "Region -&gt;
	Properties" menu to set it to "exclude".  If no regions are
	defined, the calculations are run on the entire image
	created at the current binning value. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Plotting">
    Plotting is done using the built in ds9 "BLT" plotting package.
    User can use the menu bar on the plot window to change
    the axes to log scale, change fonts and colors, etc.
      </PARA>


      <PARA title="Fitting">
   When fitting spectra, images, or radial profiles, users will 
   be presented with a model parameter editor before the fit is performed.
   Users can specify the initial value, change the limits, and thaw|freeze
   the parameters.  
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA title="Busy Indicator"> 
    Tasks which may take a while to run will launch a small window with
    the task name and a busy indicator (technically an indeterminate 
    progress bar).  To abort a running task, users need to select the 
    task again from the DAX menu. 
      </PARA>


</DESC>

<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.14.2 (April 2022) release">
  <PARA>
    The "Cross Correlate" option has been added, which uses the acrosscorr
    tool to compare two frames. This can be used to look for positional
    shifts between the two images.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    When working with a large region (such as many individual shapes or
    a polygon with many sides), dax will now save the region to a 
    temporary FITS region file.  This is to avoid problems with excessively 
    long virtual file name filters.
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.14.0 (December 2021) release">

  <PARA title="Button Bar">
  DAX makes use of the new ds9 "buttonbar" analysis menu option (new
  in ds9 v8.4).  Several of the most frequently used dax tasks are now
  available as buttons.  
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Automatically Launch Prism">
    For dax tasks that output tables or regions, users can now automatically 
    open those output files using ds9's prism interface.  To enable this
    options, users need to run this pset command before starting ds9:
  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
$ pset dax prism=yes
</VERBATIM>

  <PARA title="Output image block names">
    Previously, many of the output images would have the 
    block name set to the temporary file name.  Now, the image's
    block name is set to the tool which created the image.
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Sherpa">
    The sherpa spectral fitting tasks no allows the user to specify
    a second absorption model which is folded into the source expression.  
    In addition, the default absoprtion model has been changed to "xsphabs"
    (previously it was "xswabs").

  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Adaptive Binning">
    The new dmradar tool is available as the Image Processing -&gt;
    "Adaptive Bin (radial)" task.  The classic "Adaptive Bin" task
    (aka dmnautilus) also now has the new "method" parameter to 
    specify how many of the quadrants must exceed the SNR limit to be
    divided.
  </PARA>


</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.13.2 (June 2021) release">

  <PARA>
  The Sherpa -&gt; 2D Fitting task now allows users to specify
  a file name for the PSF and a file name for the exposure map to be 
  used when fitting the image.   Also renamed the model components 
  to "Model 1" and "Model 2" instead of "Source" and "Background" since
  what was called the "background" was not fit separately.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
  If an exception occurs during a sherpa fit() operation, the 
  text of the exception is now displayed in a dialog window.
  </PARA>
  
  <PARA>
  Added a random_seed parameter to dax.par.  This is currently used
  by the simulate_psf command; but available for future tasks which
  may need a random seed.  
  </PARA>


</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.13.1 (March 2021) release">
  <PARA>
    Added additional redshifted absorption spectral models.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    Added energy limits to the photon and energy flux calculations.
    Previously, the fluxes were computed for the entire energy range
    rather than for just the noticed energy range.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    Added button to run `conf` to the Model Editor GUI. 
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.13.0 (December 2020) release">
  <PARA>
    Updates to plotting spectral fit results to match changes 
    in sherpa.
  </PARA>

</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.12.4 (September 2020) release">

  <PARA>
  This is a major upgrade to DAX.  It includes several new analysis
  tasks, a new sherpa model parameter editor, visual busy indicators
  for long running tasks, and a few bug fixes.
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="New Tasks and Features"></PARA>

  <PARA>
    New  Detect -&gt; wavdetect task is now available.  Users select the
    wavelet scales which are used.  Note: This task can be very slow for
    large images.  wavdetect is run without an exposure map and without a 
    PSF map; therefore there will tend to be spurious source detected at the
    edge of the field of view and sources will be reconstructed using the
    smallest wavelet they were detected at (possibly smaller than PSF).
  </PARA>

    <PARA>
    New   Coordinates -&gt; Chandra Grating Energy Lookup.
    Users draw a region around the 0th order location; when this 
    task is run, it will prompt the user for a list of Energies and
    Orders.  The location of these energies and orders will be 
    identified on the image.   Only for Chandra observation which 
    used the gratings (HETG or LETG). 
  </PARA>


  <PARA>
    New Image Processing -&gt; Regrid task which allows the user to 
    shift, scale, and rotate image pixel values.  This task 
    intentionally does not adjust the WCS.  
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    New Image Processing -&gt; Reproject tasks will do a full, flux preserving, 
    reprojection of the image in the current frame to match the WCS
    in the previous frame.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    New Image Processing -&gt; Crop task.  While ds9 does support cropping,
    the WCS in the saved image does not correctly update the WCS for
    the cropped out region.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    New Chandra PSF -&gt; Simulate PSF with MARX task allows users to
    simulate a monochromatic PSF using MARX.  
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    New Create Custom Color Map task allows user to generate a
    new color map based on standard X11 color names, eg from black to 
    cadetblue, to white.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    New  Histogram -&gt; Dither Region computes the fraction of the
    region area exposed vs. time due to dither for Chandra datasets.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    New  Histogram -&gt; Enclosed Counts Fraction computes the ECF
    in the selected region.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    New  Calculator tasks allow users to perform simple arithmetic
    calculations (add, multiply, divide, subtract) using the images
    displayed in 2 frames.  Additional scaling functions are
    provided for the current frame.
  </PARA>


  <PARA title="Updates to Existing Tasks"> </PARA>

  <PARA>
  The Sherpa fitting tasks:  spectra, images, or radial profiles, 
    now launch a new model parameter editor.  Users can modify the
    initial model parameters, change the model limits, and thaw or
    freeze model parameters.  Users can also plot the model and data 
    easily before the fit to help refine the values.
  </PARA>


  <PARA>
    The spectral fit and radial fit tasks now use a common 
    set of plotting routines.  The plots have been rearranged
    so that the model is now drawn on top of the data.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    The list of spectral models has been expanded.  Users can
    also now specify a 2nd model component to be added to the
    first.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
    The Detect -&gt; celldetect task now allows users to change the
    fixed cellsize that is used.  Users can also now supply the 
    file name for an exposure map and a  PSF map.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    Most of the dax tasks are now run via a single wrapper script.  
    This means more uniform handling of regions and output files.  
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    Long running dax tasks will now launch a small "Busy Indicator" 
    window with the tool name and an indeterminate progress bar.
    Note: closing the busy indicator does not terminate the task.  
    To kill a running task users must reselect the same task.
  </PARA>


  <PARA title="Bug Fixes"></PARA>

  <PARA>
    Fix problem with Net Counts task where background counts
    and area are incorrectly reported as '0'.  Net rate errors 
    are now included in the Net Counts task.  Also now verifies a
    single unique instance of ds9 is running.
  </PARA>



</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.12.2 (April 2020) release">

  <PARA>
    Updated the CIAO -&gt; Regions -&gt; PSF Fraction task to force regions in
    ds9 format.  This update prevents dax from hanging when 
    users have modified their preferences to save regions in 
    ciao format.
  </PARA>

</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.11.3 (May 2019) release">
  <PARA>
  This release includes major changes to dax affecting most of the 
  individual analysis tasks.
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Output Files">
  Users can now select the directory where they want the DAX output file
  to be written.  There is a new dax.par parameter file where users 
  can specify the default output directory, outdir. Alternatively,
  user can set the DAX_OUTDIR environment variable, or they can 
  change the output directory via the new 'Change DAX output directory' 
  analysis task.
  </PARA>
  <PARA title="Statistics">
  </PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> Removed individual dmstat statistics</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted dmstat output</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted moments output</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Removed centroid snap task from menu</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Net counts are now computed for the selected regions (if any)
    or all regions if none are selected.  Also now uses the
    image as currently displayed rather (eg smoothed, filtered).</ITEM>
</LIST>

  <PARA title="Histograms">
  All of the histogram plots are now created using ds9 built-in
  "BLT" plotting package.  Users can use the options in the menu bar
  to save (print) the figure and adjust the plot style (linear|log, 
  fonts, colors).  All of the tasks also now save the output file 
  in the DAX_OUTDIR (as discussed above).
  </PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> New `convert_ds9_region_to_ciao_stack` script replaces
      old awk script to expand ds9 regions: panda, epanda, bpanda,
      mutli-radii annulus, multi-radii ellipse, mutli-radii box.
      Also handles excluded regions.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Radial profile task now uses image as displayed 
      (eg smoothed/etc) instead of original file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> User can now select pixels are arcsec for radial profile task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Extract along polygon now also plots data vs row-number,
      x, y, radius, or angle.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>

</LIST>  
  
  <PARA title="Coordinates">
  </PARA>
  <LIST>
    <ITEM> Removed individual coordinates; now always display all coordinates.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted 'All' coordinates </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Coordinates are now computed at:    
        The location of the crosshair, if in crosshair mode;
        Or, the center of the 1st selected circle|box|ellipse|annulus;
        Or, the center of the 1st non-selected circle|box|ellipse|annulus.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Chandra Field-of-View task now run inside a wrapper script
      so that any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>
  
  
  <PARA title="Detect"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> All detect tasks are now run with data as displayed 
      rather than going back to file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> All detect tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> celldetect is now run with fixedcell=12 </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>



  <PARA title="Region"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> All region tasks are now run with data as displayed 
      rather than going back to file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> All region tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> New `contour` task runs `dmcontour` to create regions at specified
      levels. Interior holes are automatically excluded.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved error checking in PSF Size task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Sherpa"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> Replaced chips plots with native ds9 blt plots.    </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Spectral fit now gives user the choice of      
        statistic (chi2gehrels|chi2xspecvar|cash|cstat|wstat),
        minimization method (levmar|neldermead|moncar),
        absorption model(xswabs|xsphabs)
    </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Removed clean cache task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> 2D Image fit now saves output model, residuals, and 
      fitting commands.  Model and Residuals are now displayed 
      in separate, tiled, frames.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> New Radial Profile Fit task.  Computes and fits radial profile
      with 1 or 2 additive model components from
      gauss1d|beta1d|const1d|lorentz1d|polynom1d|powlaw1d</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Image Processing"></PARA>
<LIST>
   <ITEM> All tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
   <ITEM> Updated Source Fill task to no longer rely on user Grouping
      source and background regions.  The script now requires 
      1-to-1 src-to-background region matches.</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Change DAX output directory">
  New task to allow users to change DAX output directory during the current
  analysis session. The directory selected is not saved.  Use 
</PARA>
<PARA>
  <SYNTAX><LINE>pset dax outdir=directory</LINE></SYNTAX>
</PARA>
<PARA>
  to permanently change the output directory.
</PARA>  

  
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.11.1 (December 2018) release">
  <PARA>
    Clarified error messages to indicate that users must have regions
    selected to perform spectral or spatial fits.  Additional
    internal changes to use python scripts to perform sherpa fits
    rather than using sherpa IPython wrapper.    
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.10.3 (October 2018) release">
<PARA>
      Updated to ensure that on systems where ds9 autoloads 
      funtools or zhtools analysis tools, that it is still able to 
      start the chipsServer in the background.
</PARA>
<PARA>
      Internal updates to support ds9 v8.
</PARA>
</ADESC>

<ADESC title="Change in the 4.8.4 (September 2016) release">
<PARA>
  Several tasks have been updated to ensure that the desired region
  format is retrieved from ds9 instead of relying on the assumed 
  defaults. 
</PARA>

</ADESC>



<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.6.7 (November 2014) release">
<PARA>
A new "Net Counts" option has been added that emulates the 
FUNTOOLs 'Counts in a region' functionality.  This provides
net counts and rates individually for each region.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The Aperture Photometry task has been renamed and moved.  It is now
available as the "Statistics -&gt; Photometry (srcflux)" task.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The "All" statistics have been renamed "dmstat" to make it more
clear which task is being run.
</PARA>
</ADESC>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="Known Limitations">
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  The stacked shapes (panda, annulus, elliptical annulus, box
	  annulus, etc.) only work with the radial profile task.
	</ITEM>        
      </LIST>
   </ADESC>

   <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
        website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
   </BUGS>

   <LASTMODIFIED>April 2022</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
