<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
   <ENTRY context="tools" key="dax" refkeywords="gui ds9 ds9tools ciaotools" seealsogroups="ds9">
   <SYNOPSIS>
       Run CIAO tasks from the ds9 Analysis menu
   </SYNOPSIS>


   <DESC>
      <PARA>
	A number of common CIAO tasks are available from the ds9
        Analysis menu.  This menu addition allows users to get source
        counts, smooth an image, and create a histogram - among many
        other things - from the ds9 program in CIAO.  The analysis
        menu tasks are known as "dax" (ds9 analysis
        extensions).
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Getting Started">
	The commands are stored in the file
	$ASCDS_INSTALL/contrib/config/ciao.ds9 and are
	automatically loaded when ds9 is launched within CIAO.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The user can also explicitly point to the file in the ds9
	-analysis switch:	 
      </PARA>
      <VERBATIM>
unix% ds9 -analysis $ASCDS_INSTALL/contrib/config/ciao.ds9 ...
      </VERBATIM>

      <PARA title="Using the Tools">
	Under ds9's Analysis menu, at the bottom will be a "CIAO tools (DAX)" 
	option.   Selecting "CIAO tools (DAX)" will display the category of CIAO tasks :
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM> 
           Statistics: use the defined regions to calculate
           counts, centroid, min pixel value, max pixel value, etc. 
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Histograms: create spectra, lightcurves, and radial
	   profiles, for example. 
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Coordinates: Obtain coordinates for a region center or crosshair 
           in various Chandra coordinate systems:  chips, detector, 
           sky, celestial.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Detect: run source detection tools on images.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Regions: generate regions that enclose a fraction of flux,
	   magic-wand style source selector (local contouring).
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Sherpa: extract and fit spectra, 2D images, or radial profiles.
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
           Image Processing: adaptive smooth (including csmooth),
	   adaptive bin, smooth (various kernels), non-linear
	   filtering (median), fill in where sources have been removed
	   (dmfilth), and more options. 
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA title="Calculating the Statistics">
	The options under the Statistics item use the combination of
	all defined regions to calculate the quantities.  To exclude
	certain areas, define a region and use the "Region -&gt;
	Properties" menu to set it to "exclude".  If no regions are
	defined, the calculations are run on the entire image
	created at the current binning value. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Plotting">
    Plotting is done using the built in ds9 "BLT" plotting package.
    User can use the menu bar on the plot window to change
    the axes to log scale, change fonts and colors, etc.
    
      </PARA>
</DESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.11.3 (May 2019) release">
  <PARA>
  This release includes major changes to dax affecting most of the 
  individual analysis tasks.
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Output Files">
  Users can now select the directory where they want the DAX output file
  to be written.  There is a new dax.par parameter file where users 
  can specify the default output directory, outdir. Alternatively,
  user can set the DAX_OUTDIR environment variable, or they can 
  change the output directory via the new 'Change DAX output directory' 
  analysis task.
  </PARA>
  <PARA title="Statistics">
  </PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> Removed individual dmstat statistics</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted dmstat output</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted moments output</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Removed centroid snap task from menu</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Net counts are now computed for the selected regions (if any)
    or all regions if none are selected.  Also now uses the
    image as currently displayed rather (eg smoothed, filtered).</ITEM>
</LIST>

  <PARA title="Histograms">
  All of the histogram plots are now created using ds9 built-in
  "BLT" plotting package.  Users can use the options in the menu bar
  to save (print) the figure and adjust the plot style (linear|log, 
  fonts, colors).  All of the tasks also now save the output file 
  in the DAX_OUTDIR (as discussed above).
  </PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> New `convert_ds9_region_to_ciao_stack` script replaces
      old awk script to expand ds9 regions: panda, epanda, bpanda,
      mutli-radii annulus, multi-radii ellipse, mutli-radii box.
      Also handles excluded regions.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Radial profile task now uses image as displayed 
      (eg smoothed/etc) instead of original file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> User can now select pixels are arcsec for radial profile task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Extract along polygon now also plots data vs row-number,
      x, y, radius, or angle.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>

</LIST>  
  
  <PARA title="Coordinates">
  </PARA>
  <LIST>
    <ITEM> Removed individual coordinates; now always display all coordinates.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Reformatted 'All' coordinates </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Coordinates are now computed at:    
        The location of the crosshair, if in crosshair mode;
        Or, the center of the 1st selected circle|box|ellipse|annulus;
        Or, the center of the 1st non-selected circle|box|ellipse|annulus.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Chandra Field-of-View task now run inside a wrapper script
      so that any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>
  
  
  <PARA title="Detect"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> All detect tasks are now run with data as displayed 
      rather than going back to file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> All detect tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> celldetect is now run with fixedcell=12 </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>



  <PARA title="Region"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> All region tasks are now run with data as displayed 
      rather than going back to file on disk.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> All region tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> New `contour` task runs `dmcontour` to create regions at specified
      levels. Interior holes are automatically excluded.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved error checking in PSF Size task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Sherpa"></PARA>
<LIST>
    <ITEM> Replaced chips plots with native ds9 blt plots.    </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Spectral fit now gives user the choice of      
        statistic (chi2gehrels|chi2xspecvar|cash|cstat|wstat),
        minimization method (levmar|neldermead|moncar),
        absorption model(xswabs|xsphabs)
    </ITEM>
    <ITEM> Removed clean cache task</ITEM>
    <ITEM> 2D Image fit now saves output model, residuals, and 
      fitting commands.  Model and Residuals are now displayed 
      in separate, tiled, frames.</ITEM>
    <ITEM> New Radial Profile Fit task.  Computes and fits radial profile
      with 1 or 2 additive model components from
      gauss1d|beta1d|const1d|lorentz1d|polynom1d|powlaw1d</ITEM>
    <ITEM> Improved Help</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Image Processing"></PARA>
<LIST>
   <ITEM> All tasks are now run inside a wrapper script so that
      any error messages/etc are shown.</ITEM>
   <ITEM> Updated Source Fill task to no longer rely on user Grouping
      source and background regions.  The script now requires 
      1-to-1 src-to-background region matches.</ITEM>
</LIST>

<PARA title="Change DAX output directory">
  New task to allow users to change DAX output directory during the current
  analysis session. The directory selected is not saved.  Use 
</PARA>
<PARA>
  <SYNTAX><LINE>pset dax outdir=directory</LINE></SYNTAX>
</PARA>
<PARA>
  to permanently change the output directory.
</PARA>  

  
</ADESC>



<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.11.1 (December 2018) release">
  <PARA>
    Clarified error messages to indicate that users must have regions
    selected to perform spectral or spatial fits.  Additional
    internal changes to use python scripts to perform sherpa fits
    rather than using sherpa IPython wrapper.    
  </PARA>
</ADESC>


<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.10.3 (October 2018) release">
<PARA>
      Updated to ensure that on systems where ds9 autoloads 
      funtools or zhtools analysis tools, that it is still able to 
      start the chipsServer in the background.
</PARA>
<PARA>
      Internal updates to support ds9 v8.
</PARA>
</ADESC>

<ADESC title="Change in the 4.8.4 (September 2016) release">
<PARA>
  Several tasks have been updated to ensure that the desired region
  format is retrieved from ds9 instead of relying on the assumed 
  defaults. 
</PARA>

</ADESC>



<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.6.7 (November 2014) release">
<PARA>
A new "Net Counts" option has been added that emulates the 
FUNTOOLs 'Counts in a region' functionality.  This provides
net counts and rates individually for each region.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The Aperture Photometry task has been renamed and moved.  It is now
available as the "Statistics -&gt; Photometry (srcflux)" task.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The "All" statistics have been renamed "dmstat" to make it more
clear which task is being run.
</PARA>
</ADESC>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="Known Limitations">
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  The stacked shapes (panda, annulus, elliptical annulus, box
	  annulus, etc.) only work with the radial profile task.
	</ITEM>        
      </LIST>
   </ADESC>

   <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
        website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
   </BUGS>

   <LASTMODIFIED>May 2019</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
