<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY pr "unix&#37;">
]>

<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="fluximage" context="tools"
	 refkeywords="flux fluxed exp exposure img image map
	              exposure-map exposuremap expmap emap
		      photon erg time unit units
		      correct corrected normalize normalized xygrid
		      band bands combine merge mergeall merge-all merge_all
		      csc soft medium hard broad wide weight weights
		      spectral spectrum background bkg particle time subtract scale
		      BEVTFILE BKGMETH BKGSCALE STATFILT"
	 seealsogroups="mergescripts"
	 displayseealsogroups="resptools">
    
    <SYNOPSIS>
      Create exposure-corrected images and exposure maps for an observation.
    </SYNOPSIS>
    
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The fluximage script creates exposure-corrected images of
	an ACIS or HRC observation given an events file and one or more
	energy bands. It automates the creation of the aspect histogram,
	instrument, and exposure maps. 
	The output image size can be 
	automatically chosen to cover all the data in the observation,
	or it can be set to match an existing image.
	For HRC-I observations, the HRC background files from the Chandra
	CALDB are used - if installed - to subtract off the particle background and so
	reduce the
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/expmap_hrci/index.html#caveat">ring
	artifacts</HREF> that can be seen in HRC-I data
	(this can be turned off by setting the hidden background parameter
	to "none").
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	For recently-processed data the script can be run with only
	two parameters: for example
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	creates a number of files in the directory out/, including
	the exposure-corrected image, out/broad_flux.img (ACIS)
	or out/wide_flux.img (HRC).
      </PARA>
      
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; download_chandra_obsid 1843</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; cd 1843</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro indir=. outdir=repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage . fluxed/</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; ds9 fluxed/broad_flux.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we download ObsId 1843 from the Chandra archive (an
            ACIS observation), reprocess
	    it using chandra_repro, and then create an
	    exposure-corrected image of the
	    data using the CSC broad band (0.5 to 7 keV with an effective
	    energy of 2.3 keV) in the directory
	    fluxed/ (this directory will be created if it does not
	    exist). As the infile parameter is set to a directory,
	    the script searches for any files that match the
	    pattern "./repro/*evt*", "./primary/*evt*", then
	    "./*evt".
	    In this case the script picks
 	    repro/acisf01843_repro_evt2.fits.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The output image contains all ACIS ccds that were
	    on in the observation and has been binned to 8 ACIS pixels
	    (so an output pixel scale of 3.936 arcseconds on a side).
	    The events file is used to locate all the necessary files
	    (which, due to chandra_repro, have all been copied to the repro/
	    directory).
	    Finally ds9 is used to view the exposure-corrected
	    image, the name of which includes the energy range, effective
	    energy used and the binning factor.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Note that reprocessing your data - whether via chandra_repro or
	    manually - is not required to use fluximage. It does however
	    ensure that the necessary keywords are included in the
	    events file (old data may be missing
	    one or more of the keywords used to identify the ancillary data
	    files) and that the latest calibrations have been applied.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/acisf01843_repro_evt2.fits fluxed/</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This is a repeat of the previous example except that the
	    event file to use is listed explicitly as the infile
	    parameter value.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Specifying the exact file to use is necessary when using
	    interleaved-mode observations, since there are two event
	    files in the directory. For instance:
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage 10551/repro/acisf10551e1_repro_evt2.fits out/e1</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage 10551/repro/acisf10551e2_repro_evt2.fits out/e2</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; ds9 out/e1_broad_flux.img out/e2_broad_flux.img &amp;</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
	  
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/ fluxed/ binsize=4 clobber+</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; ds9 fluxed/broad_flux.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we repeat the analysis but use half the bin
	    size (4 instead of 8, giving a pixel size of 1.968 arcseconds on a side).
	    The clobber mode has been set to yes to ensure the output from the
	    previous example does not call the script to fail.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage "evt2.fits[ccd_id&lt;4]" acisi/ binsize=2</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here a Data Model filter is used to restrict the output to
	    the ACIS I array (ie ccd_id values of 0 to 3).
	    The output image axis range is calculated so that it just covers the data
	    in the input events file (after applying any Data Model filters).
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The script will reflect any previous filtering applied to the file,
	    so the following will create the same output (the use of clobber
	    ensures that the existing data will be over-written):
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; dmcopy "evt2.fits[ccd_id&lt;4]" acisi.evt</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage acisi.evt acisi/ binsize=2 clobber=yes</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=csc,broad</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example four separate exposure-corrected images
	    are created: one each for the CSC soft, medium, hard and
	    broad energy bands. As with the previous example the names
	    of the ancillary files - such as bad-pixel file and aspect
	    solution - are read from the header of the events file.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Since the outroot does not end with a / character then
	    the the output files will be created in the same directory
	    as the events file, with names like
	    fimg_soft_flux.img.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    It is also possible to run the script once for each band;
	    so the following is equivalent to the single run above:
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=soft</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=medium</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=hard</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=broad</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; make_instmap_weights wgts.txt "xsphabs.gal*powlaw1d.pl" \</LINE>
	  <LINE>     paramvals="gal.nh=0.45;pl.gamma=1.7" emin=0.5 emax=7 ewidth=0.25</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg/ bands=wgts.txt</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; ds9 fimg/band1_flux.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example we use a weights file (wgts.txt), 
	    created by make_instmap_weights, so that the
	    exposure map is the weighted sum of a range of
	    energies rather than evaluated at a single energy.
	    The output files will be labelled "band1", so the
	    exposure-corrected image will be called "fimg/band1_flux.fits".
	    The energy range used to create the images is
	    calculated from the contents of the weights file,
	    so in this case 0.5 to 7 keV.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=csc,0.5:7:3,wgt1.dat,wgt2.dat</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we combine the three different forms for specifying
	    an energy band - using a label ("csc"), an explicit range
	    ("0.5:7:3"), and weights files ("wgt1.dat" and "wgt2.dat")
	    to create 6 exposure-corrected images.
	    The files using the weights file "wgt1.dat" are labelled
	    "band1" and those using "wgt2.dat" are labelled "band2".
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; download_chandra_obsid 6202</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; cd 6202</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; chandra_repro indir=. outdir=repro</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/ fluxed/</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; ds9 fluxed/wide_flux.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we use a HRC-I observation,
	    for which the default "bands=default" setting
	    is the same as setting "bands=wide".
	    The "wide" band uses all events (since the spectral
	    response of HRC-I is so broad), and evaluates the exposure
	    map at an energy of 1.5 keV.
	    The default binning value for HRC data is 32.
	    If the 
	    Chandra CALDB package "HRC background event files" is installed
	    then the appropriate background file will be subtracted
	    from your data in order to 
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/expmap_hrci/index.html#caveat">ring
	    artifacts</HREF> that can be seen in HRC-I data.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
            When background subtraction is used, the BEVTFILE
            keyword is set to the the name of the background event file; for
            example:
	  </PARA>
          <PARA>
            <SYNTAX>
              <LINE>&pr; dmkeypar fluxed/wide_flux.img BEVTFILE echo+</LINE>
              <LINE>/data/CALDB/data/chandra/hrc/bkgrnd/hrciD2005-01-01bkgrndN0002.fits</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    To turn off this step, set the background parameter to "none";
	    e.g.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; pset fluximage background=none</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/hrcf00144_repro_evt2.fits fluxed2/</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage hrcf00144_repro_evt2.fits fluxed/ bands=30:200:1.1 bin=16</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Band limits can also be given for HRC observaitons, but the lower
	    and upper limits are in PI channels rather than energy.
	    Here we specify the PI limits to use for the images (30 to 200), with 
	    the exposure map created at 1.1 keV.
	    The final image is called fluxed/30-200_flux.img and uses
	    a bin size of 16 HRC pixels (2.1088 arcseconds).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fi_ bands=csc xygrid=acisi/broad.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we use multiple bands (csc is a short form for "soft,medium,hard"),
	    write files to the current directory with a prefix of "fi_" (rather than
	    to a separate directory), and use the xygrid parameter to
	    make the data match the sky area covered by the
	    acisi/broad.img (in this case the result of a previous run of
	    the script but it can be any file which can be processed by the
	    get_sky_limits script).
	    The binsize parameter is not used in this case.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; pset fluximage xygrid="3428.5:5476.5:2,6874.5:7898.5:2"</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits zoom</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we explicitly give the grid for the output images.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/ fluxed/ parallel=no</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this case, by setting parallel to no, only a single
	    processor will be used.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage repro/ fluxed/ nproc=-1</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The nproc parameter allows you to control the number of
	    processors that are used; in this case (nproc=-1), 
	    all-but-one of them (if your machine has 4 processors then
	    nproc=3 could be used instead).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg badpixfile=caldb</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we use the bad-pixel file in the CALDB, rather than the
	    observation-specific bad-pixel file (the value of the BPIXFILE
	    keyword in evt2.fits).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits fimg bands=0.5:6:2 parallel=no</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; ds9 fimg_0.5-6_flux.img</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here a manually-specified band is used - 0.5 to 6 keV with
	    an effective energy (that is, the energy used to calculate
	    the exposure map), of 2 keV.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The computation only uses a single processor since the
	    parallel parameter is set to no.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out badpixfile=bpix1.fits asolfile=@asol.lis</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example most of the ancillary data files are specified explicitly rather than
	    read in from the header of the events file.
	    The aspect solution is read in from the stack of files listed in
	    the file asol.lis (see 
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/stack.html">'ahelp stack'</HREF>
	    for more information on this syntax)
	    and the bad-pixel file is taken from bpix1.fits.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    As the maskfile is "", the parameter events file evt2.fits
	    will be used to determine the file by using the MASKFILE parameter.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage "evt2.fits[sky=box(4096,4096,600,600)]" acisi/ binsize=0.25</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here the exposure-corrected image is created using pixels that are a quarter the width
	    of the default ACIS pixel. A spatial filter has been applied to restrict
	    the calculation to a small area around the aim point of the observation,
	    since this is where the Chandra spatial resolution is high enough to
	    make this analysis worthwhile.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits qlook_ units=time</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we use the units parameter to create an exposure map which
	    has units of seconds, so the exposure-corrected image will
	    have units of
	    count/s. In this case the monochromatic setting used as part
	    of the bands setting is ignored; that is bands=broad and
	    bands=0.5:7:1 will produce the same output (since they
	    both use an energy filter of 0.5 to 7.0 keV).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="infile" type="file" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  The events file to use.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The events file can include Data Model filters to
	    restrict the area used, or the chips processed; for example
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>infile="evt2.fits[sky=region(clus.reg)]"</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    This file is used to determine the location of the ancillary
	    files - such as aspect solution and bad-pixel file - if they
	    are not
	    explicitly given. If you have used chandra_repro to reprocess
	    your data then all the necessary files will be in the same
	    directory as the reprocessed events file.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="Using a directory name">
	    If the infile parameter is set to a directory name - 
	    e.g. "repro" or "." - then the following search is
	    made, where dirname represents the directory name used:
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>dirname/repro/*evt*</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>dirname/primary/*evt*</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>dirname/*evt*</ITEM>
	  </LIST>
	  <PARA>
	    The script will display which file it finds.
	    If there are no matches, or multiple matches
	    in the same directory then
	    the script will fail.
	    DataModel filters - such as "[ccd_id=0:3]" - can not
	    be used when only a directory name is given.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="outroot" type="string" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Root name for the output files.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the
	    parameter ends in "/" then the output files are placed
	    in this directory (which will be created if necessary),
	    otherwise it is prepended to the file names, with a "_" added.
	    So, with bands=broad and outroot=fi/ the 
	    exposure-corrected image is
	    called fi/broad_flux.img whereas with outroot=fi the file
	    is fi_broad_flux.img.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    An empty outroot value, or one set to ".", will cause the
	    output files to be written to the current working directory
	    with no prefix.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="bands" type="string" def="default">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  What energy or PI band, or bands, should be used?
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The script will create an exposure-corrected image - 
	    along with supporting data products - for each band.
	    A band can be given using a name (which will
	    use the appropriate definitions from the Chandra Source
	    Catalog), by explicit limits, or by giving
	    the name of a file containing the spectral weights
	    (see <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/make_instmap_weights.html">ahelp 
	    make_instmap_weights</HREF>).
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    For the first two options, 
	    the names for the output files are created using the
	    minimum and maximum limits for each band.
	    When using a weights file, the output files are
	    labelled using "band1" to "bandn", where n is the number
	    of weights file given to the parameter. 
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA title="The default setting">
	    The value of 'default' is converted to 'broad' for
	    ACIS data and 'wide' for HRC data.
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA title="Band names">
	    The following names - based on the definitions from the
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/csc/columns/ebands.html">Chandra Source Catalog</HREF>
	    - can be used; energies are given in keV and the effective
	    energy is the monochromatic energy used to calculate the exposure map for the band:
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Band name</DATA><DATA>Minimum Energy</DATA><DATA>Maximum Energy</DATA><DATA>Effective Energy</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>broad</DATA><DATA>0.5</DATA><DATA>7.0</DATA><DATA>2.3</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>soft</DATA><DATA>0.5</DATA><DATA>1.2</DATA><DATA>0.92</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>medium</DATA><DATA>1.2</DATA><DATA>2.0</DATA><DATA>1.56</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hard</DATA><DATA>2.0</DATA><DATA>7.0</DATA><DATA>3.8</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>ultrasoft</DATA><DATA>0.2</DATA><DATA>0.5</DATA><DATA>0.4</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>wide</DATA><DATA>n/a</DATA><DATA>n/a</DATA><DATA>1.5</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	  
	  <PARA title="CSC">
	    The value "csc" can be used as a short form for the
	    combination of "soft,medium,hard".
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA title="Explicit ranges">
	    If you want to use different values to those of the CSC then
	    you can use the format lo:hi:eff where
	  </PARA>

	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW><DATA>Value</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA></ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>lo</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The minimum value to use: for ACIS this value is in
		keV and must be given, for HRC it is in PI channels
		and can be left blank.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hi</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The maximum value to use: for ACIS this value is in
		keV and must be given, for HRC it is in PI channels
		and can be left blank.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>eff</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The effective energy for the instrument map and exposure
		map, in keV. This is required for both ACIS and HRC
		observations.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	  
	  <PARA title="Spectral weights">
	    If a filename is given then it is assumed to be an ASCII
	    file containing spectral weights; two colums giving the
	    energy in keV and the weight value for that energy.
	    This file can be created using the make_instmap_weights script,
	    the save_instmap_weights() routine from the
	    sherpa_contrib.utils module, or manually; see the description
	    of the 
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/mkinstmap.html#plist.spectrumfile">spectrumfile
	    parameter of mkinstmap</HREF>
	    for more information on the format of this file.
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA>
	    The energy limits to use for the images are calculated from
	    this file. If the file contains two lines (before the data)
	    with the format
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE># ENERG_LO = elo</LINE>
	      <LINE># ENERG_HI = ehi</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    then the elo and ehi values are taken for the limits (they
	    are assumed to be in keV). This format is created by
	    the make_instmap_weights script and the save_instmap_weights()
	    routine.
	    If these lines do not exist, or the elo/ehi values are not
	    valid numbers, then the limits will be calculated from
	    the first column using the formulae (x1 is the
	    first value, xn is the last, and xm the last-but-one value):
	    <EQUATION>elo = (3 * x1 - x2) / 2</EQUATION>
	    <EQUATION>ehi = (3 * xn - xm) / 2</EQUATION>
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA title="Multiple bands">
	    Multiple bands can be given either by using the name "csc"
	    or by using a comma-separated list. The different schemes
	    can be combined, so the following are all valid
	    (where wgt1.dat and wgt2.dat are weights files):
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>bands="csc,broad"</LINE>
	      <LINE>bands="0.5:7:2.5,ultrasoft"</LINE>
	      <LINE>bands="0.5:7:2.5,csc,wgt1.dat,wgt2.dat"</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    At present multiple bands can not be used with HRC data.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="xygrid" type="string" def="">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  xygrid for output or filename
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    When left at the default (empty) value, the 
	    script calculates the xygrid for the output
	    image based on the observational data; the
	    skyfov tool is used to determine the maximum
	    area of the sky that is covered by the
	    input data. In this mode the bin size is
	    determined by the binsize parameter.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    When set, it can either be:
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>a filename,</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>a grid specification of the form
	    "xlo:xhi:#nx or dx,ylo:yhi:#ny or dy".</ITEM>
	  </LIST>
	  <PARA>
	    If a filename is given then its sky
	    range is used to determine the output;
	    this is useful if you want to create an
	    exposure-corrected
	    image that matches an existing image.
	    Otherwise the grid range is given explicitly;
	    examples include "3824.5:5112.5:#161,4008.5:5296.5:#161"
	    and "3824.5:5112.5:8,4008.5:5296.5:8".
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="binsize" type="real" def="INDEF" min="0">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Image binning factor
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter is only used when xygrid is set to ""
	    (which is the default setting).
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    When set to INDEF a default value is used: 
	    8 for ACIS data and 32 for HRC data.
	    The binning factor has units of the 
	    SKY pixel (0.492" for ACIS and 0.1318" for HRC),
	    so binsize=4 for an ACIS observation will create
	    images with 1.968 arcsecond pixels.
	    The value need not be an integer, and can be less
	    than 1 if you want to look at small-scale structure near
	    the aim point of the observation; in this case it is strongly
	    suggested that a spatial filter is applied to ensure 
	    manageable file sizes.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>    
      
      <PARAM name="asolfile" type="file" stacks="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Aspect solution for the observation.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the value is empty then the ASOLFILE keyword from
	    the events file will be used to find the
	    file(s) to use. 
	    Unlike the other ancillary products, an aspect
	    solution is required for the script to run.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The aspect solution files have names like
	    pcadf*_asol1.fits and are included in the
	    output directory of the chandra_repro script.
	    If multiple asol files exist for the observation
	    and you want to explicitly select them - rather than
	    use the file names given in the ASOLFILE keyword - then use
	    the stack syntax (e.g. a comma, or space, separated
	    string as described in
	    <HREF
		link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/stack.html">"ahelp
	    stack"</HREF> for more information).
	    So to use asol1.fits and asol2.fits you could say
	    <EQUATION>asolfile="asol1.fits,asol2.fits"</EQUATION>
	    or
	    <EQUATION>asolfile="asol1.fits asol2.fits"</EQUATION>
	    The files do not have to be given in time order.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Aspect histograms - the output of the asphist tool - can
	    not be used here.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="badpixfile" type="file">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Input bad pixel file
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the
	    parameter is empty then the 
	    BPIXFILE keyword in the events file will be used.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    A value of "CALDB" will use the CalDB bad-pixel
	    file and "NONE" will use no bad-pixel file
	    (the value is case insensitive).
	    The bad-pixel file is not required to run the
	    script, but care should be taken when analyzing the
	    output if it is not used.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The bad-pixel file has a name like
	    acisf*bpix1.fits and is included in the
	    output directory of the chandra_repro script.
	    If you have used or created a custom bad-pixel file 
	    for the observation then this should
	    be used.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="maskfile" type="file">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Mask file for the observation.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the 
	    parameter is empty then the 
	    MASKFILE keyword in the events file will be used.
	    A value of "NONE" will use no mask file in the
	    analysis; in this case care should be taken when
	    analyzing the results since the exposure map
	    will not be correct if the data was taken
	    using a sub array (i.e. not all the chips or ccds
	    were read out).
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The mask file has a name like
	    acisf*msk1.fits and is included in the
	    output directory of the chandra_repro script.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="dtffile" type="file">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Input dtf file for HRC observations
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>This parameter is only used with HRC observations.</PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    If the 
	    parameter is empty then the 
	    DTFFILE keyword in the events file will be used.
	    A value of "NONE" will mean that only a mean
	    DTF value will be used.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The parameter block has a name like
	    hrcf*dtf1.fits and is included in the
	    output directory of the chandra_repro script.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="units" type="string" def="default">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Units for the exposure map
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter determines the units of the instrument
	    and exposure maps.
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>units</DATA><DATA>Exposure map</DATA><DATA>Exposure-corrected image</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>default</DATA><DATA>cm^2 s count / photon</DATA><DATA>photon / cm^2 / s</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>area</DATA><DATA>cm^2 count / photon</DATA><DATA>photon / cm^2</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>time</DATA><DATA>s</DATA><DATA>count / s</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter combines the normalize parameter of
	    mkexpmap and the modifiers for the detsubsys and mirror
	    parameters of mkinstmap (see 'ahelp ardlib').
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="Converting from the normalize parameter">
	    To replicate the old normalize=no setting, use units=default
	    and for normalize=yes use units=area.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="What is units=time equivalent to?">
	    When units=time is used, instrument maps are created with
	    the additional settings:
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>
	      ";IDEAL" is appended to the
	      detsubsys parameter to remove any correction for the
	      detector quantum efficiency (QE), quantum efficiency
	      uniformities (QEU), 
	      or the ACIS contamination model;
	    </ITEM>
	    <ITEM>
	      the mirror parameter is set to "HRMA;area=1" rather than
	      "HRMA" to ignore the effective area of the Chandra mirrors;
	    </ITEM>
	    <ITEM>
	      and the dafile parameter is set to "NONE" to 
	      remove the ACIS "dead area" correction, which accounts for
	      the (small) decrease in detector efficiency due to the
	      background cosmic ray flux.
	    </ITEM>
	  </LIST>
	  <PARA>
	    The result is that the instrument map pixels have values of
	    0 or 1.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="expmapthresh" type="string" def="1.5%">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Remove low-exposure regions?
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If set to "" then no clipping of the counts image
	    or exposure map
	    is performed before creating the exposure-corrected
	    image.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    When set, the parameter determines how the 
	    counts image and exposure map
	    are clipped before being combined together to
	    create the exposure-corrected image.
	    This can be used to  exclude those
	    pixels at the edge of a chip which, due to the
	    strong gradient in the exposure map, end up
	    dominating the final image.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    For a full list of supported options, see the
	    description of the cut parameter of dmimgthresh.
	    Here we discuss the two most common options:
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>
	      expmapthresh="2%", which excludes those pixels where the
	      exposure map falls below 2% of its peak value,
	    </ITEM>
	    <ITEM>
	      and expmapthresh="100", which excludes those pixels where
	      exposure map value is less than 100 (in this case the 
	      value of the units parameter is important).
	    </ITEM>
	  </LIST>
	  <PARA>
	    Note that both the counts image and the exposure map
	    are thresholded before being combined.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="background" type="string" def="default">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Method for background removal (HRC-I)
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter is only used for HRC-I data.
	    The reason for subtracting the particle background
	    component is to help 
	    remove the 
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/expmap_hrci/index.html#caveat">"rings" seen in exposure-corrected HRC-I data</HREF>,
	    but does significantly increase the time
	    taken to run the script.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    If set to "none", or no HRC-I background CALDB
	    file can not be found, then the data is processed with
	    no background subtraction. 
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="method=default">
	    This is the same as method=time.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="method=time">
	    This setting scales the background file by the
	    ratio of the observation to background exposure
	    times. It is the method used in the thread
	    discussed above.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA title="method=particle">
	    This option scales
	    the background by the ratio of the counts
	    in the range determined by the bkgparams
	    parameter, rather than by exposure
	    time.
	  </PARA>

          <PARA title="Header keywords">
            The full path to the selected background event file is
            added to the header file of the background-subtracted image
            and fluxed image using the BEVTFILE keyword.
	    The scaling method and factor are added to the relevant files
	    using the BKGMETH and BKGSCALE keywords, respectively.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="bkgparams" type="string" def="[pi=300:500]">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Optional argument for background subtraction
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This is only used when background subtraction occurs
	    and the method being used is set to "particle".
	    The parameter is taken to be 
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/dmfiltering.html">a
	    Data Model filter</HREF>
	    to apply to both the observation and the 
	    particle background file, and is expected to
	    be of the form "[pi=lo:hi]". It is used to select
	    a subset of the observation that represents
	    the particle background - i.e. it is 
	    not strongly
	    "contaminated" by cosmic emission - but
	    is close enough (in PI) to the source emission
	    to minimise differences in the spectral shape of
	    the particle emission between the observation and
	    that seen in the background observations.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="psfecf" type="real" def="INDEF" min="0" max="1">
	<SYNOPSIS>
          If set, create PSF map with this ECF
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
            If set, create a "PSF map" image, which contains the radius
            of the PSF which contains this ECF for each pixel, in
            arcseconds. The calculation is done by the mkpsfmap
            tool, and the energy is taken to be the same value used
            to create the exposure maps (the effective energy described
            in the the bands parameter or the weight file).
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            The output file is identified by the label "psfmap".
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="random" type="integer" def="0" min="0">
        <SYNOPSIS>
          Random seed for randomization.  
        </SYNOPSIS>

         <DESC>
           <PARA>
	     The random parameter is sent to reproject_events
	     when processing the HRC-I background files to
	     match the observation. A value of 0 uses the
	     system time to seed the random number generator.
           </PARA>
         </DESC>
      </PARAM>
 
      <PARAM name="parallel" type="boolean" def="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Run processes in parallel?
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    When run on a multi-processor system, many of the
	    tasks can be run in parallel to reduce the
	    execution time of the script.
	    Since the tasks are likely to be memory or I/O-bound,
	    the reduction in run time will be less than the
	    number of cores on a machine.
	    When parallel=yes, the default behaviour is to use all
	    the CPU processors, but this can be changed with
	    the nproc parameter.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    This option can be ignored when run on a single-processor
	    system.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="nproc" type="integer" def="INDEF">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Number of processors to use
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter is only used when parallel=yes. It determines
	    the number of processors to use. If maxproc is the actual
	    number of processors on your machine, then
	    a value of INDEF - the default value - means that all
	    maxproc processors will be used.  A positive value
	    means to use that number of processors (any value
	    larger than maxproc will be set to maxproc).
	    A negative value is added to maxproc (and any value less
	    than one is set to one).
	  </PARA>
	  <!--
	      <TABLE>
	      <CAPTION>
	      The number of processors to be used
	      for a variety of nproc and maxproc values (assuming parallel=yes).
	      </CAPTION>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>nproc argument</DATA>
	      <DATA>maxproc</DATA>
	      <DATA>number of processors used</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>INDEF</DATA>
	      <DATA>4</DATA>
	      <DATA>4</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>INDEF</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>INDEF</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>3</DATA>
	      <DATA>4</DATA>
	      <DATA>3</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>3</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>3</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-1</DATA>
	      <DATA>4</DATA>
	      <DATA>3</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-1</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-1</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-2</DATA>
	      <DATA>4</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-2</DATA>
	      <DATA>2</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      <ROW>
	      <DATA>-2</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      <DATA>1</DATA>
	      </ROW>
	      </TABLE>
	  -->
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="tmpdir" type="string" def="${ASCDS_WORK_PATH}">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Directory for temporary files. 
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Directory for storing temporary files that
	    require further processing before becoming useful.
	    If the directory does not exist then it will be created
	    for use by the script, and then deleted.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="cleanup" type="boolean" def="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Cleanup intermediary files on exit.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If set to "yes", the intermediate data products
	    are deleted when the script ends, leaving only the counts
	    image, clipped counts image, combined exposure map,
	    and exposure-corrected image.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Overwrite existing files?
	</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Output verbosity.
	</SYNOPSIS>
	
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The default verbosity value of 1 prints status
	    messages as the script runs.  Higher verbosity
	    settings print the commands that are being run.
	    Setting verbose=0 turns off most of the screen
	    output (some output is currently unavoidable).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Energy bands">
      <PARA>
	The energy bands - when given by name - are taken from the
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/csc/columns/ebands.html">Chandra Source Catalog definitions.</HREF>
	The default bands setting (i.e. "default") means
	to use the "broad" band setting for ACIS data 
	and the "wide" band setting for HRC data.
	Another common choice (for ACIS data) is "csc", which 
	creates the "soft", "medium", and "hard" bands.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	Examples of specifying the bands are:
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/ bands=soft</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/ bands=csc</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/ bands=csc,broad</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; fluximage evt2.fits out/ bands=wgt.dat</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	which use
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>the default band (so broad for ACIS, wide for HRC),</ITEM>
	<ITEM>the soft band,</ITEM>
	<ITEM>the CSC bands (i.e. soft, medium, and hard),</ITEM>
	<ITEM>and four bands (soft, medium, hard, and broad),</ITEM>
	<ITEM>and a spectral-weights file (wgt.dat), created either manually
	or with the make_instmap_weights script.</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	The examples and description of the
	bands parameter describe how either
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>
	  explicit energy or PI ranges and
	  effective energies,
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  or a spectral weights file
	</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	can be specified.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Parallel processing">
      <PARA>
	When analyzing an observation with multiple chips (ACIS) or
	HRC-S plates, or if using multiple energy bands, the
	execution time can be reduced by running some steps in
	parallel. This is controlled by the parallel flag,
	which defaults to yes.
	The nproc parameter controls the number of processors that will be used;
	the default is to use all of then.
	If run on a single-processor machine then both
	parameters are ignored.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Output files">
      <PARA>
	The primary output files are named using the following scheme:
      </PARA>
      
      <TABLE>
	<ROW><DATA>Flag</DATA><DATA>Type</DATA><DATA>Filename</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>E</DATA><DATA>Counts image</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel.img</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>E</DATA><DATA>Exposure map</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel.expmap</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>T</DATA><DATA>Optional PSF map (thresholded)</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel_thresh.psfmap</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>E</DATA><DATA>Optional PSF map (no threshold)</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel.psfmap</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>C</DATA><DATA>Clipped counts image</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel_thresh.img</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>C</DATA><DATA>Clipped exposure map</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel_thresh.expmap</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>A</DATA><DATA>Exposure-corrected image</DATA><DATA>outroot_blabel_flux.img</DATA></ROW>
      </TABLE>
      
      <PARA>
	where blabel is either the band name (e.g. soft, broad, ...),
	"lo-hi" where lo and hi are the limits of the 
	range (keV for ACIS, PI for HRC), or band1 to bandn (when using spectral
	weight files).
	The Flag column indicates when the file is created (when cleanup=yes):
	A indicates always, T is for when the expmapthresh parameter is
	set, and E is for when the the expmapthresh parameter is empty.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The above is when outroot does not end in a "/"; if it does then
	remove "outroot_" and the files will be created in the directory
	named by outroot. Examples of the exposure-corrected image
	name for a combination of bands and outroot settings are given
	in the following table:
      </PARA>
      
      <TABLE>
	<CAPTION>Names of the exposure-corrected images</CAPTION>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>outroot</DATA>
	  <DATA>bands=broad</DATA>
	  <DATA>bands=0.5:2:1.5 (ACIS)</DATA>
	  <DATA>bands=30:200:1.1 (HRC)</DATA>
	  <DATA>bands=wgt.dat</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>fimg</DATA>
	  <DATA>fimg_broad_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>fimg_0.5-2_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>fimg_30-200_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>fimg_band1_flux.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>odir/</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/broad_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/0.5-2_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/30-200_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/band1_flux.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>  
	  <DATA>odir/fimg</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/fimg_broad_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/fimg_0.5-2_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/fimg_30-200_flux.img</DATA>
	  <DATA>odir/fimg_band1_flux.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
      </TABLE>
      
      <PARA>
	For HRC data, using bands=::eval results in a label
	of "all" being used.
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	The intermediary files follow the same rule for outroot and have
	the form given below, where ccd refers to the plate number for HRC
	data:
      </PARA>
      
      <TABLE>
	<ROW><DATA>Type</DATA><DATA>Filename</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>Aspect histograms</DATA><DATA>outroot_ccd.asphist</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>Instrument maps</DATA><DATA>outroot_ccd_blabel.instmap</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>Per chip/plate exposure maps</DATA>
	  <DATA>outroot_ccd_blabel.expmap</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>HRC-I image (no background subtraction)</DATA>
	  <DATA>outroot_unsubtracted.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>HRC-I image of the particle background</DATA>
	  <DATA>outroot_particle_bgnd.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>HRC-I image after background subtraction</DATA>
	  <DATA>outroot.img</DATA>
	</ROW>
      </TABLE>      
      
      <PARA>
	By default, the intermediary per-chip data products are
	removed after the script has completed running. To save
	these (potentially numerous) files, set the cleanup
	parameter to 'no'. 
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>     
    
    <ADESC title="Output image area and size">
      <PARA>
	The default behavior - when xygrid="" - is to calculate the output image
	size so that it covers all the data:
	a FOV file is created for the observation and the limits
	of this file are used to determine the X and Y range
	of the image.
	In this mode the binning is set by the binzise parameter, is 
	in units of the native pixel size (i.e. 0.492" for
	ACIS and 0.1318" for HRC), and can be set to sub-pixel
	values (e.g. 0.5).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The tool can also be given an explicit grid for the output
	image size using the xygrid parameter (in this mode the binsize
	parameter is ignored). The grid can either be:
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>a filename,</ITEM>
	<ITEM>or a grid specification, of the form "xlo:xhi:#nx or dx,ylo:yhi:#ny or dy".</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	When given a file, the sky range of the file is used for
	the output (e.g. the get_sky_limits tool is run on the
	file and its xygrid parameter value is used).
	Otherwise, the grid is given using the same format as the
	xygrid parameter of mkexpmap; examples include:
	<EQUATION>3824.5:5112.5:8,4008.5:5296.5:8</EQUATION>
	and
	<EQUATION>3824.5:5112.5:#161,4008.5:5296.5:#161</EQUATION>
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	If the requested grid results in the last row or column being
	partially filled - in other words the width or height divided by the
	bin size is not a whole number - then the exposure map values in the
	column or row will be over estimated (since they are calculated assuming
	that the pixel is "full").
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	The default binsize parameter value (of default) is
	equivalent to 8 (ACIS) or 32 (HRC) pixels.
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA title="Handling filter or grids that do not overlap the observation">
	The tool will error out when there is no overlap between the observation
	and the xygrid (if given) or any spatial filter applied to the input file.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Required data files">
      <PARA>
	For observations that has been reprocessed by chandra_repro, then
	all that is needed is to give the events file since the
	required ancillary files can be found using the
	header of the events file (the chandra_repro script ensures
	that all the files needed for this script are copied to the same
	directory as the events file).
	These ancillary files can be located in one of the following
	directories, relative to the events file:
      </PARA>
      
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>.</ITEM>
	<ITEM>repro/</ITEM>
	<ITEM>primary/</ITEM>
	<ITEM>secondary/</ITEM>
	<ITEM>../repro/</ITEM>
	<ITEM>../primary/</ITEM>
	<ITEM>../secondary/</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      
      <PARA>
	If the files are not in one of these directories, they
	have been renamed, or new versions have been created during
	your analysis (e.g. a new bad-pixel file or a reprojected 
	aspect solution created
	by reproject_aspect) then
	they can be explicitly set using the following parameters:
      </PARA>
      
      <TABLE>
	<CAPTION>Ancillary data products</CAPTION>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>Parameter name</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>asolfile</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The aspect solution for the observation, which may be
	    split over multiple files.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>badpixfile</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The bad-pixel file for an observation. If set to CALDB then
	    the bad-pixel file in the Chandra CalDB will be used rather
	    than the observation-specific version. If set to NONE then
	    the instrument map, and hence exposure map, will be created
	    with no bad pixels.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>maskfile</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The mask file for an observation. This determines the active area of each
	    CCD or chip (e.g. if a sub-array was used).
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>dtffile</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The Dead-Time Factor correction file for HRC observations.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
      </TABLE>
      
      <PARA>
	The only required information is that provided by the
	aspect solution file(s); any other file can be ignored,
	(either explicitly, by setting the parameter to NONE, or
	implicitly because it can not be found), in which case the appropriate
	correction or information is ignored.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Processing steps">
      <PARA>
	The script primarily makes use of the asphist, mkinstmap, and
	mkexpmap tools; generally following the outline of the
	"Step-by-Step Guide" sections of the "Exposure
	Maps" threads of the <HREF link="https://cxc.cfa.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/imag.html">"Imaging"
	science analysis threads</HREF>.  The following steps are taken to create the data products:  
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>skyfov and get_fov_limits: to determine the output image area</ITEM>
	<ITEM>dmcopy: to create an events image with the specified binning factor</ITEM>
	<ITEM>hrc_bkgrnd_lookup, reproject_events, and dmimgcalc: to subtract the particle background (HRC-I only)</ITEM>
	<ITEM>asphist: to build the aspect histogram(s)</ITEM>
	<ITEM>mkinstmap: to calculate the instrument map(s) for the effective energy given for each energy band</ITEM>
	<ITEM>mkexpmap: to calculate the exposure map(s) in each energy band</ITEM>
	<ITEM>dmimgcalc: to combine the exposure maps if there are multiple ACIS CCDs or HRC-S plates</ITEM>
	<ITEM>dmimgthresh: to make a "threshold cut" before dividing the image by the exposure map, to reduce the noise at the edge of the chip (optional)</ITEM>
	<ITEM>dmimgcalc: to normalize the image by the exposure map</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA title="Background subtraction of HRC-I data">
	HRC-I data will have an estimate of the particle background
	subtracted from the data before dividing by the exposure map
	if the background parameter is not set to none
	and the CALDB "HRC background event files" package is
	installed.
	This step is intended to reduce the 
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/expmap_hrci/index.html#caveat">ring
	artifacts</HREF> that can be seen in HRC-I data. The
	raw files used to create the background-subtracted image
	are retained when the cleanup parameter is set to no.
	In this case, assuming the output fluxed image is called
	wide_flux.img, then
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
      <EQUATION>wide_flux.img = wide_thresh.img / wide_thresh.expmap</EQUATION>
      <EQUATION>wide_thresh.img = wide_unsubtracted.img - s * wide_particle_bgnd.img</EQUATION>
      <EQUATION>scale_time = observation exposure time / particle background exposure time</EQUATION>
      <EQUATION>scale_particle = observation counts PI=300:500 / particle background counts PI=300:500</EQUATION>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	where the thresholding step has been ignored for
	simplicity and s=scale_time (method=default) or s=scale_particle (method=particle).
	The backgtround method and scaling factor are written to the header
	of the relevant files as the BKGMETH and BKGSCALE keywords.
	The name of the background event file used is stored in the BEVTFILE keyword.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="STATUS filtering">
	The STATUS filter used to create the observation event file
	is used to filter the particle background file; this
	value is displayed on screen and written to the background
	files as the STATFILT keyword.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.11.1 (December 2018) release">
      <PARA>
        The script will now create a PSF map for the observation if the
        psfecf parameter is set.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.2 (January 2016) release">
      <PARA>
	The random parameter has been added. It is used to control the
	random parameter of reproject_events when background subtracting
	HRC-I data.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.1 (December 2015) release">
      <PARA>
        The code has been updated to avoid warning messages from
        NumPy version 1.9. There is no difference to how the
        script behaves.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.6 (September 2014) release">
      <PARA title="Minor improvements">
	There have been minor improvements to error messages and 
	better support for data with missing keywords, such as that
	produced by 
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/dictionary/marx.html">Marx</HREF>.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.5 (June 2014) release">
      <PARA title="Filtering the aspect solution by the event file GTI">
	The skyfov is run in order to calculate the sky range covered
	by each observation; e.g. see
	<HREF
	    link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/get_fov_limits.html">ahelp
	get_fov_limits</HREF>. The aspect solutions are now filtered
	by the good-time intervals (GTI) of the event file - that is, the script sets
	<EQUATION>aspect=asol1.fits[@evt.fits]</EQUATION>
       (assuming the aspect solution is called asol1.fits and the
       event file evt.fits) when calling skyfov. This should not
       change most results but may produce slightly-smaller 
       output images in cases where the GTI of the observation 
       covers only a small fraction of the aspect solution.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="HRC-I analysis">
	It is now possible to apply a PI filter range for the
	images by specifying PI limits in the bands parameter, that
	is bands=30:200:1.2 will use a PI range of 30 to 200
	when creating all the imaging products. The monochromatic
	energy used for the instrument map is still given in keV,
	so 1.2 keV in this example.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	A new subtraction method, which scales the
	background to match the data using the ratio of the
	counts in the band PI=300:500 (this can be
	changed with the new bkgparams parameter), can be selected by setting
	method=particle. The default method uses the exposure
	times of the observation and particle background files for
	the scaling.
	The scaling method and factor are added to the relevant files
	using the BKGMETH and BKGSCALE keywords, respectively.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The status filter used to filter the HRC-I particle background
	file is now included in the screen output at the default
	verbosity level and added to the particle background
	files (retained when cleanup=no) using the STATFILT keyword.
	The background-unsubtracted files retained when cleanup=no
	now match the documentation (rather than include the
	typo 'undsubtracted').
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.3 (March 2014) release">
      <PARA title="Removing individual instrument-map files">
	The per-chip instrument map files are now deleted when
	cleanup=yes and multiple bands were supplied.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="HRC-I background files">
	The original and background-subtracted images
	are now retained when cleanup=no; they are named
	outroot_unsubtracted.img 
	and
	outroot_particle_bgnd.img respectively.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.2 (February 2014) release">
      <PARA>
        There have been some internal changes to try and avoid
        incompatibilities between CIAO and FTOOLS parameter files.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Setting maskfile to NONE">
	The bug which meant that maskfile could not be set to "NONE"
	has been fixed.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="The BEVTFILE keyword for HRC-I datasets">
        The BEVTFILE keyword is added to HRC-I datasets when background
        subtraction is used; it contains the name of the background event
        file used.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.1 (December 2013) release">
      <PARA title="Removal of the pbkfile parameter">
	The pbkfile parameter has been removed as it is no longer needed
	to run mkinstmap on ACIS observations.
	This means that it is no longer possible to turn off the 
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/why/acisdeadarea.html">ACIS dead-area correction</HREF>
	for the exposure map; users who need this flexibility
	will have to generate the exposure maps manually (e.g.
	the 
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/expmap_acis_single/">ACIS single-chip thread</HREF>).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	For old data sets the removal of the pbkfile parameter can lead to 
	error messages about missing keywords;
	in this case please download the latest archive version of your
	observation with download_chandra_obsid and then reprocess with chandra_repro.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="mkinstmap obsfile parameter">
	The mkinstmap tool is now run with the obsfile parameter set to the
	observation event file rather than the aspect histogram for the chip or
	plate.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.5.4 (August 2013) release">
      <PARA>
        The description of the bands parameter has been updated to point out
        that when using the explicit format - e.g. a:b:c - for an energy band
        then the a and b values are required for ACIS data but should not be
        set for HRC data.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        The handling of files with a DataModel filter has been improved.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.5.2 (April 2013) release">
      <PARA title="Aspect solutions">
	The program now checks that the aspect-solution files are
	not aspect histograms.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.5.1 (December 2012) release">
      <PARA>
	The script has been updated to work in CIAO 4.5.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
	See the
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/fluximage.html">bugs page
	for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
	listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2018</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
