<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY 
        context="tools" 
        key="map2reg" 
        refkeywords="map mask bin group region convert display" 
        seealsogroups="dmimgtools"
        displayseealsogroups="regiontools"
    >
    <SYNOPSIS>
        Convert a map file into a region file.
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
        <PARA>
        This script creates a polygon region around each 
        unique set of pixel values in the input map file.
        The `dmimglasso' tool is used to identify the 
        polygons.  The polgyons may contain multiple components
        if there is a hole in the interior (eg a separate
        group completely surrounded by another group).
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        This script assumes that all groups are contiguous.  If 
        a group is split into multiple disjoint sections then
        only 1 of those sub-groups will be processed.        
        </PARA>
        
        <PARA>
        Only pixel values greater than zero (&gt;0) are considered.
        Pixel values equal to zero are considered as being ungrouped.            
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        This script runs in parallel; though for a large number of unique
        map IDs it can still be slow.
        </PARA>

        <PARA>
        The map values in the infile are not the same as the
        COMPONENT values in the output region file.
        </PARA>
    </DESC>
     <QEXAMPLELIST>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
            % map2reg hex.map hex.reg 
            % ds9 hex.map -region hex.reg
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            Convert the map file,  hex.map, into an ASC-FITS format
            region file, hex.reg.  We then use ds9 to display
            the results.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>

     <PARAMLIST>
        <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Input map file.
            </SYNOPSIS>
            <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The map file should contain integer pixel values which
                represent which pixels are grouped together.
                Pixel values equal to 0 are ignored (treated as being
                ungrouped).  
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
          <SYNOPSIS>Output region file</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The output is stored as an ASC-FITS format region
                file.  Each map ID in the input image will be output
                as one or more polygons.  The map ID is 
                not stored (it is not guaranteed to be the COMPONENT 
                value).  Each component may have interior polygons
                excluded if they completely surround another 
                group (or an ungrouped area).
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="parallel" type="boolean" def="yes" reqd="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>Run code in parallel using multiple processors?</SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            If multiple processors are available, then 
            this parameter controls whether the tool should 
            run various underlying tools in parallel.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>        
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="nproc" type="integer" def="INDEF" min="1" reqd="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>Number of processors to use</SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            If parallel=yes, then this controls the number of
            processes to run at once.  The default, INDEF,
            will use all available processors.  The value
            cannot be larger than the number of processors.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>        
      </PARAM>

        <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Amount of chatter from the tool.
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Delete outfile if it already exists?
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <BUGS>
        <PARA>
            See the
            <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
            website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
        </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <LASTMODIFIED>August 2023</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
