<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY 
        context="tools" 
        key="pathfinder" 
        refkeywords="gradient ascent steep steepest map mask adaptive bin group max tessellation" 
        seealsogroups="dmimgtools"
    >
    <SYNOPSIS>
       Group pixels by steepest gradient ascent to local maximum
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
        <PARA>
        For each pixel, identify the maximum neighboring pixel.  Those form a group.
        Continue from that maximum to identify it's maximum neighbor which
        is then added to the group and so on.    When the algorithm finds a
        local maximum which already belongs to a group, the new group is
        abandoned and the pixels are added to the existing group. The process 
        is repeated until the pixel being processed is the local maximum.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        The input image should be modestly smoothed such that the 
        local maxima are statistically significant.        
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
        This algorithm can be helpful to separate region based on the 
        "saddle-point" (where the gradient goes to zero).  For example it
        helps find the natural separation point between point-likes sources
        with different intensities (or different extent); rather than
        simply using the mid-point between them, it uses the gradient
        to assign pixel ownership to one-or-the-other.        
        </PARA>

    </DESC>

     <QEXAMPLELIST>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
                % pathfinder smoothed.img out.map 
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The smoothed infile, smoothed.img, is processed through 
            the path-finding algorithm.  The outfile, out.map, 
            contains the group ID for each local maxima.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
                % pathfinder smoothed.img out.map direction=perpendicular
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            Same as above; however this time restrict the search for
            neighboring maxima to only 4 pixels: top, bottom, left, right.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>

     <PARAMLIST>
        <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Input image.
            </SYNOPSIS>
            <DESC>
            <PARA>The image to be grouped.  Generally this 
            algorithm works better if it is moderately smoothed.
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
            Null  and NaN pixels, as well as those pixels outside the
            image subspace will not be grouped.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>

        <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
          <SYNOPSIS>
            Output map file
          </SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
              The outfile is a map file containing integer pixel values.
              The pixel values indicate which pixels are grouped
              together by the algorithm.  A pixel value of 0 are pixels
              which are ungrouped (ie outside the image subspace or below minval).           
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>

<!--
        <PARAM name="binimg" type="file" filetype="output">
          <SYNOPSIS>Optional, output binned image</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
                If the binimg file is specified, the script
                will use the input image and the output map file to
                create a binned version of the input image.
            </PARA>          
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
-->

        <PARAM name="minval" type="real" def="0">
          <SYNOPSIS>
          Minimum pixel value to group
          </SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            Pixels values less than minval will be left ungrouped.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>

        <PARAM name="direction" type="string" def="diagonal">
          <SYNOPSIS>Direction to follow gradient: perpendicular or diagonal</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            When searching for the neighboring pixel with the maximum 
            value, the tool will just consider just the 4 perpendicular
            pixels (top, bottom, left, right) of the current pixel, 
            or can consider all 8 adjacent pixels including the diagonal
            pixels.            
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>


        <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Amount of chatter from the tool.
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Delete outfile if it already exists?
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>


    <BUGS>
        <PARA>
            See the
            <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
            website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
        </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <LASTMODIFIED>January 2019</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
