<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY pr  'sherpa>'>

  <!ENTITY chart2 '<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/PSFs/chart2">ChaRT2</HREF>'>

]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="plot_chart_spectrum" context="contrib" pkg="sherpa"
	 refkeywords="plot draw chart spectrum spectra file psf simulate simulation"
	 seealsogroups="sh.plot sh.chart">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Plot up the model spectrum in the form required by ChaRT
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>plot_chart_spectrum(id=None, elow=None, ehigh=None, ewidth=None, norm=None)</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The plot_chart_spectrum() command creates a plot of the current model
	values in the form expected by &chart2;
	(the Chandra Ray Tracer).
	Please see the
	<HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/prep_chart/">ChaRT preparation thread</HREF>
	for further information on how to use this routine.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Loading the routine">
        The routine can be loaded into Sherpa by saying:
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
from sherpa_contrib.chart import *
</VERBATIM>

      <TABLE>
	<CAPTION>Arguments</CAPTION>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>Name</DATA><DATA>Default value</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>id</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>Which dataset to use: if None then the value returned
	  by get_default_id() will be used.</DATA>
	</ROW>

	<ROW>
	  <DATA>elow</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The minimum energy at which to evaluate the model; this parameter
	    controls the lower edge of the lowest-energy bin, and is in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the lowest energy bin from the
	    ARF grid. This value should not be smaller than 0.2 keV.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>ehigh</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The maximum energy at which to evaluate the model; this parameter
	    controls the upper edge of the highest-energy bin, and is in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the highest energy bin from the
	    ARF grid. This valus should not be larger than 10 keV.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>ewidth</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The bin width to use, in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the bin width from the
	    ARF grid.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>norm</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    A scaling factor to allow you to easily change the overall flux
	    of the model. A value of None is equivalent to a factor
	    of 1; a value of 10 would create a ChaRT spectral model ten times
	    brighter than the input model.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>overplot</DATA>
	  <DATA>False</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    If True then the data is added to the current plot,
            otherwise a new plot is created.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>clearwindow</DATA>
	  <DATA>True</DATA>
	  <DATA>
            If True then clear out the current plot area of all
            existing plots. This is not used if overplot is set.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>

      </TABLE>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>&pr; plot_chart_spectrum()</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>

          <PARA>
	    Create a plot of the model for the default dataset using the units
	    expected by &chart2;.
	  </PARA>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>&pr; plot_chart_spectrum(elow=1, ehigh=8)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    In this example the plot  is restricted to the range 1 to 8 keV, using the default
	    binning given by the ARF grid. Note that this energy range need not overlap the
	    range used to fit the data (or even the energy ranges of the ARF and RMF files).
	    It should however remain within the range 0.2 to 10 keV.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.11.4 (2019) release">
      <PARA title="Plotting can now use matplotlib">
	The plot_chart_spectrum() routine now uses the
	Sherpa plot backend (controlled by the plot_pkg setting in
	a user's ~/.sherpa.rc file), rather than always using ChIPS.
	As part of this update the extra labelling in the plot - that
	gave the model name and dataset identifier - have been
	removed (although the model name is now included in the plot
	title). 
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Optional arguments">
	The overplot and clearwindow optional arguments have been added
	to plot_chart_spectrum.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.2 (January 2016) release">
      <PARA>
	The plot style is now a histogram rather than a curve.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>June 2019</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
