<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="psfsize_srcs" context="tools"
         refkeywords="psf chandra point spread function prf size fraction energy bands ecf eef enclosed circle coordinates"
         seealsogroups="psftools"
         displayseealsogroups="" >
    <SYNOPSIS>
        Compute the size of a circle enclosing a specified fraction of PSF.
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
        <PARA>
            `psfsize_srcs' will compute the size of a circle
            that encloses the specified fraction of the PSF 
            at the specified energy for each of the input positions.            
        </PARA>
    
        <PARA>
            Users input a position as either a single RA/Dec pair or provide 
            a table
            with RA and Dec columns.  ASCII files can be used as long as
            they are readable by the DM ASCII kernel. (see ahelp dmascii).
            The header keyword information in the infile is used
            to convert the RA and Dec values to mirror coordinates (theta and
            phi) which are used together with the energy and ecf parameters
            to determine the output circle size.
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
            The output file is an ASC-FITS-REGION format file with 
            that can be used as input to other CIAO tasks or 
            ds9 can be used to display the regions.
        </PARA>

    
    </DESC>
    
    <QEXAMPLELIST>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>psfsize_srcs evt.fits "10:04:33.8 +41:12:34" myout.fits energy=broad ecf=0.9</LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>            
                This is an example where the tool computes a circle whose radius
                encloses 90% of the PSF at 2.3 keV (CSC 'broad' band energy) for
                the specified RA/Dec value.  The information in the evt.fits
                file is used to setup the coordinate transforms from 
                RA/Dec to mirror coordinates (theta and phi).  The output
                file will contain an ASC-FITS-REGION file with a
                SHAPE, X, Y, R column.  X, Y, and R are all returned in
                physical pixels.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>

        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>psfsize_srcs evt.fits "151.1410079341,41.2096249008" myout.fits energy=1.0 ecf=0.9</LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>            
                This example we now specify the energy explicitly as 1.0 keV
                and use decimal degrees rather than sexagesimal notation.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>

        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>psfsize_srcs evt.fits "wavdetect.fits" myout.fits energy=wide ecf=0.68</LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>            
                In this example the pos parameter is now specified as a file name,
                in this case the source list output from wavdetect.  Since it has
                RA and Dec columns they will be used.  The size of the
                circle will enclose 68% of the PSF fraction at the
                Chandra Source Catalog's 'wide' band energy of 1.5keV.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>

        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>psfsize_srcs evt.fits "csc_output.tsv[opt kernel=text/tsv]" myout.fits energy=broad ecf=0.50</LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>            
                ASCII files can also be input if they are compatible with
                the DM ASCII kernel.  In this example we use an output from
                the Chandra Source Catalog stored in tab-separated-value format
                (TSV).  This format requires the user specify the 
                kernel option as shown.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>    
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>
        <PARAM name="infile" type="file" reqd="yes" filetype="input" stacks="no">
            <SYNOPSIS>Input image or event file</SYNOPSIS>
            <DESC>
                <PARA>
                  The header keywords in the infile file are used to
                  setup all the coordinate transforms needed to go from
                  celestial coordinates to mirror coordinates.  The
                  following keywords need to be present:

                </PARA>
                <PARA>
                INSTRUME, DETNAM,  RA_NOM, DEC_NOM, RA_PNT, DEC_PNT, ROLL_PNT, 
                SIM_X*, SIM_Y*, SIM_Z*, DY_AVG*, DZ_AVG*, DTH_AVG*, 
                FIRSTROW**, NROWS**
                </PARA>

                <PARA>
                * are optional, but should be present to get accurate
                estimates of the CHIP coordinates.  They do not
                affect mirror coordinates nor the output size.  ** are
                also optional.  If they are not present, eg for HRC
                datasets, then the output "near_chip_edge" may be
                inaccurate for ACIS subarray datasets.
                </PARA>
                

                <PARA>
                The input file should not be a merged event file or
                co-added image.  In particular the *_NOM and *_PNT 
                values of those products may be insufficient to 
                get the information needed for the coordinate transforms.
                </PARA>

            </DESC>        
        </PARAM>
    
        <PARAM name="pos" type="string" reqd="yes" def="" stacks="no" units="J2000">
          <SYNOPSIS>RA and Dec value or filename with RA and Dec values </SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
             <PARA>

            The input position must be in celestial coordinates.  It can either be
            input as an RA/Dec pair, or as a filename.
                </PARA>
                <PARA title="Single Set of Values">
                If a single RA/Dec value pair is input, then they 
                can be in either decimal degrees or in 
                sexagesimal format.  Positive declinations expressed in
                sexagesimal format must include the "+" sign.  Decimal degrees should 
                be separated by a comma.
                </PARA>
                
                <TABLE>
                  <ROW>
                    <DATA>Good</DATA>
                    <DATA>Bad</DATA>
                  </ROW>   
                  <ROW>
                    <DATA>10:04:33.8 +41:12:34</DATA>
                    <DATA>10:04:33.8 41:12:34</DATA>
                  </ROW>
                  <ROW>
                    <DATA>10 04 33.8 +41 12 34</DATA>
                    <DATA>10 04 33.8 41 12 34</DATA>
                  </ROW>
                  <ROW>
                    <DATA>151.1410079341,41.2096249008</DATA>
                    <DATA>151.1410079341 41.2096249008</DATA>
                  </ROW>
                  <ROW>
                    <DATA>151.1410079341,41.2096249008</DATA>
                    <DATA>10 04 33.8,41.2096249008</DATA>
                  </ROW>
                </TABLE>
                
                <PARA title="Filename">
                If a filename is specified, the tool will look for
                the columns named "RA" and "DEC".  If they do not
                exist, the first two columns in the file are used.
                Columns may be renamed on the fly using DM virtual
                file syntax.  The following examples are all valid file names
                </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
wavdetect.fits
some_catalog.fits[cols ra=ra_j2000,dec=dec_j2000]
some_catalog.txt[flux=1e-5]
cscview_output.tsv[opt kernel=text/tsv]
</VERBATIM>


          </DESC>
                
        </PARAM>
    

        <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" reqd="yes" def="" stacks="no" filetype="output">
          <SYNOPSIS>The output file name</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The output file is an ASC-FITS-REGION format file that
            contains the output source size in the "R" (radius) column.
            As is the convention, the units of the X, Y, and R columns
            are stored in physical pixels.  The SHAPE column is 
            always a 'circle' and the COMPONENT number is simply a
            integer going from 1 to N, where N is the number of input
            positions.
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            The following columns are also created representing the
            various coordinate transforms:
          </PARA>
            <LIST>
              <ITEM>RA and DEC : original location expressed in decimal degrees</ITEM>
              <ITEM>THETA and PHI : off axis angle away from and around the optical axis</ITEM>
              <ITEM>DETX and DETY : Chandra Focal Plane coordinates</ITEM>
              <ITEM>CHIP_ID, CHIPX, CHIPY : Chandra instrument coordinates.  If the optional
              SIM keywords are missing from the infile, these coordinates will not
              be accurate.</ITEM>
            </LIST>


          </DESC>
        
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="energy" type="string"  def="broad" stacks="no">
          <SYNOPSIS>Single energy or CSC energy band</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            A single energy value or the name of a single energy band may
            be input.
            </PARA>          
                    
	  <PARA title="Band names">
	    The following names - based on the definitions from the
	    <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/csc/columns/ebands.html">Chandra Source Catalog</HREF>
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Band name</DATA><DATA>Effective Energy [keV]</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>broad</DATA><DATA>2.3</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>soft</DATA><DATA>0.92</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>medium</DATA><DATA>1.56</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hard</DATA><DATA>3.8</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>ultrasoft</DATA><DATA>0.4</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>wide</DATA><DATA>1.5</DATA>
	    </ROW>

	  </TABLE>

    <PARA title="Single Energy">
    Alternatively, any single monochromatic energy, in keV can be specified.
    The value should be between 0.2 and 10.0 keV.    
    </PARA>
            
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>


        <PARAM name="ecf" type="real"  def="0.9" stacks="no" min="0.0" max="0.999">
          <SYNOPSIS>Fraction of PSF to enclose</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            The output region will contain a circle region that
            encloses this fraction of the PSF.    The PSF technically has
            infinite extent so a value of 1.0 would create an infinitely
            large region.  Typical values will be 0.5 (50%, ie FWHM), 0.68 (68%, ie 1
            sigma), and 90%.  
            </PARA>
          
          </DESC>
        
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="psffile" type="file" filetype="input"  def="CALDB" stacks="no">
          <SYNOPSIS>The PSF calibration file name</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The name of the Chandra Radially Encircle Energy Fraction
                calibration file.  The default, 'CALDB', will signal the
                tool to look for the file in the Chandra Calibration Database.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer"  def="0" min="0" max="5">
          <SYNOPSIS>Tool chatter level</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
          Controls the amount of information tool prints to the screen.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean"  def="no" >
          <SYNOPSIS>Remove outfile if it already exists?</SYNOPSIS>        
        </PARAM>
    
    
    </PARAMLIST>


    <ADESC title="Changes in CIAO 4.7.2 (April 2015) release">
      <PARA>
        Standard HISTORY records have been added for this tool.  
        There is also a correction for the "near_chip_edge" 
        calculation for ACIS subarray datasets.
      </PARA>
    
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="Caveats">
        <PARA title="REEF File Calibration Approximations">

            The Chandra point spread function varies significantly
            across the field of view and also as a function of energy.
            It becomes highly elliptical and contains many sharp
            features that makes providing an accurate 2D analytic model 
            impossible.    The
            The calibration file used, the REEF (radially enclosed energy
            fraction) file, was created assuming a flat detector.  This is 
            accurate for HRC and for ACIS-7, but the other ACIS CCDs are 
            tilted and cause additional asymetries.
                    
        </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/">bug
        pages</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
 
    <LASTMODIFIED>March 2015</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
