<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY context="Tools::Region" key="regphystocel" 
   refkeywords="region coordinates physical celestial ds9 fk5 wcs world coordinate convert ascii" 
   seealsogroups="detecttools regiontools"
   >
    <SYNOPSIS>Convert regions in physical coordinates to ds9 format regions in
    celestial (fk5) coordinates.
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>`regphystocel' will convert a region file stored in physical coordinates
      into a ds9-format region file using celestial coordinates.  Most 
      CIAO tools can make use of regions in either physical or celestial
      coordinates.  However, when working with multiple observations with
      possibly different tangent plane projection parameters, using 
      celestial coordinates may be necessary.  This is the case when using
      the srcflux script with multiple observations.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
      The input region file can be either a FITS region file 
      or an CIAO ASCII region file.  The infile can also just be
      a region string.      
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
      The tool takes position and radius (in physical pixels) of each 
      shape and applies the world coordinate system (WCS) transform.      
      The angle is not modified (always measured counter-clockwise from the
      +X axis).  If using a FITS region file, it may contain the WCS
      necessary to do the conversion to celestial coordinates; otherwise
      users can supply an image or event file as the wcsfile parameter.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Limitations">
      CIAO regions support complex region logic using logical AND and logical
      OR operations; the ds9 format does not support this.  The following
      shapes are not supported:  'field', 'pie', and 'sector'.      
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Text and Tags">
      Regions stored in the ds9 format can have a title that will
      optionally be displayed above the region.  They can also have 
      one or more "tags" which allows the user to group 
      sources together; users can access the list of groups by 
      going to Region -&gt; Groups ... from the ds9 main menu.
      When using a FITS region file regphystocel can take values from
      columns or keywords and populate the title or tags properties.        
      </PARA>



    </DESC>
    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>
% regphystocel ciao.reg ds9.reg wcsfile=img.fits
           </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
The ASCII region stored in the file "ciao.reg" is converted to celestial 
coordinates using the WCS from the "img.fits" file.  The output is
written to "ds9.reg" which will look similar to this:
</PARA>
<VERBATIM>
# Region file format: DS9 version 4.1
global color=green dashlist=8 3 width=1 font="helvetica 10 normal roman" select=1 highlite=1 dash=0 fixed=0 edit=1 move=1 delete=1 include=1 source=1
fk5
ellipse(01:13:51.0473,13:16:17.8925,1.26168",1.17667",25.8786)
</VERBATIM>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>
% regphystocel fov.fits fov.reg
           </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
              The FITS region file "fov.fits" is converted to celestial
              coordinates using the WCS provided in the file itself.
              Most FITS region files will have a WCS.  To determine
              if the file has a WCS just
</PARA>
<VERBATIM>
% dmlist fov.fits cols
...
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
World Coord Transforms for Columns in Table Block FOV
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 
ColNo    Name
1:    EQPOS(RA ) = (+18.4654)[degree] +TAN[(-0.000136667)* (POS(X)-(+4096.50))]
           (DEC)   (+13.2705)              (+0.000136667)  (   (Y) (+4096.50)) 
</VERBATIM>

<PARA>
and in the "World Coord Transforms" section look for either "EQPOS" or "EQSRC".
If neither is present, then a wcsfile which does have one of those two
transforms must be supplied.
</PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>
% regphystocel "circle(4096.5,4096.5,100)-box(4096.5,4096.5,100,100)" ds9.reg wcsfile=img.fits
           </LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
In this example the region is provided directly in the infile parameter.
While the ds9 format does not support the full CIAO logical AND and logical OR
expressions, it does supported include and excluded shapes as shown here:
</PARA>
<VERBATIM>
# Region file format: DS9 version 4.1
global color=green dashlist=8 3 width=1 font="helvetica 10 normal roman" select=1 highlite=1 dash=0 fixed=0 edit=1 move=1 delete=1 include=1 source=1
fk5
circle(01:13:51.6855,13:16:13.8493,49.2")
-box(01:13:51.6855,13:16:13.8493,49.2",49.2")
</VERBATIM>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>


<QEXAMPLE>
<SYNTAX>
<LINE>
% regphystocel cell.src ds9.reg text=component tag=double,double_id,obs_id
</LINE>
</SYNTAX>
<DESC>
<PARA>
In this example we use the text and tag parameters to specify additional
metadata to extract from the FITS region file (cell.src) and store in 
the ds9 region file.  The value of the COMPONENT column are stored in
the text field and will be displayed above the regions.  The values
for the double and double_id columns as well as the obs_id keyword are
stored as tags.  The output will look something like this:
</PARA>
<VERBATIM>
# Region file format: DS9 version 4.1
global color=green dashlist=8 3 width=1 font="helvetica 10 normal roman" select=1 highlite=1 dash=0 fixed=0 edit=1 move=1 delete=1 include=1 source=1
fk5
ellipse(05:23:0.8521,33:28:17.0340,1.50728",1.38265",175.227) # text={1}  tag={double=False} tag={double_id=0} tag={obs_id=4396}
ellipse(05:23:0.6545,33:28:6.6130,1.4234",1.28935",39.5983) # text={2}  tag={double=False} tag={double_id=0} tag={obs_id=4396}
ellipse(05:22:40.0080,33:28:31.1923,1.49205",1.23199",22.1857) # text={130}  tag={double=False} tag={double_id=0} tag={obs_id=4396}
ellipse(05:23:6.6306,33:28:8.8049,2.28348",1.86101",156.246) # text={131}  tag={double=True} tag={double_id=343} tag={obs_id=4396}
ellipse(05:23:5.3125,33:28:36.8242,3.32145",2.22307",115.958) # text={137}  tag={double=True} tag={double_id=139} tag={obs_id=4396}
</VERBATIM>

<PARA>
In ds9, the user will see following groups:  double=False, double=True, 
double_id=0, double_id=343, double_id=139, and obs_id=4396.  The user
can select the source in these groups for additional analysis.
</PARA>

<PARA>
Only a single column or keyword can be used for the text parameter.
The tag parameter is a stack of column or keyword names.
</PARA>

</DESC>


</QEXAMPLE>  




    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM filetype="input" name="infile" reqd="yes" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            The input region.
       </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The infile can be either an ASCII CIAO region file (using
            physical coordinates) 
            or a FITS format region file (always assumed to be using
            physical coordinates).  Users can also supply a 
            simple region expression.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM filetype="output" name="outfile" reqd="yes" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            Output file name.
       </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            The output is a ds9 format region file using celestial coordinates.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM filetype="input" name="wcsfile" reqd="no" type="file">
        <SYNOPSIS>
           File used to obtain world coordinate system transformation.
       </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
        If the infile does not contain a recognized WCS, then users must
        supply a wcsfile which does.  The infile or wcsfile must contain
        either an EQPOS or EQSRC coordinate transform.  If the 
        wcsfile is specified and the infile also has a WCS, the wcsfile
        parameters are used.
         </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="text" reqd="no" type="string" stacks="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>
        The column value or keyword name to use for the region's text label.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
          When the infile is a FITS region file, the user can specify
          a column or keyword to use for the text label associated
          with each region.
          </PARA>        
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="tag" reqd="no" type="string" stacks="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>
        The column values or keyword names to use to tag each region.
        </SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
          When the infile is a FITS region file, the user can specify
          a stack columns and/or keywords to use for as grouping
          tags.  Groups can be used to attach additional information 
          to a region such as which source is associated with which
          background; which sources are extended, adding properties
          like number of counts, etc.
          </PARA>        
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>



      <PARAM def="1" max="5" min="0" name="verbose" type="integer">
        <SYNOPSIS>
        Amount of tool chatter level.
       </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM def="no" name="clobber" type="boolean">
        <SYNOPSIS>
            Overwrite output files if they already exist?
        </SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>
    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2022</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
