<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" >
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="tgmask2reg"
         context="tools" 
         refkeywords="reg2tgmask gratings spectroscopy histogram pha pha2 zeroth order extraction region letg hetg leg heg meg dispersion transmission spectrum cross plus minus"
         seealsogroups="tgtools ">

    <SYNOPSIS>Customize grating extaction region file for use with tgextract2</SYNOPSIS>
    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>tgmask2reg infile outfile [clobber] [verbose]</LINE>
      <LINE/>
      <LINE>reg2tgmask infile srcfile outfile [clobber] [verbose]</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>

       The CALDB contains a default mask file for HRC with LETG, the
       so called "bow-tie" extraction
       region, that it is used by tgextract in Standard Data
       Processing, and can be used with the 
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/tgextract2.html">tgextract2</HREF>       
       tool. This file is sufficient for some observations, but if the field contains 
       multiple sources or if the source is offset, both source and
       background extraction regions may need to be customized. This is most easily done in ds9, however, the information 
       about which region represents source and up and down background
       needs to be preserved.

      </PARA>
      <PARA>
       The tgmask2reg and reg2tgmask scripts allow the use of ds9 to
       define custom extraction regions, and use the ds9 region "tagging"
       feature to encode the grating information along with the
       extraction region coordinates.
      </PARA>


      <PARA title="The tgmask2reg Script">
       This script converts a FITS region file like the one stored in 
       the CALDB, into a ds9 ASCII region file that retains the 
       information about which polygon represents source, background 
       and +/- 1st order. The default infile is "CALDB" which will trigger 
       the tool to query the calibration database for the appropriate 
       file. The output is a ds9 format region file. It should be used 
       in ds9 when the data are binned in TG_R and TG_D coordinates.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="The reg2tgmask Script">

       This script takes a region file saved in Physical coordinates
       in ds9 format and creates a FITS file that can be used by 
       tgextract2. The ds9 region file must only contain polygons and 
       each must have the ds9 tags present that identifies the type: source or 
       background, order, and grating arm. The original FITS region file,
       which can be automatically retrieved from the CALDB, is used as
       a template for the region columns.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
       <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>unix% tgmask2reg infile=CALDB outfile=tg.reg</LINE>
            <LINE>unix% ds9 evt.fits</LINE>
            <LINE>unix% reg2tgmask infile=ds9.reg srcfile=CALDB out=tg_mask.fits</LINE>
            <LINE>unix% tgextract2 ... region_file=tg_mask.fits ...</LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
       tgmask2reg converts the CALDB tgmask file into ds9 format. The
       additional (non-coordinate) columns in the CALDB files are added as "tags" so that later 
       tools know each regions purpose.
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
            The ds9 region looks like this:
            </PARA>


<VERBATIM>
# Region file format: DS9 version 4.1
# Filename:
global color=green dashlist=8 3 width=1 font="helvetica 10 normal roman" select=1 highlite=1 dash=0 fixed=0 edit=1 move=1 delete=0 include=1 source=1
physical
polygon(...) # tag={row_idx=1} tag={rowid=SOURCE} tag={tg_part=3} tag={tg_srcid=1} tag={tg_m=-1} tag={backscal=1.0}
polygon(...) # tag={row_idx=2} tag={rowid=BACKGROUND_UP} tag={tg_part=3} tag={tg_srcid=1} tag={tg_m=-1} tag={backscal=5.0}
</VERBATIM>

            <PARA>
       Next, the event file is loaded into ds9 and the binning
       parameters are changed to the TG_R and TG_D coordinates. Once the
       original region file "tg.reg" is loaded, it can be customized
       interactivelty as needed
       either by moving points or adding new ones both for the source
       and the background areas. Note that polygon regions cannot be
       deleted, nor can be addeded. They can only be modified. The
       final customized set of regions should be saved in ds9 format in physical 
       coordinates (as "ds9.reg" in this example)


            </PARA>
            <PARA>
       The reg2tgmask script converts the modified region "ds9.reg"
       back into a FITS format compatible with tgextract2 ("tg_mask.fits").            
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
                Finally, the region is used with tgextract2 to extract
                a customized spectrum.
            </PARA>

          </DESC>
       </QEXAMPLE>    
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<ADESC title="Caveats">
<PARA title="HRC Only">
Currently this script will only work with HRC + LETG regions.  
</PARA>

<PARA title="Cannot delete regions?">
To ensure that the needed meta-data is preserved, regions cannot be deleted.
</PARA>
</ADESC>

<ADESC title="Groups">
<PARA>
       In ds9, regions can be inspected to see the extra information associated with each region by going to Region -> Groups 
       This will provide a list of the different tags in
       use. Selecting one of the tags will show and select the region(s) in the main ds9 
       window.

</PARA>
</ADESC>
    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


   <BUGS><PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/tgmask2reg.html">bugs page
        for this tool</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA></BUGS>
   <LASTMODIFIED>March 2013</LASTMODIFIED>


</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>

    
