<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY 
        context="tools" 
        key="vtbin" 
        refkeywords="cell voronoi grow localmax max site map mask adaptive bin group grow max tessellation" 
        seealsogroups="dmimgtools"
    >
    <SYNOPSIS>
       Create adaptive bin image using Voronoi Tessellation
    </SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
        <PARA>
            vtbin starts by identifying the local maxima in 
            the input image.  Each local max is assigned a unique
            group ID. It then computes the Voronoi Tessellation
            around the location of the local maxima (sites) and 
            assigns all pixels within the Voronoi cells to the group. 
        </PARA>
        <PARA>
            Users can override the initial site location by supplying 
            their own sitefile.  If not, then the input image should
            be smoothed on a scale larger than the local-max
            search size as specified by the shape and radius parameters.
            (default is a 5x5 box)
        </PARA>

        <PARA title="See also: centroid_map">
          Users may also want to consider the centroid_map tool.  It
          runs vtbin repeatedly adjusting the input sites 
          to be the centroid of each cell.        
        </PARA>

    </DESC>


     <QEXAMPLELIST>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
            % vtbin sm_img.fits vt.map 
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            Here a smoothed image is input.  With the default 
            parameters, the tool will then identify all the 
            local maxima in a 5x5 square neighborhood in the image.
            The Voronoi tessellation of the location of those maxima 
            will then computed and the map created.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
            % dmimgfilt sm_img.fits points.img "max" "box(0,0,3,1)+box(0,0,1,3)"
            % dmimgblob points.img point.map srconly=yes thresh=0.5
            % vtbin sm_img.fits vt.map sitefile=points.map
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            In this example we show how a user might create an
            input sitefile.  We use the dmimgfilt too to identify
            local maxima in a plus (+) shape region (instead of the
            box or circle available in this tool).  We then label
            each local maxima using the dmimgblob tool.            
            With the sitefile specified, the script will use the
            locations in that file for the tessellation.   
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
        <QEXAMPLE>
          <SYNTAX>
            <LINE>
            % vtbin sm_img.fits vt.map shape=circle radius=4 binimg=vt.img 
            </LINE>
          </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            In this example the local maximum search is changed to
            use a circular region with a radius of 4 logical pixels. 
            In addition we choose to output the binned image by
            specifying the binimg parameter.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>

     <PARAMLIST>
        <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Input image.
            </SYNOPSIS>
            <DESC>
            <PARA>The image to be grouped.  Generally this 
            algorithm works better if it is slightly smoothed.
            </PARA>
            <PARA>
            Null  and NaN pixels, as well as those pixels outside the
            image subspace will not be grouped.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
          <SYNOPSIS>
            Output map file
          </SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
              The outfile is a map file containing integer pixel values.
              The pixel values indicate which pixels are grouped
              together by the algorithm.  A pixel value of 0 are pixels
              which are ungrouped (ie outside the image subspace).            
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>


        <PARAM name="binimg" type="file" filetype="output">
          <SYNOPSIS>Optional, output binned image</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
                If the binimg file is specified, the script
                will use the input image and the output map file to
                create a binned version of the input image.
            </PARA>          
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
        
        
        <PARAM name="shape" type="string" def="box">
          <SYNOPSIS>Shape of local max search region.</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>The shape and radius parameters specify
            the region to use when searching for "local" maxima.
            The radius is expressed in logical (image) pixels.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM name="radius" type="real" def="2.5">
          <SYNOPSIS>Shape of local max search region.</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>The shape and radius parameters specify
            the region to use when searching for "local" maxima.
            The radius is expressed in logical (image) pixels.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM name="sitefile" type="file" filetype="input">
          <SYNOPSIS>Input site map file</SYNOPSIS>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
            If the sitefile is specified, then the local max
            search specified by the shape and radius parameters
            is not performed.  The sitefile must have the 
            same shape/size as the input image.  The pixel values
            should be integers; values not equal to zero are 
            used for the tessellation and the values 
            must be unique.  Typically there should be
            a few hundred to maybe a few thousand sites (based on
            the image sizes).             
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
        </PARAM>

        
        <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Amount of chatter from the tool.
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
        <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
            <SYNOPSIS>
            Delete outfile if it already exists?
            </SYNOPSIS>
        </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>



    <ADESC title="Relation to weighted v.t. binning">
      <PARA>Users of this tool should also be 
      familiar with Diehl &amp; Statler's the weighted Voronoi 
      tessellation binning tool, wvt_bin, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2966.2006.10125.x .      
        
      </PARA>    
    </ADESC>



    <BUGS>
        <PARA>
            See the
            <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
            website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
        </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <LASTMODIFIED>February 2020</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
