<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" >
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="xmatch_viz"
         context="Tools::Coordinates"
         refkeywords="wcs match visualize region ds9 crossmatch wcs_match"
         seealsogroups="reproject">
    <SYNOPSIS>Create a region file to visualize cross match results</SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
        'xmatch_viz' creates a DS9 region file to help users visually inspect
        astrometric cross-match results.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        In the resulting output region file:
        Input sources are green colored circles and reference sources
        are magenta colored squares. A line is drawn between matching pairs to
        show the astrometric shift. Sources included in the final transformation
        solution are shown as filled, while unused sources are hollow.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        The tool also generates a legend in the format of a DS9 illustrate mode save file
        that can be loaded into DS9 to identify the different symbols used in the visualization.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
        <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>
$ wcs_match infile=src.fits refsrc=ref_src.fits wcsfile=acis.img outfile=out.xform logfile=out.log verbose=1 clob+
          </LINE>

          <LINE>
$ parse_wcs_match_log infile=src.fits refsrc=ref_src.fits logfile=out.log outfile=out.stats
          </LINE>

          <LINE>
$ xmatch_viz infile=out.stats refsrc=ref_src.fits outfile=ds9.reg legend=ds9.seg
          </LINE>

          <LINE>
$ ds9 acis.img -region format ds9 -region ds9.reg -illustrate load ds9.seg -catalog import fits out.stats
          </LINE>

        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
    This example shows the 4 commands to run wcs_match, parse the log output,
    generate the crossmatch regions, and display the results.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
        </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>


    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="infile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>Input crossmatch table</SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>The table containing match results (e.g., from parse_wcs_match_log).</PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="refsrcfile" type="file" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>Input reference source list</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="outfile" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>Output DS9 region file name</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="legend" type="file" filetype="output" reqd="yes">
        <SYNOPSIS>Output legend illustration</SYNOPSIS>
        <DESC>
            <PARA>
                The legend file is a DS9 illustrate mode save file.
                It must be loaded using the
            <SYNTAX><LINE>-illustrate load&#160;</LINE></SYNTAX>  command.
            </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="radius" type="real" def="0.5" units="arcsec" min="0">
        <SYNOPSIS>The radius for the output regions</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="clobber" type="boolean" def="no">
        <SYNOPSIS>Overwrite existing files?</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" def="1" min="0" max="5">
        <SYNOPSIS>Tool verbosity.</SYNOPSIS>
      </PARAM>
    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Helpful Hints">
        <PARA title="Regions are Locked">
            The region file has been setup so that the regions cannot be
            resized, repositioned, nor rotated. This is to prevent accidental
            edits. Regions can still be deleted.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Legend">
            The legend is provided in Illustrate mode and will remain
            fixed in the upper left corner of the display. To disable the
            legend, go to Edit → Illustrate. Then uncheck Illustrate → Show.
        </PARA>
        <PARA title="Groups">
            The regions have had "tags" applied to them to group them together
            into the following categories:
        </PARA>
        <LIST>
          <ITEM>All_Input: This group includes all the input sources.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>All_Reference: This group include all the reference sources.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Input_Matched: This group includes all the input sources that are matched to a reference source but were not included in the final transform solution. </ITEM>
          <ITEM>Input_Unmatched: This group includes all the input sources that were not matched to reference sources.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Input_Used: This group includes all the input sources that are matched to a reference source and were included in the final transform solution. </ITEM>

          <ITEM>Reference_Matched: This group includes all the reference sources that are matched to an input source but were not included in the final transform solution. </ITEM>
          <ITEM>Reference_Unmatched: This group includes all the reference sources that were not matched to input sources.</ITEM>
          <ITEM>Reference_Used: This group includes all the references sources that are matched to an input source and were included in the final transform solution. </ITEM>
        </LIST>

        <PARA>
        Users can access the list of region groups by going to
        Region → Groups. Selecting a group from the list will select all the
        sources with that tag applied.  This can be especially helpful to do something like
        delete all the unmatched reference sources. Simply select the "Reference_Unmatch" group and press the Delete key.
        </PARA>

        <PARA title="Changing source Properties">
            Region groups also make it easy to adjust the properties of regions. For example to change the font size simply select the region group (e.g. All_Input) and then go to Region → Font and select the desired font size/properties. The same technique can be use to change the color of the regions (Region → Color)
        </PARA>

        <PARA title="Multimatch">
            If wcs_match was run with multimatch=yes, there may be multiple matches between
            input sources and reference sources.
        </PARA>

        <PARA title="Catalog">
            Loading the cross match table (i.e. the output from the
            parse_wcs_match_log tool) into ds9 together with the regions makes it easier to
            inspect the cross matches. Clicking on the sources in the Catalog table will pan the image
            display to the location of the source.
        </PARA>

    </ADESC>



    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="https://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/xmatch_viz.html">bug
        pages</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>May 2026</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
