<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
   <ENTRY context="tools" key="dax" refkeywords="gui ds9 ds9tools ciaotools" seealsogroups="ds9">
   <SYNOPSIS>
       Run CIAO tasks from the ds9 Analysis menu
   </SYNOPSIS>


   <DESC>
      <PARA>
	A number of common CIAO tasks are available from the ds9
        Analysis menu.  This menu addition allows users to get source
        counts, smooth an image, and create a histogram - among many
        other things - from the ds9 program in CIAO.  The analysis
        menu tasks are known as "dax" (ds9 analysis
        extensions).
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Getting Started">
	The commands are stored in the file
	$ASCDS_INSTALL/contrib/config/ciao.ds9 and are
	automatically loaded when ds9 is launched within CIAO.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The user can also explicitly point to the file in the ds9
	-analysis switch:	 
      </PARA>
      <VERBATIM>
unix% ds9 -analysis $ASCDS_INSTALL/contrib/config/ciao.ds9 ...
      </VERBATIM>

      <PARA title="Using the Tools">
	Under ds9's Analysis menu, at the bottom will be a "CIAO" 
	option.   Selecting "CIAO" will display the category of CIAO tasks :
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM> 
           Statistics: use the any defined regions to calculate
           counts, centroid, min, max, etc. Also includes 
           a 'snap-to-centroid' function.   
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Histograms: create spectra, lightcurves, and radial
	   profiles, for example. 
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Coords: use the ds9 crosshair to map coordinates from image
           to chip, detector, off-axis angles, etc.   (Switch to
           the crosshair cursor in the Edit menu.)
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Detect: run source detection tools on images.
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Regions: generate regions that enclose a fraction of flux,
	   magic-wand style source selector (local contouring).
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           Sherpa: extract and fit spectra or fit 2D image.
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
           Image Processing: adaptive smooth (including csmooth),
	   adaptive bin, smooth (various kernels), non-linear
	   filtering (median), fill in where sources have been removed
	   (dmfilth), and more options. 
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA title="Calculating the Statistics">
	The options under the Statistics item use the combination of
	all defined regions to calculate the quantities.  To exclude
	certain areas, define a region and use the "Region -&gt;
	Properties" menu to set it to "exclude".  If no regions are
	defined, the calculations are run on a 1024 x 1024 image
	created at the current binning value. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Plotting">
	A ChIPS server is started in the background when ds9 is
	launched; this ChIPS session is then used for any plotting.
	If ChIPS is not available, dax uses BLT to plot instead; the
	user will see an informational message in the terminal in this
	case. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	Note that if you are have loaded the CIAO analysis file
        manually, you will also need to 
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
source $ASCDS_INSTALL/contrib/config/chips_startup.tk
</VERBATIM>
        
      <PARA>
        from the command line before starting ds9.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Modifying and Saving the Plots">
	To modify a ChIPS plot, first connect to the ChIPS server with 
	the 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/ahelp/connect.html">connect() command</HREF>.  Then any ChIPS commands may be used to change the
	appearance of the plot;  more information is available on the 
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/">ChIPS website</HREF>.
      </PARA> 

      <PARA>
	Once connected to the server, the plot may be saved with the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/ahelp/make_script.html">make_script() command</HREF>.
      </PARA>
   </DESC>

    <ADESC title="Known Limitations">
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  ds9 uses the funtools syntax to specify filters (spatial,
	  energy) and block names.  dax does not convert this filter
	  information to the CIAO format; users should do so to use
	  the filters in CIAO analysis.
	</ITEM>        



        <ITEM>
	  The stacked shapes (panda, annulus, elliptical annulus, box
	  annulus, etc.) only work with the radial profile task.
	</ITEM>        
      </LIST>
   </ADESC>


<ADESC title="Change in the 4.8.4 (September 2016) release">
<PARA>
  Several tasks have been updated to ensure that the desired region
  format is retrieved from ds9 instead of relying on the assumed 
  defaults. 
</PARA>

</ADESC>



<ADESC title="Changes in the 4.6.7 (November 2014) release">
<PARA>
A new "Net Counts" option has been added that emulates the 
FUNTOOLs 'Counts in a region' functionality.  This provides
net counts and rates individually for each region.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The Aperture Photometry task has been renamed and moved.  It is now
available as the "Statistics -&gt; Photometry (srcflux)" task.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The "All" statistics have been renamed "dmstat" to make it more
clear which task is being run.
</PARA>
</ADESC>




   <BUGS>

      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/index.html">CIAO
        website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
   </BUGS>

   <LASTMODIFIED>September 2016</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
