<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY tool "find_chandra_obsid">

 <!ENTITY pr "unix&#37;">

 <!ENTITY dco "<HREF link='http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/download_chandra_obsid.html'>download_chandra_obsid</HREF>">

 <!ENTITY cdaenv "CDA_MIRROR_SITE">

]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="find_chandra_obsid" context="tools"
	 refkeywords="find search download ftp chandra obsid obsids
		      data archive cda mirror public chaser webchaser
		      footprint footprints
		      fco find_chandra_obsids
		      &cdaenv;"
         seealsogroups="contrib.cda"
	 >

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Find, and optionally download, publicly-available Chandra ObsIds from the Chandra archive.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The &tool; tool will find publicly available Chandra data
	that covers a circular region of sky (a point search can be
	used by setting the search radius to 0). The download
	parameter can be used to download the data, or the
	&dco; script can be used.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	This tool makes use of the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/cda/footprint/">Chandra Footprint Service</HREF>,
	which can also be searched using a web browser.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Single argument">
	When called with a single argument, it is checked to see if it matches
	an
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/dictionary/obsid.html">Observation Id (ObsId)</HREF>
	value (that is, an integer between 1 and 65535),
	otherwise it is treated as an object name.
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA title="ObsId">
	If an integer value is given, then the Chandra Data Archive is
	searched to find the location of the observation, and this
	is used in the search (which means that the ObsId will be
	one of the returned values). If the ObsId is unrecognized by the
	archive then it is treated as an object name.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	You can check the coordinates that are returned for the name
	by setting the verbose parameter to 2.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Object names">
	The name resolver at the CADC is used to convert names to
	a position. If the name contains a space then it must be given 
	surrounded by quotes - e.g. "NGC 1333" - to ensure that the script
	recognizes it as a single argument.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	You can check the coordinates that are returned for the name
	by setting the verbose parameter to 2.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Solar system objects">
	The name resolver does not support solar-system objects.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Using a position">
	If two arguments are given then they are taken to be the
	Right Ascension and Declination to search about (J2000).
	A range of formats can be used (which may require surrounding
	the value in quotes or protecting characters depending on the shell you
	are using):
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
&pr; &tool; 12.3 -1.2
&pr; &tool; 12:14 "-1 15 23"
&pr; &tool; "12h 14m 3.2s" "-0d 5'"
</VERBATIM>

      <PARA>
	If verbose is set to 2 then the script will display the result
	of the conversion from the input values into decimal degrees.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Selecting instruments">
	The default search uses all instruments, but you can restrict
	the results using the instrument parameter, so
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; m31 instrument=acis</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; m31 instrument=aciss</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	searches for all ACIS or just ACIS-S observations of M31.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Selecting gratings">
	The default search does not filter on the grating; to do so
	use the grating parameter.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; mkn421 grating=letg</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; perseus grating=any</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	searches for LETG observations of Markarian 421 and any grating observations
	of Perseus.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Downloading data">
	When the download parameter is "none" - which is the default - then a table of
	values for the matching observations are displayed. If set to "all" then
	the matching ObsIds are downloaded to the working directory; in this case
	the information on the matching ObsIds is not given.
	When set to "ask", you are queried whether to download each ObsId 
	and then the download will take place for the chosen observations.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The data is downloaded to the current working directory and uses the same
	layout as the &dco;
	script. If the file already exists it will not be over-written, unless the
	file size is larger than on disk; a smaller value is taken to mean a previous
	download attempt was interrupted, so it will append to the file.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	Unlike download_chandra_obsid, there is no way to select
	a subset of data to download for each ObsId.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Subsetting the data for download">
	This script provides limited capabilities for filtering the data,
	by using the instrument and grating parameters. More complicated
	filtering can be done by taking advantage of the fact that the
	screen output of the script can be manipulated using the 
	CIAO command-line tools. For example
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&pr; find_chandra_obsid 350.86 58.81 > matches.dat
&pr; dmlist matches.dat counts
115
&pr; dmlist "matches.dat[time>20,inst=HRC-I][cols obsid]" data,raw 
#  obsid
               1505.0
&pr; download_chandra_obsid 1505
...
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
	shows that ObsId 1505 is the only HRC-I observation with an exposure
	of 20 ks or higher. The download_chandra_obsid tool is then used
	to download the matching observation.
      </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 3040</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    All observations that overlap the aim point
	    of ObsId 3040 are reported.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Setting the verbose value to 2, or higher, displays
	    the coordinates returned by by the name resolver; for instance
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&pr; &tool; 3040 verbose=2
Looking for position of ObsId 3040
ObsId 3040 status=archived RA=12 01 53.70 Dec=-18 52 35.50
Found ra=180.47375 dec=-18.8765277778
    = 12h 1m 53.7s -18d 52' 35.5"
...
</VERBATIM> <!-- " for emacs -->
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; arp244</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this case a name resolver is used to convert
	    the argument into a position, and then all observations
	    which overlap that position are reported.
	    Unfortunately solar system names are not supported.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Setting the verbose value to 2, or higher, displays
	    the coordinates returned by by the name resolver; for instance
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&pr; &tool; arp244 verbose=2
Querying name resolvers for name=arp244
Found ra=180.47208 dec=-18.87694
    = 12h 1m 53.2992s -18d 52' 36.984"
...
</VERBATIM> <!-- " for emacs -->
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 'ARP 244'</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If the object name contains spaces then it must be
	    quoted with single or double quotes.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 180.47 -18.88</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If two arguments are given then the script interpets these
	    as Right Ascension and Declination. This call will
	    find all the publicly-available Chandra observations
	    that overlap the circle with a center at RA of 180.47 degrees
	    and Declination of -18.88 degrees, and a radius of 1 arcminute.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 12:1:54 -18:52:36</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The script supports the most common formats for specifying
	    RA and Dec. Values that include spaces will need to be
	    quoted to avoid being interpreted as multiple arguments by
	    the shell - e.g.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; &tool; "12 1 54" "-18 52 36"</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; &tool; "12h 1m 54s" "-18d 52' 36"'"'</LINE> <!-- " needed by emacs -->
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Setting the verbose value to 2, or higher, displays
	    the decimal coordinates calculated by the script:
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&pr; &tool; "12h 15m 46s" "-0 0 4" verbose=2
Converting 12h 15m 46s and -0 0 4 to decimal degrees.
-> 183.941666667 -0.00111111111111
...
</VERBATIM>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 180.47 -18.88 detail=obsid</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we list just the ObsId values for each observation.
	    The detail setting can also be changed to all to get
	    more columns (basically the RA and Dec of the aim point
	    for each observation).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 180.47 -18.88 download=ask</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Instead of listing all the matches, you will be asked
	    whether to download each ObsId; the output will look something like
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
There were 7 matching observations:

1/7: Obsid=315 Sepn=0.3 Inst=ACIS-S Grat=NONE Exp=73.2 ObsDate=1999-12-01
   PI=Murray Target=NGC 4038/NGC 4039
2/7: Obsid=3040 Sepn=0.3 Inst=ACIS-S Grat=NONE Exp=69.9 ObsDate=2001-12-29
   PI=Fabbiano Target=NGC 4038/NGC 4039
...
7/7: Obsid=3718 Sepn=0.3 Inst=ACIS-S Grat=NONE Exp=35.2 ObsDate=2002-07-13
   PI=Fabbiano Target=NGC 4038/NGC 4039

Use h to get help on the download options.

1/7: Obsid=315 Sepn=0.3 Inst=ACIS-S Grat=NONE Exp=73.2 ObsDate=1999-12-01
   PI=Murray Target=NGC 4038/NGC 4039

Download [y, n, q, a, h]: y

...
</VERBATIM>
	  <PARA>
	    The instrument and grating flags can be used to restrict the
	    set of matches, in which case the use of download=all may
	    be appropriate; this downloads all the matching data without asking
	    you for confirmation.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 350.86 58.81 instrument=hrc</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we restrict the search to just HRC observations.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 350.86 58.81 radius=0</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we restrict the search to those observations that
	    overlap the given point, rather than any part of a
	    circle about the point.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 'cas a' grating=any</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here we find all the grating observation of Cas A.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 12:0 0 radius=3600 instrument=hrci grating=letg</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The grating and instrument parameters can be combined to restrict,
	    in this case, to HRC-I observations with the LETG, using
	    a search of 1 degree about RA=12:0:0 and a Declination of 0.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; &tool; 350.86 58.81 mirror=ftp://cdaftp.cfa.harvard.edu/pub</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
            If you have access to a mirror of the Chandra Data Archive (CDA), then
            use the mirror parameter to point to it. The script will then
            search in the mirror site, rather than the CDA,
            for the files. Note that if you use a partial mirror, or an out of date one,
            that the script does not fall back to trying the CDA
            if it can not find the requested data on the mirror site.
            Note that in this example we have used the location of the CDA
            itself.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    An alternative is to use the &cdaenv; environment variable, so that
	    the above could also be written as:
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&pr; setenv &cdaenv; ftp://cdaftp.cfa.harvard.edu/pub</LINE>
	      <LINE>&pr; &tool; 350.86 58.81</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <PARAMLIST>
      <PARAM name="arg" type="string" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>RA, ObsId, or name of source</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The Right Ascension (J2000) or name of the source.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Many common RA formats can be used, as shown below. Values
	    including a space need to be surrounded by quotes.
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>12.3</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>12:14</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>"12h 14m 3.2s"</ITEM>
	  </LIST>
	  <PARA>
	    If the Dec argument is empty than the value is taken to
	    be wither be an ObsId (if an integer in the range 1 to
	    65535), or the name of the source and sent to the 
	    CADC name resolver. Set verbose to 2 to see the 
	    position that is returned.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Not all names can be resolved; for instance solar system
	    objects.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="dec" type="string" reqd="yes">
	<SYNOPSIS>Dec of source</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The declination (J2000) of the source. If not given,
	    or set to "", the first argument is taken to be the
	    name or ObsId of the source.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Many common formats can be used, as shown below. Values
	    including a space need to be surrounded by quotes or
	    protetected in some way, depending on your shell:
	  </PARA>
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>-34.2</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>"-34 12"</ITEM>
	    <ITEM>"-34d 12' 2.8"'"'</ITEM> <!-- " for emacs -->
	  </LIST>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="radius" type="real" def="1" min="0" units="arcmin">
	<SYNOPSIS>Radius for search overlap in arcmin</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The search radius around the source to look for overlap
	    with any Chandra observation. A value of 0 means that the
	    search location must lie within the "footprint" of a
	    Chandra observation for it to be returned.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="download" type="string" def="none">
	<SYNOPSIS>What ObsIDs should be downloaded?</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    What should be done with matching ObsIDS?
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Value</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>none</DATA>
	      <DATA>No data is downloaded. A list of matching observations is
	      displayed to the screen (the detail parameter controls the level of
	      detail).</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>ask</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The user is asked whether each matching ObsID should be downloaded.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>all</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		All matching ObsIDs are downloaded. Care should be taken here
		since this can result in a lot of data being downloaded from the archive.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	  
	  <PARA>
	    Note that there is no way to restrict the data being downloaded. If you
	    only want a subset of files for each ObsID then use the 
	    &dco; script once you have
	    found the list of matching ObsID values.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="instrument" type="string" def="all">
	<SYNOPSIS>Choice of instrument</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The search can be restricted to one or more instruments
	    using this parameter:
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Setting</DATA><DATA>Instrument(s)</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>all</DATA>
	      <DATA>No instrument filter is applied.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>acis</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only ACIS-I or ACIS-S data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hrc</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only HRC-I or HRC-S data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>acisi</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only ACIS-I data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>aciss</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only ACIS-S data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hrci</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only HRC-I data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hrcs</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only HRC-S data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="grating" type="string" def="all">
	<SYNOPSIS>Choice of grating</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The search can be restricted to one or more grating settings
	    using this parameter:
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Setting</DATA><DATA>Grating(s)</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>all</DATA>
	      <DATA>No grating filter is applied.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>none</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only observations with no grating are returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>letg</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only LETG data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>hetg</DATA>
	      <DATA>Only HETG data is returned.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>any</DATA>
	      <DATA>Search for LETG or HETG observations.</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="detail" type="string" def="basic">
	<SYNOPSIS>Columns to display</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    This parameter controls the number of columns displayed
	    when the download parameter is "none". The options are:
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Setting</DATA><DATA>Columns</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>basic</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		obsid, sepn, inst, grat, time, obsdate, piname, target
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>obsid</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		obsid
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>all</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		obsid, sepn, inst, grat, time, 
		rastr, decstr, 
		obsdate, piname, target, ra, dec
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	  <PARA>
	    and the description of the columns is given below:
	  </PARA>
	  <TABLE>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>Column</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>obsid</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The 
		<!--
		    <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/dictionary/obsid.html">Observation Id</HREF>
		-->
		Observation Id
		for the observation.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>sepn</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The separation, in arcminutes, between the
		<!--
		    <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/faq/aimpoint.html">aim point</HREF>
		-->
		aim point
		of the observation and the search location.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>inst</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The instrument used in the observation, one of
		ACIS-S, ACIS-I, HRC-S, or HRC-I.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>grat</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		Thr grating used in the observation, one of
		NONE, LETG, or HETG.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>time</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The exposure time of the observation, in kiloseconds.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>rastr</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The RA of the aim point of the observation, using h:m:s
		format (J2000).
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>decstr</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The Declination of the aim point of the observation, using d:m:s
		format (J2000).
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>obsdate</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The date of the observation. When the detail level is basic then this
		contains just the day of the observation; the time is included when
		the detail level is all.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>piname</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The surname of the Principal Investigator for the observation.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>target</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The target name.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>ra</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The RA of the aim point of the observation, in decimal degrees.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	    <ROW>
	      <DATA>dec</DATA>
	      <DATA>
		The Declination of the aim point of the observation, in decimal degrees.
	      </DATA>
	    </ROW>
	  </TABLE>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
      <PARAM name="mirror" type="string" def="">
	<SYNOPSIS>Use this instead of the CDA FTP site</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The default FTP site used to download data is the Chandra
	    Data Archive. 
	    If the mirror parameter site is set then this is taken
	    to be the address of the mirror site to use,
	    otherwise if the &cdaenv; environment
	    variable is set then this is used, otherwise the
	    default setting (the Chandra Data Archive) is used.
	    If the observation is not found at
	    the mirror site then the script will skip it (i.e. it does not
	    try the CDA site).
	  </PARA>
          <PARA>
            The mirror location should include the URL of the FTP site
            (the leading ftp:// is required) and the path up to, but not including,
            the byobsid/ directory. So, for the Chandra Data Archive itself
            you would use
            <EQUATION>ftp://cdaftp.cfa.harvard.edu/pub</EQUATION>
            (although obviously in this case you do not need to use the mirror
            option).
            Please see the documentation for the mirror site to find out
            the correct path to use.
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            If needed, you can include a username and password in the mirror
            setting, following 
            <HREF link="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3986">RFC3986</HREF>,
            for instance
            <EQUATION>ftp://anonymous:foo@bar.com@cdaftp.cfa.harvard.edu/pub</EQUATION>
          </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>

      <PARAM name="verbose" type="integer" min="0" max="5" def="1">
	<SYNOPSIS>
	  Verbose level
	</SYNOPSIS>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    If set to 0 then there will be no screen output
	    apart from error messages. The default setting
	    of 1 is intended for most users; a value of 2 will display
	    the position found for the name when the dec argument is
	    empty.
	    Higher levels are
	    mainly useful for debugging (e.g. when reporting a problem to
	    to the CXC HelpDesk).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </PARAM>
      
    </PARAMLIST>

    <ADESC title="Parameter handling">
      <PARA>
	This script has a default mode setting of "h", rather than the usual
	"ql", so that you can say:
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&pr; &tool; 234.568 -23.24
&pr; &tool; "1h 33m 50s" "30d 39' 40"
&pr; &tool; m101
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
        without having to be prompted for an declination (when using just
        a name), or having to clear out previous values.
	It does mean that it is an error to call the script without
	either a position or object name on the command line
	(i.e. you will not be prompted
	for these arguments).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	Use pset 
        if you wish to permanently set options, for instance to set 
        instrument to acis to exclude HRC observations.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.1 (December 2015) release">
      <PARA>
        The code has been updated to avoid warning messages from
        NumPy version 1.9. There is no difference to how the
        script behaves.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.7.1 (December 2014) release">
      <PARA title="Support for searching by ObsId">
	If a single argument is given and it is an integer in the
	range 1 to 65535, then it is first checked against the 
	Chandra Data Archive and, if it matches an existing ObsId,
	then its position is used, otherwise it is passed to the
	name server.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.5.4 (August 2013) release">
      <PARA title="Support for CDA mirror sites">
	The mirror parameter and support for the
	&cdaenv; environment variable 
	has been added to allow data access from a
	mirror of the Chandra Data Archive site.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Screen output">
        A minor change to the screen output when no matches are found
        (the search position is now included in the message).
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see this page for installation instructions - such as how to
        ensure that the parameter file is available.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
	See the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/find_chandra_obsid.html">bugs page
	for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
	listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>November 2015</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
