<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY key="fullgarf"  context="tools"  refkeywords="grating spectroscopy effective area flux psf lsf aspect dither letg hetg meg heg leg gratings transmission spectrum arf response exposure order pha"  seealsogroups="resptools"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

      Create a grating ARF for a particular order and grating
      for a given observation.
   
</SYNOPSIS>

<DESC>
<PARA>

          fullgarf is a  script that creates a grating ARF for a 
          particular order and grating for a given observation.  While
          the mkgarf tool will create a grating ARF for an individual
          chip given an aspect histogram, this script will create 
          ARFS for each chip, creating aspect histograms as necessary.
          The script will then combine the individual ARFS into the
          full array&apos;s ARF via the dmarfadd tool (see mkgarf for further
          details). The order and grating can be specified either by 
          giving the corresponding row in a Type II PHA file,
          or by specifying a Type I PHA file which contains a spectrum
          for the desired order/grating combination. 

       
</PARA>
<PARA>

          This tool carries out all of the steps involved in creating
          a grating ARF and runs asphist, mkgarf and dmarfadd. See
          help on those tools for additional information.  In
          successive invocations, the rootname parameter is used to
          check for the existence of asphist files in order to avoid
          re-creating them for the same chip (since they depend only
          on chip, and not grating or order).
       
</PARA>

<PARA title="HRC-S/LETG Data">

          For HRC-S/LETG data, fullgarf creates +/- 1 gARFs
          correctly.  However, the functionality does not exist to
          create higher order responses.  Users who wish to model more
          than the first order of the observation should follow the
          <HREF
          link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/mkgarf_letghrcs/">Compute
          LETG/HRC-S Grating ARFs thread</HREF> to creater gARFs for
          higher orders. 
</PARA>

<PARA title="HRC-I/LETG Data">

	This script does not operate on HRC-I/LETG data.  Users doing
	analysis with this configuration should follow the <HREF
	link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/mkgarf_letghrci/">Compute
	LETG/HRC-I Grating ARFs thread</HREF>. 
	
</PARA>

</DESC>
<QEXAMPLELIST>
<QEXAMPLE>
<SYNTAX>
<LINE>

            fullgarf phafile=acisf00007_005N001_pha2.fits pharow=1
            evtfile=acisf00007N001_evt2.fits.gz
            asol=pcadf085492801N001_asol1.fits
            engrid=&quot;grid(acis_heg_1.rmf[cols ENERG_LO,ENERG_HI])&quot; 
            maskfile=acisf00007_002N001_msk1.fits
            dafile=CALDB

         
</LINE>

</SYNTAX>
<DESC>
<PARA>

         For the first 2 examples, consider an HETG+ACIS-S observation
 with a pha file named &quot;acisf00007_005N001_pha2.fits&quot;. Examining the file via dmlist 
 (dmlist &quot;acisf00007_005N001_pha2.fits[SPECTRUM][cols tg_m,tg_part]&quot; opt=data) gives:
       
</PARA>
<VERBATIM>

----------------------------------------------------------------------
Data for Table Block SPECTRUM
----------------------------------------------------------------------
 
ROW    TG_M TG_PART
 
     1   -3    1
     2   -2    1
     3   -1    1
     4    1    1
     5    2    1
     6    3    1
     7   -3    2
     8   -2    2
     9   -1    2
    10    1    2
    11    2    2
    12    3    2
      </VERBATIM>
<PARA>

         In other words, e.g., row one corresponds to an HEG (TG_PART=1)
      minus-third order spectrum while row ten corresponds to an MEG
      (TG_PART=2) first-order spectrum.
      
</PARA>
<PARA>

         In this case, fullgarf will create an ACIS-S, HEG ARF for the minus third order. 
      
</PARA>

</DESC>

</QEXAMPLE>
<QEXAMPLE>
<SYNTAX>
<LINE>

            fullgarf phafile=acisf00007_005N001_pha2.fits pharow=11
           evtfile=acisf00007N001_evt2.fits.gz
           asol=pcadf085492801N001_asol1.fits
           engrid=&quot;grid(acis_meg_1.rmf[cols ENERG_LO,ENERG_HI])&quot; 
           maskfile=acisf00007_002N001_msk1.fits
           dafile=NONE
 
         
</LINE>

</SYNTAX>
<DESC>
<PARA>

            This will create an ACIS-S, MEG ARF for the second order.
            The ACIS dead area correction is not applied.
         
</PARA>

</DESC>

</QEXAMPLE>
<QEXAMPLE>
<SYNTAX>
<LINE>

            fullgarf hrcf01715_002N001_pha2.fits 1
            hrcf01715_002N001_evt2.fits.gz
            hrcf01715_002N001_asoff.fits
            engrid=&quot;grid(hrc_leg_1.rmf[cols
            ENERG_LO,ENERG_HI])&quot;
            dtffile=hrcf01715_000N001_dtf1.fits rootname=mrk421_
            maskfile=""
 
         
</LINE>

</SYNTAX>
<DESC>
<PARA>

            This will create an HRCS-S, LEG ARF for the minus first order.
              
         
</PARA>

</DESC>

</QEXAMPLE>
</QEXAMPLELIST>
<PARAMLIST>
<PARAM name="phafile"  type="file"  reqd="yes"  stacks="no"  >
<DESC>
<PARA>

         The name of the PHA file containing the order, grating
         and source position information. This file may be either
         a Type I or a Type II PHA file. (See tgextract for information
         on Type I/Type II PHA files.)  In the case of a Type I
         file, this information is contained in header keywords.
         For a Type II file this information is contained in
         the data table of the SPECTRUM extension. In this case
         the data are specified by row number via the pharow
         parameter.
       
</PARA>
<PARA>

         Note that the user does not need to specify which type
         of PHA file the above file is.  The script will determine
         this via looking at the TFORMx header keywords.
         
       
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="pharow"  type="integer"  reqd="yes"  def="1">
<DESC>
<PARA>

           Type II PHA files contain multiple spectra in the
           SPECTRUM binary-table extension. (Type I files contain only
           one spectrum.) Each row of the table contains one
           spectrum for a given order, grating and source.
           The pharow parameter specifies the appropriate row 
           for the desired order and grating combination.
           (The order and grating data are contained in the
            TG_M and TG_PART columns). The dmlist tool can be
            used to determine row corresponds to which grating
            grating and order.

         
</PARA>
<PARA>

           Note that if a Type I pha is specified for the phafile
           parameter, the pharow parameter is ignored.
         
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="evtfile"  type="file"  reqd="yes"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the asphist tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

           The event file provides observational configuration 
           information via FITS keywords. It
           also provides good-time interval (GTI) data.
        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="asol"  type="file"  reqd="yes"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the asphist tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

         This parameter give the aspect solution or sim-corrected aspect
         offset file(s).
         It is required as input to the asphist 
         tool. (For additional information on this, try
         ahelp asphist.) 
        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="engrid"  type="string"  units="keV"  reqd="yes"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the mkgarf tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

         This parameter gives the specification for the energy 
         grid. The string may specify either a file (FITS or
         ASCII) which contains the energy grid or an explicit energy
         grid.  CIAO users should, in general, use a gRMF file (created
         with mkgrmf) for the energy grid specification.
        
</PARA>
<PARA>

          For example, to specify the grid contained in the MATRIX
          block of an RMF file name &quot;grating_rmf.fits&quot;, specify:
          &quot;engrid=grid(grating_rmf.fits[MATRIX][cols ENERG_LO,ENERG_HI])&quot;
           You should NOT specify a block that contains a wavelength
	   grid! For example, often a file will contain 
           columns named BIN_LO and BIN_HI which may contain
           wavelengths. Such grids may not be specified, since the
           values will be interpreted as energies.
        
</PARA>
<PARA>

          To explicitly specify a grid which runs from 0.3 keV
          to 10.0 keV in 0.01 keV increment steps, specify:
          &quot;engrid=0.3:10.0:0.01&quot;
        
</PARA>
<PARA>

         To use an ASCII file which contains two columns, the energ_lo 
          and energ_hi, specify: 
          &quot;engrid=grid(myfile.tbl)&quot;
        
</PARA>
<PARA>

          Note that the preferred grid is linear in wavelength, since this 
          reflects the natural dispersion of photons onto the detector. For 
          back-compatibility, we write the grid in energy units in ascending 
          order. Grating rmfs (see mkgrmf) have energy grids in descending
          linear wavelength. (Also see mk_tggrid, a script which converts
          the wavelength grid of a pha file into an FITS-format energy 
          grid file.)

          

        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>

<PARAM name="dtffile"  type="file"  reqd="yes"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the asphist tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

        This parameter gives the name of the file containing the
       dead-time correction factor. In the case of the HRC, these
       data are contained as a table in a FITS file. For the ACIS,
       a single value given by the DTCOR header keyword is used.
       This value is stored in the event file, so that usually
       (for the case of ACIS only!) one specifies the same
       value for this parameter as for the evtfile parameter.

       
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="badpix"  type="file"  reqd="yes"  >
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the ardlib.par file.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

         This parameter will replace the value given in ardlib.par.
       It is not implemented for observations involving the HRC.

        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
<PARAM name="rootname"  type="string"  reqd="yes"  >
<DESC>
<PARA>

          The rootname for all of the output files. The script will
         prepend this parameter to all output filenames. The
         script will first check for the existence of an output file 
         (which includes this rootname). If the file already exists,
         the script will not create a new version. 
       
        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>


<PARAM name="maskfile" type="string" filetype="input" reqd="yes">
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the mkgarf tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>
   The mask file (msk1.fits) for the observation; used by mkgarf.  The
   mask file is needed in particular when a window or subarray was
   used.  A value of "NONE" indicates that no mask file will be applied.
</PARA>
</DESC>
</PARAM>

<PARAM name="dafile" type="string" filetype="input" def="CALDB">
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the mkgarf tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
  <DESC>
    <PARA>
      ACIS "dead area" coefficients file, which may have the values
      "NONE" (no dead area computation), CALDB (for automatic lookup),
      or an explicit file reference to an ACIS "dead area"
      coefficients FITS table. 
    </PARA>

    <PARA>
      See "ahelp mkgarf" for more information on this parameter.
    </PARA>
  </DESC>
</PARAM>      

<PARAM name="osipfile" type="string" filetype="input" def="CALDB" reqd="no">
<SYNOPSIS>

          This parameter is passed on to the mkgarf tool.
     
</SYNOPSIS>
<DESC>
<PARA>
  The Order Sorting and Integrated Probability file; used by mkgarf.  
  The default value, "CALDB", indicates that the highest version for
  the most recent date before the observation date will be retrieved
  from the calibration database.         
</PARA>

    <PARA>
      See "ahelp mkgarf" for more information on this parameter.
    </PARA>

</DESC>
</PARAM>

<PARAM name="clobber"  type="boolean"  def="no">
<DESC>
<PARA>

         If set to yes, existing output files will be removed.  Note
         that this value is passed on to each tool in the script.
         That is, the value chosen for this parameter will 
         set the value for the clobber parameter of all
         tools called by the script.

        
</PARA>

</DESC>

</PARAM>
</PARAMLIST>


    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.10.1 (April 2018) release">
      <PARA>
      Extend the chips used to create the ARF to support offset pointings
      when zero order is not on ACIS-7.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>



    <ADESC title="Changes in CIAO 4.6 contributed software release">
      <PARA>
            The ACIS parameter block file parameter, pbkfikle, was
            removed.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>


    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
        made available as "contributed" software via the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
        Please see the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/instructions.html">installation
          instructions page</HREF> for help on installing the package.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/fullgarf.html">bugs page
        for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
        listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

<LASTMODIFIED>January 2018</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY>

</cxchelptopics>

