<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" >
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="r4_header_update"
         context="tools" 
         refkeywords="keyword header meta data metadata pbk parameter block sum_2x2 fep_ccd orc_mode oclkpair dy_avg dz_avg dth_avg mean aspect offset"
         >
    <SYNOPSIS>Update file header with various keywords to match latest archive processing</SYNOPSIS>
    <DESC>
      <PARA>
      
        Most data in the Chandra archive was reprocessed starting in 
        January 2012 -- an effort to bring uniformity to the calibrations and data
        products.  The internal designation was known as 
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/cda/repro4.html">Repro-4</HREF>.
        All but the first few months of data in the mission were
        included in this bulk processing.  The ASCDSVER keyword will 
        be '8.4.2' or higher for data that has been through repro-4.
        In addition to capturing the latest standard calibrations, there
        were several calibration improvements to astrometry and absolute
        timing.

        At the same time, two sets of keywords were added to the 
        Chandra event files and derived products that make data analysis
        easier and more self-contained (ie requiring fewer auxiliary
        files).          
        </PARA>
        
        <PARA>
        For ACIS and HRC, three new keywords were added to
        capture the mean SIM offsets during an observation:  DY_AVG,
        DZ_AVG, and DTH_AVG.   These numbers
        are needed by tools like dmcoords, mkacisrmf, and mkwarf to
        correctly map detector coordinates back to the location on the
        instruments.  Previously each tool used the information in 
        the asolfile parameter to compute the mean value, every time 
        the tool was run.  With the mean values now simply encoded
        as header keywords, the tools can run more efficiently.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        For ACIS, the information in the Level 0 parameter block file, pbk0,
        needed to compute the dead area calibration was also added to 
        the event file headers.  The new keywords include:
        SUM_2X2, FEP_CCD, ORCMODE, and OCLKPAIR.  This information
        together with some existing keywords, is used by ARF and Exposure
        map tools when creating response.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        The r4_header_update script will examine the header of 
        the infile, determine which of the above keywords are missing, and
        will add them to the header.        
      </PARA>

    </DESC>
    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>unix% dmkeypar my_old_evt.fits ASCDSVER echo+</LINE>
          <LINE>7.6.8</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% r4_header_update my_old_evt.fits</LINE>
          <LINE>unix% dmkeypar my_old_evt.fits FEP_CCD echo+</LINE>
          <LINE>x012346</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            This example shows and older version of an event file created
            with ASCDSVER=7.6.8.  This file will not have the keywords
            necessary to run all CIAO 4.6 tasks.            
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            The script will attempt to locate the auxiliary files it needs,
            the parameter block and aspect solution files.  The 
            file is updated in place.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>unix% r4_header_update my_old_evt.fits pkb=orig_pbk0.fits asol=@my_asol.lis</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            If data are very old, then the information relating an
            event file to the parameter block and aspect solution
            may not be available in the event file header.  In that case
            users will need to specify the auxiliary files explicitly.
          
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

   <BUGS><PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/r4_header_update.html">bugs page
        for this tool</HREF>
        on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA></BUGS>
   <LASTMODIFIED>December 2013</LASTMODIFIED>


  </ENTRY>
  
</cxchelptopics>
