<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY pr  'sherpa>'>

  <!ENTITY chart2 '<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/PSFs/chart2">ChaRT2</HREF>'>

]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="save_chart_spectrum" context="contrib" pkg="sherpa"
	 refkeywords="write_chart_spectrum save write create chart spectrum spectra file psf simulate simulation"
	 seealsogroups="sh.save sh.chart">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Write out the model spectrum in the form required by ChaRT2
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>save_chart_spectrum(outfile, format="text", clobber=True, verbose=True, id=None, elow=None, ehigh=None, ewidth=None, norm=None)</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The save_chart_spectrum() command writes out the current model
	values in the form expected by &chart2;
	(the Chandra Ray Tracer).
	Please see the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/prep_chart/">ChaRT preparation thread</HREF>
	for further information on how to use this routine.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Loading the routine">
        The routine can be loaded into Sherpa by saying:
      </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
from sherpa_contrib.chart import *
</VERBATIM>

      <TABLE>
	<CAPTION>Arguments</CAPTION>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>Name</DATA><DATA>Default value</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>outfile</DATA>
	  <DATA></DATA>
	  <DATA>The name of the file to create.
	    It is no longer valid to use a value of None for this
	    argument.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>format</DATA>
	  <DATA>"text"</DATA>
	  <DATA>The output format of the file: "text" for
	    ASCII format, "fits" for a FITS binary table.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>clobber</DATA>
	  <DATA>True</DATA>
	  <DATA>Determines the behavior if the output file already
	    exists: a value of True (the default) means that the
	    file will be overwritten, otherwise an error will be
	    raised.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>verbose</DATA>
	  <DATA>True</DATA>
	  <DATA>If verbose is True then a message will be printed to the
	  standard output when the file has been created.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>id</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>Which dataset to use: if None then the value returned
	  by get_default_id() will be used.</DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>elow</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The minimum energy at which to evaluate the model; this parameter
	    controls the lower edge of the lowest-energy bin, and is in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the lowest energy bin from the
	    ARF grid. This value should not be smaller than 0.2 keV.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>ehigh</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The maximum energy at which to evaluate the model; this parameter
	    controls the upper edge of the highest-energy bin, and is in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the highest energy bin from the
	    ARF grid. This valus should not be larger than 10 keV.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>ewidth</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    The bin width to use, in keV.
	    A value of None means to use the bin width from the
	    ARF grid.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>norm</DATA>
	  <DATA>None</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    A scaling factor to allow you to easily change the overall flux
	    of the model. A value of None is equivalent to a factor
	    of 1; a value of 10 would create a ChaRT spectral model ten times
	    brighter than the input model.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>

      </TABLE>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>&pr; load_pha("3c273.pi")</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; subtract()</LINE>
	  <LINE>&pr; notice(0.1, 6)</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; set_source(xsphabs.abs1 * powlaw1d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; abs1.nh = 0.07</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; freeze(abs1)</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; guess(p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; fit()</LINE>
          <LINE>...</LINE>
          <LINE>&pr; save_chart_spectrum("chart.dat")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>

          <PARA>
	    Here we load in a source spectrum from the file 3c273.pi, along
	    with the associated files (e.g. ARF, RMF, and background) that are indicated
	    in its header.
	    The background is subtracted, the analysis restricted to the 0.1 to 6 keV
	    range, a model is created - consisting of an absorbed power law - and then
	    parameter values are set before the fit is made.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    After the fit has been made the save_chart_spectrum() routine is used to
	    write out the best-fit model - in a format usable by
	    &chart2; - 
	    to the text file "chart.dat".
	  </PARA>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>&pr; save_chart_spectrum("chart.dat", elow=1, ehigh=8)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    In this example the output is restricted to the range 1 to 8 keV, using the default
	    binning given by the ARF grid. Note that this energy range need not overlap the
	    range used to fit the data (or even the energy ranges of the ARF and RMF files).
	    It should however remain within the range 0.2 to 10 keV.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>&pr; save_chart_spectrum("chart.fits", format="fits")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    The data is written to a FITS binary table called
	    'chart.fits'.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.2 (January 2016) release">
      <PARA>
	The routine has been updated to work with
	version 2 of ChART:
	the output now contains three columns rather than two;
	it can be in FITS or ASCII format; a clobber parameter
	has been added; and the outfile parameter can no-longer
	be set to None.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>

    <LASTMODIFIED>January 2016</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
