<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY     pr  "unix&#x25; ">
]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="check_ciao_caldb" context="tools"
	 refkeywords="caldb install installation calibration check verify test chkcif latest version"
	 seealsogroups="caltools install py.caldb">
    <SYNOPSIS>
      A tool to test the installation of the CIAO Calibration Database (CALDB)
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>check_ciao_caldb</LINE>
      <LINE>check_ciao_caldb --latest</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The check_ciao_caldb tool allows users to easily
	check that the
	CIAO Calibration Database (CALDB) is installed correctly.
	It is intended to be used after installing or upgrading
	CIAO, or to help diagnose problems seen with other CIAO
	toos.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The tool only tests the basic installation, and so
	provides a quick and easy test.
	It does not
	perform the same verification steps as 
	either the 
	calvalid tool from CIAO (see "ahelp calvalid")
	or the 
	the chkcif
	tool from the FTOOLS package (as described on the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/caldb/downloads/index.html#dl_verify">Download the CIAO
	CALDB</HREF>
	page), which should be used for a more thorough evaluation.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Tool behavior">
	As shown in the example below, the tool will print out some basic
	information on the CALDB installation, and then exit with a status
	value of 0 when the installation is correct. If there is a problem
	then an error message will be displayed and the exit status
	will be set to a non-zero value.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="The --latest flag">
	Calling the script with the --latest flag will check whether there
	are any newer versions of the CALDB available. This step requires
	internet access. If a newer version is available then see the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/caldb/downloads">CALDB downloads
	page</HREF> or the 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/threads/ciao_install_tool/">ciao_install
	thread</HREF>.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Availability">
	The check_ciao_caldb tool is part of the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO contributed
	scripts package</HREF> which should have been included as part
	of the CIAO installation.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; check_ciao_caldb</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The tool accepts no arguments. If the Chandra CALDB is set up correctly
	    then you should see something like the following:
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
CALDB environment variable = /soft/ciao-4.2/CALDB
             CALDB version = 4.2.2
             release date  = 2010-04-19T19:00:00 UTC
CALDB query completed successfully.
</VERBATIM>
	  <PARA>
	    The actual output will vary depending on where, and what version,
	    of the CALDB is installed.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&pr; check_ciao_caldb --latest</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    As the --latest flag has been given, the tool also checks whether there is a
	    newer version of the CALDB available. The extra screen output will either be:
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
The CALDB installation is up to date.
</VERBATIM>
	  <PARA>
	    when there is no newer version available, or
	  </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
ERROR: The latest available CALDB version is &lt;latest version&gt;
</VERBATIM>
	  <PARA>
	    for when there is.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
    
    <ADESC title="What is checked?">
      <PARA>
	The script is intended to provide a simple check of the CALDB installation,
	to pick up some of the common problems seen in HelpDesk tickets, rather
	than a complete check of the integrity of the Chandra CALDB. It therefore
	just checks that:
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>The CALDB envrionment variable exists, and points to a directory;</ITEM>
	<ITEM>the directory contains a Chandra version file in the correct location;</ITEM>
	<ITEM>and that a query for the DET_GAIN product (a basic element required for
	re-processing ACIS event lists with acis_process_events) returns a file and that
	this file can be read in.</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	The script does not check for any ancillary CALDB products that may have been
	installed, such as the ACIS background files or the PSF libraries.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Version check">
	The --latest flag causes the script to look at the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/caldb/downloads/releasenotes.html">CALDB release 
	notes</HREF> page to look for the latest version released for CIAO,
	and this value is compared against the version of the local CALDB
	installation.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.1 (December 2015) release">
      <PARA>
        The code has been updated to avoid warning messages from
        NumPy version 1.9. There is no difference to how the
        script behaves.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="About Contributed Software">
      <PARA>
        This tool is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
	made available as "contributed" software via the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
	Please see the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/instructions.html">installation
	instructions page</HREF> for help on installing the package.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
	See the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/">bugs page</HREF>
	on the CIAO website for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <LASTMODIFIED>November 2015</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
