<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY tool "convert_xspec_user_model">

 <!ENTITY upr "unix&#37;">
 <!ENTITY spr "sherpa>">
 <!ENTITY xspec "XSPEC">

]>
<cxchelptopics>
  <ENTRY key="convert_xspec_user_model" context="tools"
	 refkeywords="xspec x-spec user model compile build
		      initpackage lmodel.dat model.dat
		      f2py udmget lmod cfitsio no-xspec noxspec
		      sherpa_contrib.xspec.local xspec.local
		      local lmod
		      "
         seealsogroups=""
	 >

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Compile a &xspec; user model for use in Sherpa *experimental*
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>&tool; name modelfile [extrafile [extrafile [..]]</LINE>
      <LINE/>
      <LINE>Unlike most CIAO contributed scripts, there is no parameter file.</LINE>
      <LINE/>
      <LINE>The supported command-line flags can be found using -h/--help:</LINE>
      <LINE/>
      <LINE>--no-xspec   do not include &xspec; libraries when building</LINE>
      <LINE>--cfitsio    include the CFITSIO library when building</LINE>
      <LINE>-c / --clobber will overwrite existing files.</LINE>
      <LINE>-p / --prefix flags are used to control the user model names.</LINE>
      <LINE>-k / --keep flags keep the .pyf file used in compilation.</LINE>
      <LINE>-v / --verbose changes the amount of screen output.</LINE>
      <LINE>-f / --f2py passes through arguments to the f2py call.</LINE>
      <LINE>--version prints the script version</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The &tool; tool will compile a &xspec; user model into a form
	usable by Sherpa; it is therefore similar to the "initpackage"
	command in &xspec;.  Unlike the initpackage command, this
	script does not require that the &xspec; source package is
	installed, and is not run from Sherpa but the command line.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	This script is *experimental* and will not work
	for all models; please see the "Known Problems"
	section below for more information and contact the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/helpdesk/">CXC HelpDesk</HREF>
	if you find problems or models that it will not compile.
	At present any model requiring access to the udmget
	&xspec; routine is not supported.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The script takes the model file - often called model.dat or
	lmodel.dat - and the source code in the working directory,
	using them to create a Python module consisting of the
	compiled model and some supporting Python code that creates
	the Sherpa model.  The output is a Python module, whose name
	is the first argument to the script. This can be loaded into
	Sherpa by saying (assuming that you ran '&tool; relxill ...'
	and that you are in the same directory):
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; import relxill</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	or, by using the lmod rouine, which allows you to load in
	models from other directories, displays a list of the
	models in the module, and imports all the convolition
	routines into the current namespace:
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; from sherpa_contrib.xspec.local import lmod</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; lmod('relxill', '/data/models/relxill')</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
	

      <PARA>
	At this point the models can then be used; the default
	behavior of the script is to add the prefix "xs"
	to the model name (in a similar manner to how Sherpa uses
	the prefix "xs" for the &xspec; models), but this
	can be changed using the --prefix flag, as shown
	below in the examples.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Convolution models">
	The interface to the &xspec; convolution models has
	not been thoroughly tested, so take care when
	using them! Note that there is currently no support in Sherpa for
        extending the grid to use in a computation, which means that
        some of the convolution models are not going to give the
        desired results. Models like CFLUX should be okay.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The convolution models require a slightly different interface,
	which is designed to follow the Sherpa load_conv and load_psf
	commands. For each convolution model there will be a corresponding
	load_XXX command; e.g. if the model file contains a convolution
	model called specconv then there will be a 
	load_specconv command (note that this naming scheme
	ignores the value of the --prefix flag).
	If you have used the "import name" form, shown above,
	then you have to use "name.load_specconv" to call the function.
	This can be avoided by importing the symbols directly - e.g.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; from relxill import load_specconv</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; from relxill import *</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	- or by using the lmod routine discussed earlier
	(see <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/lmod.html">ahelp lmod</HREF>).
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The load routines take a single argument, a string
	giving the model name, which can then be used as a model
	component and any parameters changed. For example,
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; load_specconv("convmdl")</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; print(convmdl)</LINE>
          <LINE>...</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; convmdl.spin = 3.2</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; set_source(convmdl(powlaw1d.pl))</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	where this assumes that the specconv model has
	a spin parameter.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Table models">
	Sherpa already supports additive and multiplicative
	table models using the
        load_xstable_model command; this was added in CIAO 4.9
        and replaces the support for XSPEC table models in
        the 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/load_table_model.html">load_table_model</HREF>
        command.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; ls *.f</LINE>
	  <LINE>mdl.f</LINE>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; mymodel lmodel.dat</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    The mymodel module is created, which contains the model(s)
	    defined in the file lmodel.dat and with code in mdl.f.
	    If the script completes successfully then it will have
	    created the directory mymodel/, and you can then load
	    it into Sherpa with the command:
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&spr; import mymodel</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    At this point any additive or multiplicative model
	    will be available using the &xspec; name with the prefix
	    "xs". So, if lmodel.dat contained models mdl1 and mdl2
	    then instances of these models can be created and
	    inspected as any other Sherpa model; for example
	    (assuming mdl2 has an alpha component):
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    <SYNTAX>
	      <LINE>&spr; set_source(xsphabs.galabs * xsmdl1.mdl)</LINE>
	      <LINE>&spr; xsmdl2.gas</LINE>
	      <LINE>&spr; print(mdl)</LINE>
	      <LINE>&spr; gas.alpha = 2</LINE>
	    </SYNTAX>
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; mymodel2 lmodel.dat --prefix</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this case the model names are not preceeded by "xs",
	    as in the example above, because the --prefix argument has
	    been given. This means that instead of saying
	    xsmdl1.mdl you would just say mdl1.mdl.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Note that there is no check that the model names do not
	    match existing Sherpa models or function names, so there
	    is a chance for confusion.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    To use a different prefix than "xs" supply an argument to
	    the --prefix flag, but it must start with a capital letter - 
	    e.g.
	    <EQUATION>--prefix XSUM</EQUATION>
	    would make the model name be xsummdl1 rather than xsmdl1.mdl.
	    The requirement for a capital letter is because the name is
	    also used to create a Python class (this class is not used
	    in normal use of Sherpa).
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; ls *.c</LINE>
	  <LINE>polar.c polarutils.c</LINE>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; polar lmodel_polar.dat --clobber</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Here the models in the file lmodel_polar.dat - with C code
	    automatically picked up from the polar.c and polarutils.c
	    files - are compiled to create a polar module.
	    The --clobber argument is used to delete any existing version
	    of the module.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; foo model.dat --no-xspec --cfitsio</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    In this case the model uses CFITSIO to read in files, but
	    not other &xspec; libraries. This may cause problems when
	    trying to load the module, due to differences in the FORTRAN
	    compiler used to build CIAO and the model code. If this
	    happens then &tool; will fail, so the --no-xspec and --cfitsio
	    flags are used to try to avoid this problem.
	  </PARA>
	</DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
	    
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <ADESC title="Loading the module">
      <PARA title="Loading a model from a different directory">
	Since the code generates a Python module, you can
	load in modules from different directories by
	adjusting your PYTHONPATH environment variable or
	the os.sys.path array. We provide a simple wrapper
	routine, lmod, in the sherpa_contrib.xspec.local
	package, which can be used in a similar manner to the
	&xspec; lmod command. For example, after
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; cd /data/models</LINE>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; mymod model.dat</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	you can load in the model package with the following:
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; from sherpa_contrib.xspec.local import lmod</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; lmod("mymod", "/data/models")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	which will also display the models contained in the
	module; see
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/lmod.html">ahelp lmod</HREF>
	for more information.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Automatically loading the module into Sherpa">
	Models can automatically be loaded into Sherpa by taking
	advantage of the IPython startup directory. Any Python file
	in $HOME/.ipython-ciao/profile_sherpa/startup/ will be
	loaded when Sherpa is started up, so add a file to this
	directory - e.g. 90-xspec-models.py - with commands to 
	set up the models. An example file is shown below; adjust
	as appropriate:
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
import os

from sherpa_contrib.xspec.local import lmod
# This assumes that &tool; was run in the two directories
# given in the lmod command:
lmod("carbatm", "/data/models/carbatm", verbose=False)
lmod("relxill", "/data/models/relxill", verbose=False)

# The carbatm model needs to know where the data files are
# via &xspec; settings; relxill via an environment variable:
set_xsxset("CARBATM", "/data/models/carbatm")
os.environ["RELLINE_TABLES"] = "/data/models/relxill"

# display a screen message to remind me what I have loaded
print("&xspec; models: carbatm and relxill")
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
        Starting Sherpa will display the message before the
	first prompt:
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
&upr; sherpa -n
&xspec; models: carbatm and relxill
sherpa-1&gt;
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
	The verbose flag is set to False when calling lmod()
	to avoid the model names always being displayed
	when Sherpa is started.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Notes">
	This only works for the Sherpa application. If you
	have loaded up Sherpa into ChIPS, an IPython session,
	or a script then you wil have to manually load in the
	models you need.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Change in the IPython configuration directory">
	The location of the IPython configuration directory changed
	in CIAO 4.8 to $HOME/.ipython-ciao/. In CIAO 4.5 to 4.7,
	inclusive, it was $HOME/.ipython-ciao45/.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Known Problems">
      <PARA>
	Please contact the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/helpdesk/">CXC HelpDesk</HREF>
	if you have a problem or need to use an unsupported
	feature, such as platform or language.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Platform support">
	The OS-X support is limited.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Language support">
	All the languages supported by &xspec; user models - i.e.
	C, C++, and Fortran - should be supported, as long
	as the compiler is compatible with that used
	to compile the &xspec; models in CIAO (see below).
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="No support for udmget">
	Those models that require the --udmget flag
	to the &xspec; initpackage are not supported
	at this time.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Model types">
	Sherpa only supports the additive, multiplicative,
	and convolution models; other models will be ignored.
	The convolution models have only been lightly tested.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	Models that need to be re-evaluated per spectrum 
	or that calculate model variances 
	are converted but there has been no testing to see
	if they work correctly (note that Sherpa ignores
	the error array that is returned by these models).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	When using convolution models, one possible 
	problem is if you have ignored an energy - or
	wavelength - range within the data; if this 
	range is larger than the RMF at this energy
	then it may be possible that the convolution
	will not properly account for edge effects.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Choice of module name">
	The first argument to &tool; is used to 
	create a Python module of the same name that can then
	be loaded into Sherpa or a Python script.
	It can not match the name of one of the models (once
	the prefix value has been added), and it 
	should not match other Python modules or common symbols,
	otherwise it could confuse users.
	There is only limited checking to see whether there
	are possible name clashes for the module and model
	names.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Parameter types">
	Periodic parameters are not supported.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Accessing &xspec; routines">
	The default behavior is to try and link against the
	&xspec; libraries, but the results have not been
	well tested. One known problem is if the gfortran
	version is significantly different to that used to
	build the &xspec; models provided as part of
	<!--
	    CIAO (gcc/gfortran version 4.? in CIAO 4.8),
	-->
	CIAO,
	which can lead to errors such as
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
undefined symbol: _gfortran_copy_string
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
	If the model does not make use of the &xspec; libraries
	then the --no-xspec flag can be used to avoid linking
	against the &xspec; code, which may help in this
	situation.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	If the model does not use the &xspec; libraries but
	it does use CFITSIO then try both the --no-xspec and
	--cfitsio flags; an example of when this is needed is
	seeing messages such as
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
undefined symbol: ftgmsg_
</VERBATIM>
      <PARA>
	The --f2py option can be used to fine-tune the compile and link
	options used by f2py if the --no-xspec and --cfitsio options
	are insufficient. The --keep argument is useful here, 
	since it displays the
	f2py command line used by the script/
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="External files or set up">
	The equivalent location of the spectral/xspec/
	directory of &xspec; is the 
	$ASCDS_INSTALL/ots/spectral/modelData/ directory.
	The 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/set_xsxset.html">set_xsxset command</HREF>
	can be used to set an &xspec;
	"xset" variable, if the model uses these to define
	alternative locations for data files or other
	configuration information. The os.environ
	directionary can be used to set an environment 
	variable if these are used by the model; for example
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&spr; set_xsxset('CARBATM', '/data/models/data/carbatm')</LINE>
	  <LINE>&spr; os.environ['TBLLOC'] = '/data/models/data'</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	will set the CARBATM &xspec; variable and the
	TBLLOC environment variable.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Parameter names">
      <PARA>
	Not all parameter names are usable in Sherpa, due
	to the Python grammar. Below is
	a list of the conversion rules used, but if you are in
	doubt then just print out an instance of a model
	to see what the names are.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The conversion rules are:
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>The @ character is replaced with the string At.</ITEM>
	<ITEM>The name break is converted to break_, lambda to lambda_, type to type_; any
	  parameter surrounded by &lt; and &gt; has these characters
	  removed and _ave added to the end (so "&lt;kT&gt;" would
	  be changed to "kT_ave"); and a name ending with "(...)"
	  is replaced by "_..." (so "Rin(G)" becomes "Rin_G").
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>Any invalid character for a Python symbol is replaced by _.</ITEM>
      </LIST>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="What does the script do?">
      <PARA>
	The compilation of the code is handled by the
	f2py script (despite the name it can also handle C code;
	see the <HREF link="http://cens.ioc.ee/projects/f2py2e/">F2PY home page</HREF>
	for more information).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	There are two parts to the process:
      </PARA>
      <LIST>
	<ITEM>create a module of the compiled code</ITEM>
	<ITEM>create the Python interface to this compiled code.</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      <PARA>
	The model definition file is parsed to extract all the models,
	which provides details on the model name, its type (such
	as additive or multiplicative), the arguments, the 
	name of the routine that evaluates the model, and 
	the language used for this routine.
	The parsing follows the definition given in the
	<HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/xanadu/xspec/manual/XSappendixLocal.html">&xspec;
	  appendix on local models</HREF>.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="Creating the compiled code">
	This information is then used to create a f2py signature file
	which defines the interface we want to have in Python to the
	compiled code.  The signature file is named &lt;module&gt;.pyf
	in the working directory and is deleted by default but can be
	retained using the --keep flag, which will also display the
	coommand-line arguments used to run f2py, in case it needs
	changing.  The signature file then processed by f2py to create the
	compiled module, which is moved to the location
	&lt;module&gt;/_&lt;module&gt;.so.
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	If the f2py call fails, then the command-line used to run it
	will be displayed and the signature file will not be deleted.
	Extra flags
	can be passed through to f2py using the --f2py (or -f) 
	flag; for instance
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; &tool; mdl lmodel.dat -f="-DDBG" -f="-L/opt/local/lib" -f="-lmutils"</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	will add the options -DDBG, -L/opt/local/lib, and
	-lmutils to the f2py call.
	Use
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; $ASCDS_INSTALL/ots/bin/f2py -h</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	for more information on the flags supported by f2py.
      </PARA>
      <PARA title="What files are compiled?">
	The following files in the current working directory are
	compiled: *.f, *.f03, *.f90, *.c, *.cxx, *.C, and
	*.cc. Note that if C++ models - i.e. those with a
	C_ prefix in the model.dat file - cause the script
	to create a file called wrap_&lt;modulename&gt;.cxx,
	which is also compiled by f2py and then deleted
	(unless --keep is specified).
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Creating the python code">
	The script creates one Python file, __init__py, in the directory,
	which contains the classes for the models along with the
	code needed to "install" them into Sherpa (e.g. so that
	they are included in the output of list_models).
	The model class names are created by appending the
	model name from the definition file to the prefix
	value (which defaults to "XS"); since Python class
	names have to start with a capital letter the prefix
	must be capitalised (or, if blank, then the first
	character of the model name is capitalized).
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.10.1 (April 2018) release">
      <PARA>
        The include files have been updated to match XSPEC 12.9.1,
        which is the version used by CIAO 4.10.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.9.2 (April 2017) release">
      <PARA>
        The script should now work with XSPEC convolution models.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>
    
    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.9.1 (December 2016) release">
      <PARA>
	The script has been updated to work with CIAO 4.9 but has
	only seen very-limited testing. There is still no support
	for convolution models.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.2 (January 2016) release">
      <PARA title="Support for models with an initialization string">
	XSPEC models which use an initialization string, such as the
	<HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/xanadu/xspec/models/snapec.html">snapec model</HREF>
	can now be converted.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.8.1 (December 2015) release">
      <PARA>
	This script has not been updated to reflect changes made
	in Sherpa in this release. Please contact the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/helpdesk/">CXC HelpDesk</HREF>
	if you need to use this script.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Changes in the scripts 4.6.6 (September 2014) release">
      <PARA>
	The script is new in this release.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="Notes">
      <PARA>
	This script is not an official part of the CIAO release but is
	made available as "contributed" software via the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/">CIAO scripts page</HREF>.
	Please see the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/download/scripts/instructions.html">installation
	instructions page</HREF> for help on installing the package.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <BUGS>
      <PARA title="Support on El-Capitan and later">
	The security changes in OS-X El-Capitan mean that an
	additional step may be required, after running
	convert_xspec_user_model. If the tool reports a failure
	when trying to import the module (which it does to check
	that the build was a success) then try the following
	command (replacing lname with the first argument to the
	convert_xspec_user_model call):
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>&upr; install_name_tool `ls -1 name/*so` -change libcfitsio.2.dylib @rpath/../ots/lib/libcfitsio.2.dylib</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    <!--
    <BUGS>
      <PARA>
	See the
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/bugs/convert_xspec_user_model.html">bugs page
	for this script</HREF> on the CIAO website for an up-to-date
	listing of known bugs. 
      </PARA>
    </BUGS>
    -->

    <LASTMODIFIED>March 2018</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
